[{"title": "Basics", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What is COVID-19?", "answer": "COVID-19 is a disease caused by a virus called SARS-CoV-2. Most people with COVID-19 have mild symptoms, but some people can become severely ill. Although most people with COVID-19 get better within weeks of illness, some people experience post-COVID conditions. Post-COVID conditions\u00a0are a wide range of new, returning, or ongoing health problems people can experience\u00a0more than four weeks after first being infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Older people and those who have certain underlying medical conditions\u00a0are more likely to get severely ill from COVID-19. Vaccines\u00a0against COVID-19 are safe and effective."}, {"question": "Why is the disease being called coronavirus disease 2019, COVID-19?", "answer": "On February 11, 2020 the World Health Organization announced an official name for the disease that is causing the 2019 novel coronavirus pandemic, first identified in Wuhan China. The new name of this disease is coronavirus disease 2019, abbreviated as COVID-19. In COVID-19, \u201cCO\u201d stands for corona, \u201cVI\u201d for virus, and \u201dD\u201d for disease. Formerly, this disease was referred to as \u201c2019 novel coronavirus\u201d or \u201c2019-nCoV.\u201d"}]}, {"title": "Spread", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "How does the virus spread?", "answer": "COVID-19 is thought to spread mainly through close contact from person to person, including between people who are physically near each other (within about 6 feet). People who are infected but do not show symptoms can also spread the virus to others. Cases of reinfection with COVID-19 \u00a0have been reported but are rare. We are still learning about how the virus spreads and the severity of illness it causes.\nCOVID-19 spreads very easily from person to person. How easily a virus spreads from person to person can vary. The virus that causes COVID-19 appears to spread more efficiently than influenza but not as efficiently as measles, which is among the most contagious viruses known to affect people.\nFor more information about how COVID-19 spreads, visit the How COVID-19 Spreads\u00a0page to learn how COVID-19 spreads and how to protect yourself."}, {"question": "What is community spread?", "answer": "Community spread means people have been infected with the virus in an area, including some who are not sure how or where they became infected. Each health department determines community spread differently based on local conditions. For information on community spread in your area, please visit your local health department\u2019s website."}, {"question": "Can mosquitoes or ticks spread the virus that causes COVID-19?", "answer": "At this time, CDC has no data to suggest that this new coronavirus or other similar coronaviruses are spread by mosquitoes or ticks. The main way that COVID-19 spreads is from person to person. See How Coronavirus Spreads\u00a0for more information."}]}, {"title": "Prevention", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "How can I protect myself?", "answer": "Visit the How to Protect Yourself & Others\u00a0page to learn about how to protect yourself from respiratory illnesses, like COVID-19."}, {"question": "Does CDC recommend the use of masks to prevent COVID-19?", "answer": "Yes. CDC recommends that people wear masks in public settings, at events and gatherings, and anywhere they will be around other people. When you wear a mask, you protect others as well as yourself. Masks work best when everyone wears one. A mask is NOT a substitute for social distancing. Masks should still be worn in addition to staying at least 6 feet apart, especially when indoors around people who don\u2019t live in your household.\nEffective February 2, 2021, masks are required\u00a0on planes, buses, trains, and other forms of public transportation traveling into, within, or out of the United States and in U.S. transportation hubs such as airports and stations.\nWhile masks are strongly encouraged to reduce the spread of COVID-19, CDC recognizes there are specific instances when wearing a mask may not be feasible. In these instances, adaptations and alternatives\u00a0should be considered whenever possible.\nMore information about masks can be found on our masks site.\n\nYour Guide to Masks\nHow to Wear\nHow to Store and Wash\nImprove How Your Mask Protects You\nTypes of Masks\nGuidance for Wearing Masks\nImprove Fit and Filtration of Your Mask"}, {"question": "Is it safe to get care for my other medical conditions during this time?", "answer": "Continue taking care of your health and wellness\n\n\nContinue your medications,\u00a0and do not change your treatment plan without talking to your healthcare provider.\nContinue to manage your disease\u00a0the way your healthcare provider has told you.\nHave at least a 2-week supply\u00a0of all prescription and non-prescription medications.\nTalk to your healthcare provider about whether your vaccinations and other preventative services are up to date.\nCall your healthcare provider\n\nif you have any concerns\u00a0about your medical conditions, or if you get sick.\nto find out about different ways you can connect with your healthcare provider for chronic disease management or other conditions.\n\nIf you must visit in-person, protect yourself and others.\n\n\n\n\nDo not delay getting emergency care for your health problems or\u00a0any underlying medical\u00a0condition that requires immediate attention.\n\nIf you need emergency help, call 911.\nEmergency departments have infection prevention plans to protect you from getting COVID-19 if you need care for your medical condition.\n\n\nContinue to practice everyday prevention. Wash your hands often, avoid close contact, wear a mask, cover coughs and sneezes, and clean frequently touched surfaces often.\n\n\nWhen picking up medicines, use drive-thru windows, curbside services (prescriptions brought to you in your car), mail-order, or other delivery services.\n\nFor more information, see Groups at Higher Risk for Severe Illness."}, {"question": "Am I at risk for COVID-19 from mail, packages, or products?", "answer": "Coronaviruses are thought to be spread most often by respiratory droplets. Although the virus can survive for a short period on some surfaces, it is unlikely to be spread from domestic or international mail, products, or packaging. However, it may be possible that people can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads.\nLearn more about safe handling of deliveries and mail."}, {"question": "Is it okay for me to donate blood?", "answer": "In healthcare settings across the United States, donated blood is a lifesaving, essential part of caring for patients. The need for donated blood is constant, and blood centers are open and in urgent need of donations. CDC encourages people who are well to continue to donate blood if they are able, even if they are practicing social distancing because of COVID-19. CDC is supporting blood centers by providing recommendations that will keep donors and staff safe. Examples of these recommendations include spacing donor chairs 6 feet apart, thoroughly adhering to environmental cleaning practices, and encouraging donors to make donation appointments ahead of time."}, {"question": "Should contact lens wearers take special precautions to prevent COVID-19?", "answer": "Currently, there is no evidence to suggest contact lens wearers are more at risk for acquiring COVID-19 than eyeglass wearers.\nContact lens wearers should continue to\u00a0practice safe contact lens wear and care hygiene habits\u00a0to help prevent against transmission of any contact lens-related infections, such as always washing hands with soap and water before handling lenses.\nPeople who are healthy can continue to wear and care for their contact lenses as prescribed by their eye care professional.\n\nFind more information about\u00a0how coronavirus spreads and how to protect yourself.\nVisit\u00a0CDC\u2019s contact lens website\u00a0for more information on healthy contact lens wear and care."}, {"question": "Is contact lens disinfecting solution effective against COVID-19?", "answer": "Hydrogen peroxide-based systems\u00a0for cleaning, disinfecting, and storing contact lenses should be effective against the virus that causes COVID-19.\n\nFor other disinfection methods, such as multipurpose solution and ultrasonic cleaners, there is currently not enough scientific evidence to determine efficacy against the virus.\n\n\nAlways use solution\u00a0to disinfect your contact lenses and case to kill germs that may be present.\nHandle your lenses over a surface that has been cleaned and disinfected.\n\nFind more information about\u00a0how coronavirus spreads and how to protect yourself.\nVisit\u00a0CDC\u2019s contact lens website\u00a0for more information on healthy contact lens wear and care."}, {"question": "Should I use soap and water or hand sanitizer to protect against COVID-19?", "answer": "Handwashing is one of the best ways to protect yourself and your family from getting sick. Wash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, especially after blowing your nose, coughing, or sneezing; going to the bathroom; and before eating or preparing food. If soap and water are not readily available, use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol."}, {"question": "What cleaning products should I use to protect against COVID-19?", "answer": "Clean frequently touched surfaces such as tables, doorknobs, light switches, countertops, handles, desks, phones, keyboards, toilets, faucets, and sinks. Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. You may choose to also disinfect depending on\u00a0certain conditions\u00a0or everyday practices required by your home. To disinfect, most common Environmental Protection Agency-registered household disinfect ants will work. See CDC\u2019s recommendations for household cleaning and disinfection."}]}, {"title": "If You or Someone You Know is Sick or Had Contact with Someone who Has COVID-19", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What should I do if I get sick or someone in my house gets sick?", "answer": "Most people who get COVID-19 will be able to recover at home. /coronavirus/2019-ncov/if-you-are-sick/index.html\u00a0for people who are recovering at home and their caregivers, including:\n\nStay home when you are sick, except to get medical care.https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/guidance-prevent-spread.htmlCDC has directions\nIf you have COVID-19, tell your close contacts\u00a0so that they can quarantine at home and get tested.\nUse a separate room and bathroom for sick household members (if possible).\nThe person who is sick should isolate. Learn when and how to isolate.\nWash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, especially after blowing your nose, coughing, or sneezing; going to the bathroom; and before eating or preparing food.\nIf soap and water are not readily available, use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol. Always wash hands with soap and water if hands are visibly dirty.\nThe person who is sick should wear a\u00a0mask\u00a0when they are around other people at home. They do not need to wear a mask if they are alone.\nClean the sick room and bathroom, as needed, to avoid unnecessary contact with the sick person.\n\nHowever, some people may need emergency medical attention. Watch for symptoms and learn when to seek emergency medical attention.\nCall 911 or call ahead to your local emergency facility:\u00a0Notify the operator that you are seeking care for someone who has or may have COVID-19."}, {"question": "What should I do if I have had close contact with someone who has COVID-19?", "answer": "The best way to protect yourself and others is to quarantine by staying home for 14 days if you think you\u2019ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department\u2019s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period.\nBe alert for symptoms\u00a0of COVID-19.\nIf possible, stay away from others, especially people who are at higher risk for getting very sick from COVID-19.\nYou may NOT need to quarantine if:\n\nYou have been fully vaccinated\u00a0and have no symptoms\nYou were previously diagnosed with COVID-19\u00a0within the last three months and don\u2019t develop any new symptoms"}]}, {"title": "Children", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What is the risk of my child becoming sick with COVID-19?", "answer": "Children can be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 and can get sick with COVID-19. Most children with COVID-19 have mild symptoms or they may have no symptoms at all (\u201casymptomatic\u201d). Fewer children have been sick with COVID-19 compared to adults. Babies younger than 1 and children with certain underlying medical conditions may be more likely to have serious illness from COVID-19. Some children have developed a rare but serious disease that is linked to COVID-19 called multisystem inflammatory syndrome (MIS-C).\nFor more information for parents or caregivers of children, see Children and Teens and the COVID-19 Parental Resources Kit.\nFor more information about how people get sick with the virus that causes COVID-19, see How COVID-19 Spreads."}, {"question": "Should children wear masks?", "answer": "In general, children 2 years and older should wear a mask. However, CDC recognizes that wearing masks may not be possible in every situation or for some people. Appropriate and consistent use of masks may be challenging for some children, such as children with certain disabilities, including cognitive, intellectual, developmental, sensory and behavioral disorders. Learn more about what you should do if your child or you cannot wear masks in certain situations and special considerations for children who may have difficulties with techniques for improved fit and filtration."}, {"question": "What is multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C)?", "answer": "Multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) is a serious condition associated with COVID-19 where different body parts can become inflamed, including the heart, lungs, kidneys, brain, skin, eyes, or gastrointestinal organs. For information, see MIS-C."}, {"question": "Can my child spend time with older adults and people with chronic medical conditions?", "answer": "Older adults and people who have certain underlying medical conditions are at increased risk for getting severely ill from COVID-19. To protect those who are at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19, you may consider taking these extra precautions.\n\nSeparate your child from others in your household who have an increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19.\nCarefully consider who might be best to provide childcare if you are unable to care for your child (for example, you are not able to stay with your child while childcare or school is closed).\nLimit your child\u2019s contact with other people if someone at higher risk for COVID-19 will be providing care (such as an older adult or someone with an underlying medical condition).\nPostpone visits or trips to see grandparents, older family members and family members who are at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19. Consider connecting virtually or by writing letters."}, {"question": "My child has an underlying medical condition. What additional steps should my family take?", "answer": "Children with underlying medical conditions\u00a0are at increased risk for severe illness compared to children without underlying medical conditions. Current evidence on which underlying medical conditions in children are associated with increased risk is limited. Children with the following conditions might be at increased risk for severe illness: obesity, medical complexity, severe genetic disorders, severe neurologic disorders, inherited metabolic disorders, sickle cell disease, congenital (since birth) heart disease, diabetes, chronic kidney disease, asthma and other chronic lung disease, and immunosuppression due to malignancy or immune-weakening medications. In addition to following the recommendations to prevent getting sick, families can take steps recommended for children with underlying conditions.\n\nConsider identifying potential alternative caregivers, in case you or other regular caregivers become sick and are unable to care for your child. If possible, these alternative caregivers should not be at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19. For more information, see Sick Parents and Caregivers. Make sure these caregivers take extra precautions if your child has a disability.\nIf your child receives any support care services in the home, such as services from personal care attendants, direct support professionals, or therapists, make plans for what you will do if your child\u2019s direct care providers or anyone in your family gets sick. You can review CDC\u2019s recommendations for Direct Service Providers.\n\nFor more information, see Children and Teens and Others who Need Extra Precautions."}, {"question": "Should my infant or child be tested for COVID-19?", "answer": "Not everyone needs to be tested. Your infant or child may need to be tested for COVID-19 if your child:\n\nHas symptoms of COVID-19, or\nHad close contact\u00a0(within 6 feet of an infected person for a cumulative total of 15 minutes or more over a 24-hour period) with someone who tested positive for COVID-19, or\nTook part in activities that put them at higher risk for COVID-19, because they could not stay at least 6 feet apart as needed (such as travel, attending large social or mass gatherings, or being in a crowded or poorly ventilated indoor setting), or\nWas asked or referred to get testing by their state, tribal, localexternal icon, or territorial health department\u00a0or healthcare provider.\n\nIf your child is tested because they have COVID-19 symptoms or have been in close contact with someone with COVID-19,\u00a0keep your child home until they can safely end isolation\u00a0or quarantine and follow the advice of your healthcare provider or a public health professional. If your child has recovered from COVID-19 in the past 3 months\u00a0and does not have symptoms of COVID-19, they do not need to be retested for up to 3 months from their last positive test result."}]}, {"title": "Symptoms & Emergency Warning Signs", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What are the symptoms and complications that COVID-19 can cause?", "answer": "People with COVID-19 have reported a wide range of symptoms \u2013 from mild symptoms to severe illness. Symptoms may appear 2-14 days after exposure to the virus. If you have fever, cough, or other symptoms, you might have COVID-19."}, {"question": "When should I seek emergency care if I have COVID-19?", "answer": "Look for emergency warning signs* for COVID-19. If someone is showing any of these signs, seek emergency medical care immediately\n\nTrouble breathing\nPersistent pain or pressure in the chest\nNew confusion\nInability to wake or stay awake\nPale, gray, or blue-colored skin, lips, or nail beds, depending on skin tone\n\n*This list is not all possible symptoms. Please call your medical provider for any other symptoms that are severe or concerning to you.\nCall 911 or call ahead to your local emergency facility: Notify the operator that you are seeking care for someone who has or may have COVID-19."}, {"question": "Is it possible to have the flu and COVID-19 at the same time?", "answer": "Yes. It is possible to test positive for flu (as well as other respiratory infections) and COVID-19 at the same time. Because some of the symptoms of flu and COVID-19 are similar, it may be hard to tell the difference between them based on symptoms alone. Testing may be needed to help confirm a diagnosis.\nThe best way to prevent seasonal flu is to get vaccinated every year. Flu vaccines will not prevent COVID-19, but they will reduce your chances of getting flu. See Prevent Seasonal Flu\u00a0for more information."}]}, {"title": "Testing", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Is at-home specimen collection or testing available?", "answer": "Yes. At-home testing and collection allow you to collect a specimen at home and either send it to a testing facility or preform the test at home.\nYou and your healthcare provider might consider either an at-home collection kit or an at-home test if you have signs and symptoms of COVID-19 or if you can\u2019t get testing at a local healthcare facility.\nFor more information, see At-Home Testing."}, {"question": "Should I be tested for a current infection?", "answer": "The following should be tested for current infection:\n\nPeople who have symptoms\u00a0of COVID-19.\nMost people who have had close contact\u00a0(within 6 feet for a total of 15 minutes or more over a 24-hour period) with someone with confirmed COVID-19.\n\nFully vaccinated people with no COVID-19 symptoms do not need to be tested following an exposure to someone with COVID-19.\nPeople who have tested positive for COVID-19 within the past 3 months and recovered do not need to get tested following an exposure as long as they do not develop new symptoms.\n\n\nPeople who have taken part in activities that put them at higher risk for COVID-19 because they cannot physically distance as needed to avoid exposure such as travel, attending large social or mass gatherings, or being in crowded or poorly-ventilated indoor settings.\nPeople who have been asked or referred to get tested by their healthcare provider, or state, tribal, localexternal icon, or territorial health department.\n\nCDC recommends that anyone with any signs or symptoms of COVID-19\u00a0get tested, regardless of vaccination status or prior infection.\u00a0 If you get tested because you have symptoms or were potentially exposed to the virus, you should stay away from others pending test results and follow the advice of your health care provider or a public health professional."}, {"question": "How can I get tested for a current infection (viral test) and what does my test mean?", "answer": "A viral test checks specimens from your nose or your mouth\u00a0 to find out if you are currently infected with SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19.\nContact your healthcare provider or visit your state, tribal, localexternal icon, and territorial health department\u2019s website to find the latest local information on\u00a0testing. The type of viral COVID-19\u00a0tests offered\u00a0differ by location. You and your healthcare provider might also consider either an at-home collection kit\u00a0or an\u00a0at-home test if you have signs and symptoms of COVID-19 and if you are not able to be tested by a healthcare provider or public health official.\nWhile waiting for test results pdf icon[2 pages, 224KB], you should self-quarantine at home and stay away\u00a0from others, including those living in your household. If your test results are positive, isolate yourself. If you have symptoms of COVID-19 or you have been in close contact with someone with COVID-19 and are not tested, it is still important to stay home.\u00a0 For more information, visit What to Do if You Are Sick and When to Quarantine."}, {"question": "How can I get tested for a past infection (antibody test) and what does my test mean?", "answer": "Antibody tests for COVID-19 are available through healthcare providers and laboratories. Check with your healthcare provider to see if they offer antibody tests and whether you should get one.\nA positive test result shows you might have antibodies from an infection with the virus that causes COVID-19. However, there is a chance a positive result means that you have antibodies from an infection with a virus from the same family of viruses (called coronaviruses), such as the one that causes the common cold.\nHaving antibodies to the virus that causes COVID-19 might provide some protection from getting infected with the virus again. If it does, we do not know how much protection the antibodies might provide or how long this protection might last. Confirmed and suspected cases of reinfection have been reported, but remain rare.\nYou should continue to protect yourself and others\u00a0since you could get infected with the virus again.\nIf you test negative, you might not have ever had COVID-19. Talk with your healthcare provider about your test result and the type of test you took to understand what your result means.\nRegardless of whether you test positive or negative, the results do not confirm whether or not you are able to spread the virus that causes COVID-19. Until we know more, continue to take steps to protect yourself and others.\nIf you want more information about antibody tests, see Test for Past Infection."}, {"question": "Can someone test negative and later test positive on a viral test for COVID-19?", "answer": "Yes, it is possible. You may test negative if the sample was collected early in your infection and test positive later during this illness. You could also be exposed to COVID-19 after the test and get infected then. Even if you test negative, you still should take steps to\u202fprotect yourself and others. See Testing for Current Infection for more information."}]}, {"title": "People at Higher Risk for Severe Illness", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Who is at increased risk for developing severe illness from COVID-19?", "answer": "People at increased risk include:\n\nOlder adults\nPeople of all ages with certain underlying medical conditions\n\nPregnant and recently pregnant people\u202fare also at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19.\nLong-standing systemic health and social inequities have put many people from racial and ethnic minority groups\u00a0at increased risk of getting sick and dying from COVID-19.\nIn addition to those at increased risk, there are certain groups of people who require extra precautions during the pandemic."}, {"question": "Are there any medications I should avoid taking if I have COVID-19?", "answer": "Currently, there is no evidence to suggest that taking any specific medications, like blood pressure medication or ibuprofen, leads to more severe illness from COVID-19.\n\nContinue to take your medications and to follow your treatment plan as prescribed by your healthcare provider. Any changes to your medications should only be made after talking with your healthcare provider.\nContact your healthcare provider if you have questions or concerns.\n\nFor more information, see People with Underlying Medical Conditions."}, {"question": "Are people with disabilities at higher risk?", "answer": "Adults with disabilities are more likely to have an underlying medical condition\u00a0that may put them at increased risk of severe illness from COVID-19 including, but not limited to, heart disease, stroke, diabetes, chronic kidney disease, cancer, high blood pressure, and obesity. In addition, having a disability may make it harder to practice social distancing, wear a mask, and practice hand hygiene.\nFor more information, see People with Disabilities and People who May Need Extra Precautions."}]}, {"title": "People with Seasonal Allergies", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What is the difference between COVID-19 and seasonal allergies?", "answer": "COVID-19 is a contagious respiratory illness caused by infection with a new coronavirus (called SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19). Seasonal allergies triggered by airborne pollen can lead to seasonal allergic rhinitis, which affects the nose and sinuses, and seasonal allergic conjunctivitis, which affects the eyes.\nCOVID-19 and seasonal allergies share many symptoms, but there are some key differences between the two. For example, COVID-19 can cause fever, which is not a common symptom of seasonal allergies. The image below compares symptoms caused by allergies and COVID-19.\nBecause some of the symptoms of COVID-19 and seasonal allergies are similar, it may be difficult to tell the difference between them, and you may need to get a test to confirm your diagnosis\n\n508 version\n*Seasonal allergies do not usually cause shortness of breath or difficulty breathing, unless a person has a respiratory condition such as asthma that can be triggered by exposure to pollen.\nThis is not a complete list of all possible symptoms of COVID-19 or seasonal allergies. Symptoms vary from person to person and range from mild to severe. You can have symptoms of both COVID-19 and seasonal allergies at the same time.\nIf you think you have COVID-19, follow CDC\u2019s guidance on\u00a0\u201dWhat to do if you are sick.\u201d\u00a0If you have\u00a0an emergency warning sign\u00a0(including trouble breathing), seek emergency medical care immediately.\nGet more information on\u00a0COVID-19 symptoms, or more information on seasonal allergy symptomsexternal icon."}, {"question": "Does having seasonal allergies increase my risk of contracting COVID-19 or having more severe symptoms if I do contract COVID-19?", "answer": "There is not enough scientific information at this time to know whether having seasonal allergies puts you at higher risk of contracting COVID-19 or having more severe symptoms if you do contract COVID-19. We do know that older adults and people who have severe underlying medical conditions like obesity, diabetes, or heart or lung disease are at higher risk for developing more serious complications when they have COVID-19. Get more information on people at high risk for severe COVID-19."}, {"question": "Will I be protected from seasonal allergies if I wear a mask?", "answer": "CDC recommends wearing\u00a0masks\u00a0to slow the spread of COVID-19. Everyone should wear a mask covering unless they are under 2 years of age, have breathing problems, or are unconscious or incapacitated and would need assistance removing a mask.\u00a0 Masks also offer some protection against seasonal allergies because they can prevent some larger particles from being inhaled. However, if you have seasonal allergies, masks should not be your only protection against pollen exposure because smaller particles can still get through the covering and be inhaled.\nWash your masks after each use, particularly if you suffer from seasonal allergies, because the covering may carry particles such as pollen. See information on how to\u00a0wash masks."}, {"question": "How can I protect myself from seasonal allergies?", "answer": "The best way to protect yourself against seasonal allergies is to reduce your exposure to pollen. During high pollen days:\n\nLimit your time outdoors and seek indoor spaces with clean air.\nCreate a cleaner air space at home to protect yourself from outdoor air irritants during the COVID-19 pandemic. Use a portable air cleaner in one or more rooms. Portable air cleaners work best when run continuously with doors and windows closed.\u00a0Do-it-yourself box fan\u00a0filtration units are a low-cost filtration alternative, but they should never be left unattended.\nKeep your cleaner air space a comfortable temperature by using air conditioners, heat pumps, fans, and window shades.\nIf you have a forced air system in your home, consult a qualified heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) professional about different filters (HEPA or MERV-13 or higher) and settings (\u201cRecirculate\u201d and \u201cOn\u201d rather than \u201cAuto\u201d) that can be used to reduce indoor air irritants.\nIf outdoors, avoid activities that stir up pollen, such as mowing lawns or raking leaves. When you return indoors, take a shower and change your clothes.\n\nThe EPA website on indoor air and COVID-19external icon and the EPA Guide to Air Cleaners in the Home pdf icon[7 pages, 2.93mb]external icon\u00a0provide additional information on improving indoor air quality. You can also find out the daily pollen levels in your area by checking local weather forecasts and pollen counting stationsexternal icon. Learn more about\u00a0reducing your exposure to respiratory triggers."}]}, {"title": "Contact Tracing", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What is contact tracing?", "answer": "Contact tracing has been used for decades by state and local health departments to slow or stop the spread of infectious diseases.\nContact tracing slows the spread of COVID-19 by\n\nLetting people know they may have been exposed to COVID-19 and should monitor their health for signs and symptoms of COVID-19\nHelping people who may have been exposed to COVID-19 get tested\nAsking people to self-isolate if they have COVID-19 or self-quarantine if they are a close contact of someone with COVID-19\n\nDuring contact tracing, the health department staff will not ask you for\n\nMoney\nSocial Security number\nBank account information\nSalary information\nCredit card numbers"}, {"question": "What will happen with my personal information during contact tracing?", "answer": "Discussions with health department staff are confidential. This means that your personal and medical information will be kept private and only shared with those who may need to know, like your health care provider.\nIf you have been diagnosed with COVID-19, your name will not be shared with those you came in contact with. The health department will only notify people you were in close contact with that they might have been exposed to COVID-19. Each state and jurisdiction use their own method for collecting and protecting health information. To learn more, contact your state or local health department.\nYou may also be interested in: If I participate contact tracing for COVID-19 using a digital tool, is my personal health information secure?"}, {"question": "Who is considered a close contact of someone with COVID-19?", "answer": "For COVID-19, a\u00a0close contact\u00a0is anyone who was within 6 feet of an infected person for a total of 15 minutes or more over a 24-hour period (for example, three individual 5-minute exposures for a total of 15 minutes). An infected person can spread COVID-19 starting from 2 days before they have any symptoms (or, if they are asymptomatic, 2 days before their specimen that tested positive was collected), until they meet the criteria for\u00a0discontinuing home isolation.\nYou may also be interested in: What should I do if I have had close contact with someone who has COVID-19?"}, {"question": "I have COVID-19. How do I tell the people I was around?", "answer": "If you have COVID-19, tell your close contacts pdf icon[93 KB, 2 Pages]\u00a0you have COVID-19 so that they can quarantine at home and get tested. By letting your close contacts\u00a0know they may have been exposed to COVID-19, you are helping to protect them and others within your community.\nYou can call, text, or email your contacts. If you would like to stay anonymous, there is also an online tool that allows you to tell your contacts by sending out emails or text notifications anonymously (www.tellyourcontacts.orgexternal icon)."}, {"question": "Does mask use help determine if someone is considered a close contact?", "answer": "A person is still considered a close contact even if one or both people wore a mask when they were together.\nMasks work best when everyone wears one. However,\u00a0masks\u00a0are not 100% effective at preventing spread of COVID-19, and the\u00a0type of masks used and whether or not they are used consistently and correctly varies throughout the general population. Therefore, mask use is not considered when determining whether someone is a close contact during case investigation and contact tracing."}, {"question": "If I am a close contact, will I be tested for COVID-19?", "answer": "If you have been in close contact with someone who has COVID-19, you should be tested, even if you do not have symptoms of COVID-19. The health department may be able to provide resources for testing in your area.\n\nWhile you are waiting for your COVID-19 test result, stay home away from others (self-quarantine) and monitor your health for symptoms of COVID-19 to protect your friends, family, and others from possibly getting COVID-19.\nIf your test is positive, you should continue to stay home and self-isolate away from others and monitor your health. If you have symptoms of COVID-19 and they worsen or become severe, you should seek emergency medical care. Severe symptoms include trouble breathing, persistent pain or pressure in the chest, confusion, inability to wake or stay awake, or pale, gray, or blue-colored skin, lips, or nail beds, depending on skin tone. Someone from the health department may call you to\n\nCheck on your health,\nDiscuss who you have been around, and\nAsk where you have spent time while you may have been able to spread COVID-19 to others.\n\n\nThe best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you\u2019ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department\u2019s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period.\nIf your test is negative and you don\u2019t have symptoms, you should continue to stay home and self-quarantine away from others for 14 days after your last exposure to COVID-19 and follow all recommendations from the health department. This is important because symptoms can appear up to 14 days after you\u2019ve been exposed and are infected. A negative result before the end of your quarantine period does not rule out possible infection. Additionally, you do not need a repeat test unless you develop symptoms, or if you require a test to return to work.\nIf your\u00a0test is negative\u00a0and you\u00a0have symptoms,\u00a0you should continue to self-quarantine away from others for 14 days after your last exposure to COVID-19 and follow all recommendations from the health department. Additional medical consultation and a second test may be needed if your symptoms do not improve."}, {"question": "What will happen during contact tracing if I am diagnosed with COVID-19?", "answer": "If you are diagnosed with COVID-19, someone from the health department may call you to check on your health, discuss who you have been around, and ask where you spent time while you may have been able to spread COVID-19 to others. You will also be asked to continue to stay at home and self-isolate, away from others.\n\nYour name will not be shared with those you came in contact with.\nThe health department staff will not ask you for\n\nMoney\nSocial Security number\nBank account information\nSalary information, or\nCredit card numbers\n\n\nSelf-isolation means staying at home in a specific room away from other people and pets, and using a separate bathroom, if possible.\nSelf-isolation helps slow the spread of COVID-19 and can help protect the health of your family, friends, neighbors, and others you may come in contact.\nIf you need support or assistance while in self-isolation, your health department or community organizations may be able to provide assistance.\n\nWatch for or monitor your symptoms of COVID-19. If your symptoms worsen or become severe, you should seek medical care."}, {"question": "What will happen during contact tracing if I have been around someone with COVID-19?", "answer": "If you were around someone who has been diagnosed with COVID-19, someone from the health department may call you to let you know that you may have been exposed to COVID-19.\nThe best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you\u2019ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department\u2019s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period. Health department staff will help identify the dates for your self-quarantine. Health department staff can also provide resources for COVID-19 testing in your area.\n\nSelf-quarantine means staying home away from others and monitoring your health.\nIf you need to be around other people or animals in or outside of the home, wear a mask. This will help protect the people around you.\nIf you need support or assistance while in self-quarantine, your health department or community organizations may be able to provide assistance.\n\nMonitor your health and watch for symptoms of COVID-19. Remember, symptoms may appear 2-14 days after you were exposed to COVID-19. Tell the health department if you develop any symptoms. Tell people you were around recently if you become ill, so they can monitor their health. If your symptoms worsen or become severe, seek medical care. Severe symptoms include trouble breathing, persistent pain or pressure in the chest, new confusion, inability to wake or stay awake, or pale, gray, or blue-colored skin, lips, or nail beds, depending on skin tone.\nThe health department staff will not ask you for\n\nMoney\nSocial Security number\nBank account information\nSalary information, or\nCredit card numbers"}, {"question": "I was around someone who has COVID-19, and my COVID-19 test came back negative. Do I still need to quarantine for 14 days after I was last exposed?", "answer": "Yes. You should still self-quarantine for 14 days since your last exposure. It can take up to 14 days after exposure to the virus for a person to develop COVID-19 symptoms. A negative result before end of the 14-day quarantine period does not rule out possible infection. By self-quarantining for 14 days, you lower the chance of possibly exposing others to COVID-19. The best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you\u2019ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department\u2019s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period."}, {"question": "I was recently around someone who has COVID-19, but I feel fine. Why should I stay at home?", "answer": "People with COVID-19 can still spread the virus even if they don\u2019t have any symptoms. If you were around someone who had COVID-19, it is critical that you stay home and away from others for 14 days from the last day that you were around that person. Staying home and away from others at all times helps your health department in the fight against COVID-19 and helps protect you, your family, and your community. The best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you\u2019ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department\u2019s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period."}, {"question": "What if I have been around someone who was identified as a close contact?", "answer": "The best way to protect yourself and others is to quarantine by staying home for 14 days if you think you\u2019ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department\u2019s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period.\nBe alert for symptoms\u00a0of COVID-19.\nIf possible, stay away from others, especially people who are at higher risk for getting very sick from COVID-19.\nYou may NOT need to quarantine if:\n\nYou have been fully vaccinated and have no symptoms\nYou were previously diagnosed with COVID-19 within the last three months and don\u2019t develop any new symptoms"}, {"question": "Will there be a national app for contact tracing?", "answer": "No, there will not be a national app for contact tracing. There are many options available now, and it is up to each state and individual to decide which tools best fit their needs."}, {"question": "If I participate in contact tracing for COVID-19 using a digital tool, is my personal health information secure?", "answer": "Yes, if you agree to participate in contact tracing for COVID-19 with the health department, your information is secure.\nDiscussions with health department staff are confidential. This means that your personal and medical information will be kept private and only shared with those who may need to know, like your health care provider. Your name will not be shared with those you came in contact with. If you have been diagnosed with COVID-19, the health department will only notify people you were in close contact with that they might have been exposed to COVID-19.\nHealth departments may use case management tools to help make the contact tracing process more efficient. If you choose to provide information through one of these tools, your information is secure and stored with the health department. These tools also help health departments quickly receive and analyze information about COVID-19. Case management tools are under the same laws and regulations for all sensitive health information use (e.g. HIPPA). You must provide consent for the health department to collect information using a case management tool. Just like traditional contact tracing, digital tools will not collect information regarding money, Social Security numbers, bank account information, salary information, or credit card numbers.\nExposure notification tools may be an app that you can download on your personal cell phone. If you choose to download an exposure notification app for COVID-19, your information is secure. Exposure notification apps are developed in collaboration with or endorsed by health departments. These apps undergo rigorous testing to determine their trustworthiness, security, and ability to protect people\u2019s privacy. Until you give consent to share information with your local health department, any information you have entered into the app is stored only on your personal phone. Your information is stored only on your own phone and is not sent to the health department or any other third party. The app and your information can be deleted any time. When you consent to share your information with the local health department, your information is secure."}, {"question": "Will I be required to download a contact tracing app for COVID-19 on my phone?", "answer": "No, you are not required to download an app to give information for contact tracing for COVID-19. Health departments commonly use case management tools to make the contact tracing process more efficient. These types of tools are not downloaded on personal cell phones.\nIf you choose to give information to your local or state health department for contact tracing for COVID-19, you do not need to download an app on your cell phone. The health department staff may call you to\n\nCheck on your health,\nDiscuss who you have been around, and\nAsk where you have spent time while you may have been able to spread COVID-19 to others.\n\nIt is up to you to decide if you download an exposure notification app for COVID-19."}]}, {"title": "Funerals", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Am I at risk if I go to a funeral or visitation service for someone who died of COVID-19?", "answer": "There is currently no known risk associated with being in the same room at a funeral or visitation service with the body of someone who died of COVID-19. However, you may be at risk of getting COVID-19 if you attend a funeral where there are multiple people congregating. For more information about what you can do to help protect yourself and others from COVID-19 during these services, and to help cope with the loss of a loved one, see Funeral Guidance."}, {"question": "What should loved ones know about handling belongings and the body of someone who died from COVID-19?", "answer": "The virus that causes COVID-19 is thought to spread\u00a0from close contact (i.e., within about 6 feet) with a person who is infected with the virus. The virus spreads primarily through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs, sneezes, or talks.\nThis type of spread is not a concern after death. It may be possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads. If the deceased person had confirmed or suspected COVID-19, avoid kissing, washing, or shrouding the body before, during, and after the body has been prepared, if possible. For more information on recommended precautions while handling the belongings and the body of someone who died from COVID-19, see Funeral Guidance."}]}, {"title": "Cleaning and Disinfection", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Do disinfectants kill new strains of COVID-19?", "answer": "CDC, in collaboration with\u00a0EPAexternal icon, expects all products on\u00a0List N: Disinfectants for Coronavirus (COVID-19)external icon\u00a0to kill all strains of\u00a0SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19.\nGenetic mutations to COVID-19 do not impact the effectiveness of disinfectants. Destroying a virus is dependent on its physical properties, and recent genetic changes have not changed the basic physical properties of the virus that causes COVID-19.\u200b\nLearn more about cleaning and disinfection recommendations for\u00a0facilities\u00a0and\u00a0homes."}, {"question": "Do car seats and booster seats need extra cleaning and disinfection to prevent spread of COVID-19? If so, how should car seats and booster seats be cleaned and disinfected?", "answer": "It may be possible that people can get COVID-19 by\u00a0touching a surface or object that has the virus on it\u00a0and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this isn\u2019t thought to be the main way the virus spreads. Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. You may choose to also disinfect depending on\u00a0certain conditions or everyday practices required by your home. Washing hands frequently or using hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol also prevent the spread of COVID-19.\nSome cleaning and disinfectexternal icon\u00a0products are not recommended for use on car seats and booster seats. Owners should follow the manufacturer\u2019s cleaning instructions for their car seats and booster seats."}, {"question": "What is the difference between cleaning and disinfecting?", "answer": "Cleaning\u00a0with soap and water or a detergent removes germs, dirt, and impurities from surfaces. It lowers the risk of spreading\u00a0infection.\u00a0Disinfecting with a household disinfectant on List N: Disinfectants for Coronavirus (COVID-19)external icon\u00a0kills germs on the surface. By disinfecting or killing germs on a surface after cleaning the surface, it can further lower the risk of spreading infection. For more information review cleaning and disinfection recommendations for facilities and homes."}, {"question": "Is it safe to vacuum in a school, business, or community facility after someone with COVID-19 was there?", "answer": "The risk of spreading COVID-19 during vacuuming is unknown. At this time, there are no reported cases of COVID-19 associated with vacuuming.\n\nAfter cleaning:\n\nUse a vacuum equipped with a high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter and bags, if available.\nDo not vacuum a room or space that has people in it. Wait until the room or space is empty to vacuum, such as at night, for common spaces, or during the day for private rooms.\nWhile vacuuming, temporarily turn off in-room, window-mounted, or on-wall recirculation HVAC to avoid contamination of the HVAC units.\nDo NOT deactivate central HVAC systems. These systems tend to provide better filtration capabilities and introduce outdoor air into the areas that they serve."}, {"question": "How effective are alternative disinfection methods, such as ultrasonic waves, high intensity UV radiation, and LED blue light?", "answer": "The efficacy of these disinfection methods against the virus that causes COVID-19 is not known. EPA only recommends use of the\u00a0surface disinfectants identified on List Nexternal icon against the virus that causes COVID-19. EPA does not routinely review the safety or efficacy of pesticidal devices, such as UV lights, LED lights, or ultrasonic devices. However, CDC is producing guidance on use of Germicidal ultraviolet as an alternative disinfection method. Therefore, EPA cannot confirm whether, or under what circumstances, such products might be effective against the spread of COVID-19. For more information on CDC\u2019s recommendations for primary surface disinfection in occupied environments please visit the CDC/EPA guidance for surface disinfection."}, {"question": "Can sanitizing tunnels be used at facility entrances or exits to prevent the spread of COVID-19?", "answer": "CDC does not recommend the use of sanitizing tunnels. There is no evidence that they are effective in reducing the spread of COVID-19. In addition, chemicals used in sanitizing tunnels could cause skin, eye, or respiratory irritation or damage."}, {"question": "Should sidewalks, roads, and other outdoor spaces be disinfected to prevent the spread of COVID-19?", "answer": "CDC does not recommend disinfection of sidewalks, roads, or most other outdoor spaces. Spraying disinfectant on sidewalks, roads, and other outdoor spaces is not an efficient use of disinfectant supplies and has not been proven to reduce the risk of COVID-19 to the public. The risk of spreading the virus that causes COVID-19 from these surfaces is very low and disinfection is not effective on these surfaces."}]}, {"title": "Pets and Animals", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Can I get COVID-19 from my pets or other animals?", "answer": "Based on the available information to date, the risk of animals spreading COVID-19 to people is considered to be low. See If You Have Pets\u00a0for more information about pets and COVID-19.\nHowever, since animals can spread other diseases to people, it\u2019s always a good idea to practice\u00a0healthy habits\u00a0around pets and other animals, such as washing your hands and maintaining good hygiene. For more information on the many benefits of pet ownership, as well as staying safe and healthy around animals including pets, livestock, and wildlife, visit CDC\u2019s\u00a0Healthy Pets, Healthy People website."}, {"question": "Can animals carry the virus that causes COVID-19 on their skin or fur?", "answer": "Although we know certain bacteria and fungi can be carried on fur and hair, there is no evidence that viruses, including the virus that causes COVID-19, can spread to people from the skin, fur, or hair of pets.\nHowever, because animals can sometimes carry other germs that can make people sick, it\u2019s always a good idea to practice healthy habits around pets and other animals, including washing hands before and after interacting with them."}, {"question": "Can I use hand sanitizer on pets?", "answer": "Do not wipe or bathe your pet with chemical disinfectants, alcohol, hydrogen peroxide, or other products, such as hand sanitizer, counter-cleaning wipes, or other industrial or surface cleaners. If you have questions about appropriate products for bathing or cleaning your pet, talk to your veterinarian. If your pet gets hand sanitizer on their skin\u00a0or fur, rinse or wipe down your pet with water immediately. If your pet\u00a0ingests hand sanitizer (such as by chewing the bottle)\u00a0or is showing signs of illness after use, contact your veterinarian or pet poison control immediately."}, {"question": "Can I take my dog to a dog park?", "answer": "Dog parks provide socialization and exercise for dogs, which is an important part of their wellbeing. Because there is a risk that people with COVID-19 could spread it to animals, CDC recommends that you do not let pets interact with people outside of your household, especially in places with community spread of COVID-19. Therefore, you should consider avoiding dog parks or other places where large numbers of people and dogs gather.\nSome areas are allowing dog parks to open. If you choose to go to a dog park, follow local guidelines. There are ways to reduce the risk of you or your dog getting infected with COVID-19 if you go to a dog park.\n\nDo not take your dog to a dog park if you are sick or if you have recently been in close contact with a person with COVID-19.\nDo not take your dog to a dog park if your dog is sick. Signs of sickness in dogs may include fever, coughing, difficulty breathing or shortness of breath, lethargy, sneezing, discharge from the nose or eyes, vomiting, or diarrhea.\nIf your dog has tested positive for the virus that causes COVID-19, talk to your veterinarian about when it is appropriate for your pet to go back to normal activities.\nTry to limit your dog\u2019s interaction with other people outside of your household while at the dog park.\nAs much as possible, avoid touching common items in the dog park like water bowls. Wash your hands or use hand sanitizer after touching items from the park. To make sure your dog has fresh water, consider bringing your own portable water bowl.\nLimit other pet items brought to the dog park, such as toys. Clean and disinfect anything taken to the park and returned home (leashes, toys, water bowls).\nDo not wipe or bathe your dog with chemical disinfectants, alcohol, hydrogen peroxide, or other products, such as hand sanitizer, counter-cleaning wipes, or other industrial or surface cleaners. If you have questions about appropriate products for bathing or cleaning your pet, talk to your veterinarian.\n\nSee more\u00a0information on pets and COVID-19\u00a0and recommendations for how to help keep your pet safe."}, {"question": "Can I take my dog to daycare or a groomer?", "answer": "Until we know more about how this virus affects animals, CDC encourages pet owners to treat pets as you would other human family members to protect them from possible infection. This means limiting contact between your pets and people outside your household as much as possible and avoiding places where large numbers of people gather.\nSome areas are allowing groomers and boarding facilities such as dog daycares to open. If you must take your pet to a groomer or boarding facility, follow any protocols put into place at the facility, such as wearing a mask\u00a0and maintaining at least 6 feet of space between yourself and others if possible.\nLimit pet items brought from home to the groomer or boarding facility, and disinfect any objects that are taken into a facility and returned home (such as leashes, bowls, and toys). Use an EPA-registered disinfectantexternal icon\u00a0to clean items and rinse thoroughly with clean water afterwards. Do not wipe or bathe your pet with chemical disinfectants, alcohol, hydrogen peroxide,\u00a0or other products, such as hand sanitizer, counter-cleaning wipes, or other industrial or surface cleaners. If you have questions about appropriate products for bathing or cleaning your pet, talk to your veterinarian.\nDo not put masks on pets, and do not take a sick pet to a groomer or boarding facility. Signs of sickness in dogs may include fever, coughing, difficulty breathing or shortness of breath, lethargy, sneezing, discharge from the nose or eyes, vomiting, or diarrhea.\u00a0If you think your pet is sick, call your veterinarian. Some veterinarians may offer telemedicine consultations or other plans for seeing sick pets. Your veterinarian can evaluate your pet and determine the next steps for your pet\u2019s treatment and care.\nSee more information on pets and COVID-19\u00a0and recommendations for how to help keep your pet safe."}, {"question": "What should I do if my pet gets sick and I think it\u2019s COVID-19?", "answer": "Most pets that have gotten sick from the virus that causes COVID-19 were infected after close contact with a person with COVID-19. Talk to your veterinarian about any health concerns you have about your pets.\nIf your pet gets sick after contact with a person with COVID-19,\u00a0call your veterinarian and let them know the pet was around a person with COVID-19. If you are sick with COVID-19, do not take your pet to the veterinary clinic yourself. Some veterinarians may offer telemedicine consultations or other plans for seeing sick pets. Your veterinarian can evaluate your pet and determine the next steps for your pet\u2019s treatment and care. Routine testing of animals for COVID-19 is not recommended at this time."}, {"question": "What should I do if there are pets at my long-term care facility or assisted living facility?", "answer": "Based on the available information to date, the risk of animals spreading COVID-19 to people is considered to be low. However, it appears that the virus that causes COVID-19 can spread from people to animals after close contact with people with COVID-19.\nUntil we learn more about how this virus affects animals, use similar precautions for pets and other animals in your facility as you would for other people in your facility. This will help protect both people and pets in your facility from COVID-19.\n\nDo not let pets in the facility interact with sick people.\nPets or other animals should not be allowed to roam freely around the facility, and cats should be kept indoors.\nResidents should avoid letting their pets interact with people as much as possible.\nDogs should be walked on a leash at least 6 feet (2 meters) away from others.\nPeople sick with COVID-19 should\u00a0avoid contact with pets and other animals.\nDo not allow pets into common areas of the facility such as cafeterias and social areas.\n\nTalk to a veterinarian\u00a0if a pet in your facility gets sick\u00a0or if you have any concerns about the health of any pets in the facility. If you think a pet in the facility was exposed to or is showing\u00a0signs\u00a0consistent with COVID-19, contact your\u00a0state health official\u00a0to discuss guidance on testing pets or other animals for the virus that causes COVID-19.\nPeople who are at higher risk for severe illness\u00a0from COVID-19 should avoid providing care for sick pets, if possible.\nFor more information, visit CDC\u2019s\u00a0If You Have Pets\u00a0webpage."}, {"question": "Are imported animals or animal products safe?", "answer": "CDC does not have any evidence to suggest that imported animals or animal products pose a risk for spreading COVID-19 in the United States. This is a rapidly evolving situation and information will be updated as it becomes available. CDC, the U. S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) play distinct but complementary roles in regulating the importation of live animals and animal products into the United States.\n\nCDC regulates\u00a0animals and animal products that pose a threat to human health,\nUSDA regulatesexternal icon animals and animal products that pose a threat to agriculture; and\nFWS regulatesexternal icon importation of endangered species and wildlife that can harm the health and welfare of humans, the interests of agriculture, horticulture, or forestry, and the welfare and survival of wildlife resources."}, {"question": "Can I travel to the United States with dogs or import dogs into the United States during the COVID-19 pandemic?", "answer": "Beginning July 14, 2021, there is a temporary suspension for dogs imported from countries\u00a0that CDC considers high risk for dog rabies. Please refer to CDC\u2019s requirements for bringing a dog into the United States."}, {"question": "What precautions should be taken for animals that have recently been imported from outside the United States (for example, by shelters, rescues, or as personal pets)?", "answer": "Imported animals will need to meet\u00a0CDC and USDA\u2019sexternal iconexternal icon\u00a0requirements for entering the United States. At this time, there is no evidence that companion animals, including pets and service animals, can spread the virus that causes COVID-19. As with any animal introduced to a new environment, animals recently imported should be observed daily for signs of illness. If an animal becomes ill, the animal should be examined by a veterinarian. Call your local veterinary clinic\u00a0before\u00a0bringing the animal into the clinic and let them know that the animal was recently imported from another country.\nThis is a rapidly evolving situation and information will be updated as it becomes available."}, {"question": "Can wild animals spread the virus that causes COVID-19 to people or pets?", "answer": "Currently, there is no evidence to suggest the virus that causes COVID-19 is circulating in free-living wildlife in the United States, or that wildlife might be a source of infection for people in the United States.\nIf a wild animal were to become infected with the virus, we don\u2019t know whether the infection could then spread among wildlife or if it could spread to other animals, including pets. Further studies are needed to understand if and how different animals, including wildlife, could be affected by COVID-19. Because wildlife can carry other diseases, even without looking sick, it is always important to enjoy wildlife from a distance.\nTake steps to prevent getting sick from wildlife in the United States:\n\nKeep your family, including pets, a safe distance away from wildlife.\nDo not feed wildlife or touch wildlife droppings.\nAlways wash your hands and supervise children washing their hands after working or playing outside.\nLeave orphaned animals alone. Often, the parents are close by and will return for their young.\nConsult your state wildlife agency\u2019s guidance if you are preparing or consuming legally harvested game meat.\nDo not approach or touch a sick or dead animal \u2013 contact your state wildlife agency instead.\n\nSee\u00a0COVID-19 and Animals\u00a0for more information."}, {"question": "Can bats in United States get the virus that causes COVID-19, and can they spread it back to people?", "answer": "Other coronaviruses have been found in North American bats in the past, but there is currently no evidence that the virus that causes COVID-19 is present in any free-living wildlife in the United States, including bats. In general, coronaviruses do not cause illness or death in bats, but we don\u2019t yet know if this new coronavirus would make North American species of bats sick. Bats are an important part of natural ecosystems, and their populations are already declining in the United States. Bat populations could be further threatened by the disease itself or by harm inflicted on bats resulting from a misconception that bats are spreading COVID-19. However, there is no evidence that bats in the United States are a source of the virus that causes COVID-19 for people. Further studies are needed to understand if and how bats could be affected by COVID-19."}, {"question": "Is hunter-harvested game meat safe to eat during the COVID-19 pandemic?", "answer": "Currently, there is no evidence that you can get infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 by eating food, including wild hunted game meat. However, hunters can get infected with other diseases when processing or eating game.\u00a0 Hunters should always practice good hygiene when processing animals by following these food safety recommendations:\n\nDo not harvest animals that appear sick or are found dead.\nKeep game meat clean and cool the meat down as soon as possible after harvesting the animal.\nAvoid cutting through the backbone and spinal tissues and do not eat the brains of any wild animal.\nWhen handling and cleaning game:\n\nWear rubber or disposable gloves.\nDo not eat, drink, or smoke.\n\n\nWhen finished handling and cleaning game:\n\nWash your hands thoroughly with soap and water.\nClean knives, equipment, and surfaces that were in contact with game meat with soap and water and then disinfect them. While these recommendations apply to general food safety practices, if you are concerned about COVID-19, you may use a product on the EPA list of disinfectants for use against the COVID-19 virusexternal icon.\n\n\nCook all game meat thoroughly (to an internal temperature of 165\u00b0F or higher).\nCheck with your state wildlife agency regarding any testing requirements for other diseases and for any specific instructions regarding preparing, transporting, and consuming game meat."}, {"question": "How can I safely run my equestrian facility?", "answer": "You should follow your state and/or local jurisdictional guidance regarding continuing operations at your facility. There have not been any reports of horses testing positive for the virus that causes COVID-19. Based on the limited information available to date, the risk of animals spreading the virus that causes COVID-19 to people is considered to be low. COVID-19 is primarily spread from person to person, so steps should be taken to reduce the risks for people visiting your facility.\n\nEncourage employees and other visitors, including boarders, owners, farriers, veterinarians, and those taking lessons, not to enter the facility if they are sick. Employees should not return to work until the criteria to discontinue home isolation\u00a0are met, after talking with their doctor. Implement sick leave policies that are flexible, nonpunitive, and consistent with public health guidance, allowing employees to stay home if they have symptoms of respiratory infection.\nConsider conducting daily health checks (e.g., symptom and/or temperature screening) of employees and others visiting the facility before they enter the premises. People with a fever of 100.40(38.00C) or above or other signs of illness should not be admitted to the premises. If implementing health checks, conduct them safely and respectfully. See General Business FAQs\u00a0for more information.\n\nEmployees or visitors who appear to have symptoms upon arrival or who become sick during their visit should immediately be separated from other employees and visitors and sent home.\n\n\nLimit the number of people entering the facility. Consider staggering lesson and visiting times to limit the number of people in the facility and potential for person-to-person contact. If possible, you can also take steps to decrease high-traffic areas by limiting areas open to visitors/owners or staggering use of common areas like grooming or wash stalls and tack rooms.\nIncrease distance and limit duration of contact between employees and visitors in the facility. Whenever possible, people should maintain at least 6 feet of distance between each other at the facility, including instructors teaching lessons. Allow for social distancing\u00a0and avoid large numbers of people within the facility, including in employee-only areas.\nVisitors and employees should wear masks especially where social distancing measures are difficult to maintain. Masks offer some protection to the wearer and are also meant to protect those around the wearer, in case they are infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Wearing a mask does NOT replace the need to practice social distancing.\nSet up hand hygiene stations at the entrance and within the facility, so that employees and people entering can clean their hands before they enter. Employees should wash hands regularly with soap and water for at least 20 seconds. An alcohol-based hand sanitizer containing at least 60% alcohol can be used, but if hands are visibly dirty, they should be washed with soap and water before using an alcohol-based hand sanitizer. Examples of hand hygiene stations may be a hose and soap located at entrances to allow for handwashing before entry.\nCleaning high touch surfaces and shared objects once a day is usually enough\u00a0to sufficiently remove virus that may be on surfaces unless someone with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 has been in the equestrian facility.\u00a0Disinfecting (using disinfectants on\u00a0U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)\u2019s List Nexternal icon) removes any remaining germs on surfaces, which further reduces any risk of spreading infection.\u00a0\u00a0For more information on cleaning regularly and cleaning when someone is sick, see Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Facility.\nFollow local guidance on shelter in place and travel recommendations when traveling for showing, training, or trail riding.\nIf traveling to a new facility, limit contact between people, horses, tack, equipment, and other supplies from different facilities, and maintain a distance of at least 6 feet between horses and riders.\n\nFollow state and local guidance on travel. People who are sick should not travel to other facilities.\nPeople visiting other facilities should follow the same precautions as they would normally, including maintaining at least 6 feet of distance between each other, wearing a mask to protect others, and washing hands frequently with soap and water.\n\n\nIf other animals, such as barn cats, are present at the facility, be aware that a small number of pets have been reported to be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19, mostly after contact with people with COVID-19.\n\nFor more information, see Guidance on Preparing Workplaces for COVID-19 pdf icon[35 pages, 1.4mb]external icon\u00a0and Interim Guidance for Businesses and Employers to Plan and Respond to Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19)."}, {"question": "Can the virus that causes COVID-19 get back into the environment from wastewater and infect wildlife?", "answer": "SARS-CoV-2 (the virus that causes COVID-19) can be shed in the feces of people with COVID-19. Genetic material from SARS-CoV-2 has been found in untreated wastewater. However, while data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater, and no information to date that anyone has become sick with COVID-19 because of exposure to wastewater. It is possible that wildlife could become infected with SARS-CoV-2 from contact with untreated wastewater, but evidence from studies of virus infectivity in feces and survival in wastewater suggests that this transmission route is unlikely to occur."}]}, {"title": "Community Mitigation", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What is community mitigation?", "answer": "Community mitigation is a set of actions that people and communities can take to slow the spread of infectious diseases like COVID-19. The goal of community mitigation in areas with local COVID-19 transmission is to slow its spread and to protect all individuals, especially those at increased risk for severe illness, while minimizing the negative impacts of these strategies. For more information, see Community Mitigation Framework."}, {"question": "What are community mitigation actions for COVID-19?", "answer": "There are several actions that individuals and communities can take to help reduce the chance that they, their families and friends, and their communities get COVID-19. In general, the more cases spreading in your community, the more likely it will spread to you or your family. Also, the more people an individual interacts with, and the longer each interaction lasts, the higher the risk of viral spread. Location can be a factor, too, with outdoor activities generally being less risky than indoor activities.\n\u00a0Individuals can take the following community mitigation actions:\n\nWear a mask (with some exceptions) when in public settings or around others not living in the same household\nFollow healthy hygiene practices, such as frequent hand washing\nPractice social distancing\nStay home when sick\nClean frequently touched surfaces daily\n\nCommunities can take the following actions:\n\nPromote behaviors that prevent spread\nMaintain healthy environments\nEnsure institutions in the community are practicing appropriate precautions\nPrepare for when someone gets sick\nClose businesses and schools, and limit other services\n\nFor more information, see Community Guidance, Community Mitigation, and Community Mitigation Framework."}]}, {"title": "Food and Water", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Can I get COVID-19 from food (including restaurant take-out, produce, refrigerated, or packaged food) or drinking water?", "answer": "Currently there is no evidence that people can get COVID-19 by eating or handling food.\nIt may be possible that people can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object, such as a food package or dining ware that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes. However, this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads. Follow\u00a0food safety guidelines\u00a0when handling and cleaning fresh produce.\u00a0Do not wash produce with soap, bleach, sanitizer, alcohol, disinfectant or any other chemical.\nThere is also no current evidence that people can get COVID-19 by drinking water. The COVID-19 virus has not been detected in drinking water. Conventional water treatment methods that use filtration and disinfection, such as those in most municipal drinking water systems, should remove or kill the virus that causes COVID-19.\u200b Learn more about food and COVID-19."}, {"question": "Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread through treated drinking water?", "answer": "The virus that causes COVID-19 has not been detected in treated drinking water. Water treatment plants use filters and disinfectants to remove or kill germs, like the virus that causes COVID-19. The Environmental Protection Agency regulates water treatment plants to ensure that treated water is safe to drink.\nCurrently, there is no evidence that the virus that causes COVID-19 can be spread to people by drinking treated water. COVID-19 is spread mainly through close contact from person-to-person. You can continue to use and drink water from your tap as usual."}, {"question": "Is the virus that causes COVID-19 found in feces (stool)?", "answer": "The virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in the feces of some patients diagnosed with COVID-19. However, it is unclear whether the virus found in feces may be capable of causing COVID-19. There has not been any confirmed report of the virus spreading from feces to a person. Scientists also do not know how much risk there is that the virus could be spread from the feces of an infected person to another person. However, they think this risk is low based on data from previous pandemics of diseases caused by related coronaviruses, such as severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS)."}, {"question": "Can the COVID-19 virus spread through wastewater systems?", "answer": "SARS-CoV-2 (the virus that causes COVID-19) can be shed in the feces of individuals with COVID-19. Genetic material from SARS-CoV-2 has been found in untreated wastewater. However, while data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater, and no information to date that anyone has become sick with COVID-19 because of exposure to wastewater. Wastewater treatment plants use chemical and other disinfection processes to remove and degrade many viruses and bacteria. SARS-CoV-2 is inactivated by the disinfection methods used in wastewater treatment. At this time, the risk of transmission of the virus that causes COVID-19 through properly designed and maintained wastewater systems is thought to be low."}, {"question": "Should wastewater workers take extra precautions to protect themselves from the virus that causes COVID-19?", "answer": "Recently, ribonucleic acid (RNA) from the virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in untreated wastewater. While data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater, and no information to date that anyone has become sick with COVID-19 because of exposure to wastewater.\nStandard practices associated with wastewater treatment plant operations should be sufficient to protect wastewater workers from the virus that causes COVID-19. These standard practices can include engineering and administrative controls, hygiene precautions, specific safe work practices, and personal protective equipment (PPE) normally required when handling untreated wastewater. No additional COVID-19\u2013specific protections are recommended for workers involved in wastewater management, including those at wastewater treatment facilities.\nSee Information for Wastewater and Sanitation System Workers on COVID-19 for additional information."}, {"question": "If my utility has issued a Boil Water Advisory, can I still use tap water to wash my hands?", "answer": "In most cases, it is safe to wash your hands\u00a0with soap and tap water during a Boil Water Advisory. Follow the guidance from your local public health officials. If soap and water are not available, use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer containing at least 60% alcohol."}, {"question": "Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through floodwater?", "answer": "There is\u00a0no evidence that COVID-19 can spread to people through water, including floodwater.\nSometimes floodwater can mix with\u00a0wastewater. CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus being spread by swallowing or coming in contact with water contaminated by feces from an infected person.\u00a0Stay out of floodwater to\u00a0avoid hazards and illnesses\u00a0from contaminants that are not associated with COVID-19. To learn more about COVID-19 and wastewater, see question, \u201cCan the COVID-19 virus spread through sewerage systems?\u201d"}]}, {"title": "Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through the water in pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds?", "answer": "CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus that causes COVID-19 spreading to people through the water in pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds. Plus, proper operation of public pools, hot tubs, and water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) and disinfection of the water (with chlorine or bromine) should inactivate the virus.\nThe virus mainly spreads when respiratory droplets from infected people land in the mouths or noses of others or possibly when inhaled into the lungs by others. If a public pool, hot tub, or water playground is open, it is important for all visitors and staff to take steps to slow the spread of the virus:\n\nStay home if you are infected or might be infected\u00a0with the virus that causes COVID-19.\nStay at least 6 feet apart (in and out of the water) from people you don\u2019t live with.\nWear cloth masks\u00a0when not in water.\nCover coughs and sneezes with a tissue (or use the inside of your elbow), throw used tissues in the trash, and wash hands.\nWash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds. Use hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol if soap and water are not readily available.\n\nSee Considerations for Public Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds\u00a0for more information."}, {"question": "Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through the water in saltwater pools?", "answer": "CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus that causes COVID-19 spreading to people through the water in pools, including saltwater pools. Plus, proper operation\u00a0of public pools (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) and disinfection of the water (with chlorine or bromine) should inactivate the virus. Saltwater pools are chlorinated pools.\nIn traditional pools, chlorine products (such as granules or liquid bleach) are added to the water to disinfect it. In saltwater pools, table salt (made up of sodium and chloride) is added to the water, and an electrical current is then run through the water with dissolved salt. This creates the same disinfecting form of chlorine that is created when chlorine products are added to the water in traditional pools."}, {"question": "Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through the water in lakes, oceans, or rivers?", "answer": "CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus that causes COVID-19 spreading to people through the water in lakes, oceans, rivers, or other natural bodies of water.\nThe virus mainly spreads when respiratory droplets from infected people land in the mouths or noses of others or possibly when inhaled into the lungs by others. If a public beach or other swim area in a natural body of water is open, it is important for all visitors and staff to take steps to slow the spread of the virus:\n\nStay home if you are infected or might be infected\u00a0with the virus that causes COVID-19.\nStay at least 6 feet apart (in and out of the water) from people you don\u2019t live with.\nWear cloth masks\u00a0when not in water.\nCover coughs and sneezes with a tissue (or use the inside of your elbow), throw used tissues in the trash, and wash hands.\nWash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds. Use hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol if soap and water are not readily available.\n\nSee Considerations for Public Beaches\u00a0for more information.\nRNAexternal icon of the virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in untreated wastewater, which can come from combined sewer overflowsexternal icon (rainwater runoff, domestic sewage, and industrial wastewater) and other sourcesexternal icon\u00a0(such as, leaking septic tanks or animal waste from farms nearby) and enter swim areas. While data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater. Plus, CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus being spread by swallowing or coming in contact with water contaminated by feces (poop) from an infected person.\nAt lakes, oceans, and rivers with routine water quality monitoring programs, staff look for changes in fecal (poop) contamination of the water. Water quality advisories and beach closures alert the public to avoid getting in or on the water because of increased fecal contamination. Learn more about healthy swimming in natural bodies of water and access water quality information by state."}, {"question": "Can cloth masks be worn in the water?", "answer": "No, do NOT wear a cloth mask in the water. It can be difficult to breathe through a cloth mask when it is wet. Plus, wet cloth masks don\u2019t slow the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19 as well as dry cloth masks. All of this means it is particularly important to stay at least 6 feet apart\u00a0in the water from people you don\u2019t live with.\nIn case cloth masks do get wet by mistake, bring a second (or extra) cloth mask for everyone heading out to the public pool or beach."}, {"question": "Can Lycra (Spandex or elastane), the cloth used to make swimsuits, be used to make cloth masks?", "answer": "CDC does not yet have evidence on the effectiveness of different types of cloth materials.\nMasks offer some protection to you and are also meant to protect those around you, in case you are unknowingly infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Make sure your cloth mask:\n\nfits snugly but comfortably against the side of the face,\ncompletely covers the nose and mouth,\nis secured with ties or ear loops,\nincludes multiple layers of fabric,\nallows for breathing without restriction, and\ncan be laundered and machine dried without damage or change to shape.\n\nCloth masks should NOT be worn by children less than 2 years old or anyone who has trouble breathing or is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the mask without assistance. Learn more about how to wear, take off, and wash\u00a0your cloth masks."}, {"question": "How many people, visitors and staff, can be in and around a public pool, hot tub, or water playground (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) at the same time?", "answer": "The design of the public pool, hot tub, or water playground and surrounding deck and if visitors live together or not will affect how many people can stay at least 6 feet apart\u00a0from those they don\u2019t live with.\nCDC recommends operators of public pools, hot tubs, and water playgrounds:\n\ncomply with local, state, territorial, federal, and tribal regulatory agency policies and requirements on gathering (so the number of swimmers in the water isn\u2019t more than the maximum allowed) and\nteach and reinforce social (physical) distancing\u00a0among visitors and staff.\n\nOperators might want to limit the number of people in and around the water so if the water needs to be evacuated (because of lightning or other health or safety threat) social distancing can be maintained on the deck. Otherwise, if the water is evacuated and social distancing cannot be maintained on the deck, close the deck to visitors. There is no standard formula to determine how many people can maintain social distancing in the water and on the surrounding deck.\nSee Considerations for Public Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds\u00a0for more information."}, {"question": "Can I use pool, hot tub, or water playground water to disinfect surfaces or shared objects?", "answer": "No. Only List N disinfectants approved by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agencyexternal icon\u00a0should be used to disinfect surfaces (such as handrails and in bathrooms) and shared objects (such as kickboards and pool noodles).\nThe list includes hundreds of disinfectants. Operators of public pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) should consult with the design company or engineer to determine which disinfectants are best suited for surfaces and with manufacturers to determine which disinfectants are best suited for shared objects.\nRemember to clean surfaces and shared objects before disinfecting them\u00a0and to follow directions on labels of cleaning products and disinfectants."}, {"question": "Can the sun\u2019s ultraviolet (UV) light disinfect surfaces and shared objects?", "answer": "We don\u2019t know yet. Early scientific data suggest that SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, can be inactivated by the sun\u2019s UV light. However, the ability of the sun\u2019s UV light to inactivate the virus on surfaces (such as handrails and in bathrooms) and shared objects (such as kickboards and pool noodles) needs more research. Factors \u2014 such as cloudiness, latitude (distance from equator), time of day, and amount of time exposed to the sun\u2019s UV light \u2014 will determine how effectively the virus is inactivated.\nRemember to clean surfaces and shared objects before disinfecting them and to follow directions on labels of cleaning products and disinfectantsexternal icon."}, {"question": "How often do surfaces (such as handrails and in bathrooms) at public pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) need to be cleaned and disinfected?", "answer": "The more frequently a surface is touched by multiple people, the more frequently it should be cleaned and then disinfected with a List N disinfectant approved by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agencyexternal icon. Frequently touched surfaces should be cleaned and disinfected at least daily.\nRemember to clean surfaces and shared objects before disinfecting them\u00a0and to follow directions on labels of cleaning products and disinfectants."}, {"question": "Do procedures for responding to formed fecal (poop) or diarrheal incidents in public pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) need to change during the COVID-19 pandemic?", "answer": "No. RNAexternal icon of the virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in feces (poop). While data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in feces. Plus, CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus being spread by swallowing or coming in contact with water contaminated by feces from an infected person. As a result, CDC has not changed its fecal incident response recommendations. Remember, do NOT vacuum feces out of the water."}, {"question": "Can lifeguards monitor how visitors socially distance (stay at least 6 feet apart from people you don\u2019t live with), wear cloth masks, or wash hands?", "answer": "Not when lifeguards are actively lifeguarding. Lifeguards actively lifeguarding should not be doing other tasks that could distract them. Drowning deaths have resulted, at least in part, from lifeguards being distracted.\u00a0\nDrowning can occur quickly and quietly. Learn and take steps to prevent drowning."}, {"question": "How can the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19 be slowed during lifeguard training?", "answer": "Lifeguard trainers can consider the following steps to slow the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19:\n\nHave the virus? Stay home to save lives.\n\nEducate instructors, lifeguard students, and others about when they should stay home to isolate (if they have symptoms of COVID-19 or tested positive for COVID-19) or quarantine (if they have been in close contact with someone who has COVID-19) and when they can return or reschedule training.\nConduct daily health checks (see frequently asked question on screening) or ask instructors, students, and others to conduct self-checks (such as temperature screening or symptom checking), if possible.\n\nConduct health checks safely and respectfully and in accordance with any applicable local, state, territorial, federal, and tribal privacy and confidentiality laws, rules, and regulations.\n\n\n\n\nBe smart, stay at least 6 feet apart\n\nConduct knowledge training virtually or online, when possible, to limit contact among instructors, students, and others.\nTeach and reinforce social (physical) distancing\u00a0during in-person skills training in and out of the water \u2014 maintaining at least 6 feet between people who don\u2019t live together.\n\nProvide physical cues or guides (such as lane lines in the water or chairs and tables on the deck) and visual cues (such as posted signs or tape on the deck).\n\n\nLimit close contact, particularly face-to-face interactions, between people who don\u2019t live together, as recommended by the lifeguarding-certifying organization. Such as\n\nAquatic rescue\n\nFor practice rescues\n\nHave each student practice rescues on his or her household member instead of another student.\n\n\nFor actual rescues\n\nStress the need to keep the number of people involved in rescue and resuscitation to the minimum number needed to provide proper care.\nStress the need to 1) perform rescues from the deck (using an extending or throwing device) if conditions allow and 2) if possible, have people on the deck wear cloth masks, when removing victim from the water because social distancing cannot be maintained. If an in-water rescue is needed, minimize exposure to the distressed swimmer\u2019s face without protection, if possible approaching him or her from behind.\n\n\n\n\nCardiopulmonary Resuscitation (CPR)\n\nFor practice resuscitation\n\nLimit student-to-manikin ratio and student-to-automated external defibrillator (AED) training device ratio to 1:1. Have each student use his or her own breathing barrier when doing rescue breathing on a manikin.\n\n\nFor actual resuscitation\n\nStress the need for and train with personal protective equipment (PPE) during resuscitation, as recommended by the CPR-certifying organization (such as the American Red Crossexternal icon), and use a bag-valve mask (BVM) with a high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter. BVM ventilation is best delivered with two rescuers.\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nWear a mask. Save lives.\n\nTeach and reinforce use of cloth masks\u00a0in public settings when around people you don\u2019t live with, particularly when it is difficult to maintain social distancing.\n\nAdvise people wearing masks to not wear them in the water. Cloth masks can be difficult to breathe through when they\u2019re wet. This means it is particularly important to maintain social distancing in the water. Plus, wet cloth masks don\u2019t slow the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19 as well as dry cloth masks.\n\n\n\n\nCover coughs and sneezes\n\nTeach and reinforce covering coughs and sneezes with a tissue (or use the inside of elbow), throw used tissues in the trash, and wash hands.\n\n\nWash hands often\n\nTeach and reinforce handwashing\u00a0with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, particularly after being in a public place or after blowing your nose, coughing, or sneezing.\n\nUse hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol, if soap and water are not readily available.\n\n\n\n\n\n\nClean and then disinfect\n\nCleaning with a household cleaner that contains soap or detergent reduces the amount of germs on surfaces and decreases risk of infection from surfaces. In most situations, cleaning alone removes most virus particles on surfaces. Disinfection to reduce spread of COVID-19 at home is likely not needed unless someone in your home is sick or someone with COVID-19 has been in your home within the last 24 hours. For more information on cleaning your home regularly and cleaning your home when someone is sick, see\u00a0Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Home.\nCDC has more COVID-19\u2013related considerations for public pools and public beaches\u00a0and non-COVID-19\u2013related healthy and safe swimming resources."}]}, {"title": "Vaccines", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "If I have already had COVID-19 and recovered, do I still need to get vaccinated with a COVID-19 vaccine?", "answer": "Yes, you should be vaccinated regardless of whether you already had COVID-19. That\u2019s because experts do not yet know how long you are protected from getting sick again after recovering from COVID-19. Even if you have already recovered from COVID-19, it is possible\u2014although rare\u2014that you could be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 again. Studies have shown that vaccination provides a strong boost in protection in people who have recovered from COVID-19. Learn more about why getting vaccinated is a safer way to build protection\u00a0than getting infected.\nIf you were treated for COVID-19 with monoclonal antibodies or convalescent plasma, you should wait 90 days before getting a COVID-19 vaccine. Talk to your doctor if you are unsure what treatments you received or if you have more questions about getting a COVID-19 vaccine.\nIf you or your child has a history of multisystem inflammatory syndrome in adults or children (MIS-A or MIS-C), consider delaying vaccination until you or your child have recovered from being sick and for 90 days after the date of diagnosis of MIS-A or MIS-C. Learn more about the clinical considerations\u00a0people with a history of multisystem MIS-C or MIS-A.\nExperts are still learning more about how long vaccines protect against COVID-19. CDC will keep the public informed as new evidence becomes available.\nRelated pages:\n\nBenefits of Getting Vaccinated\nPreparing for Your COVID-19 Vaccination"}, {"question": "Is it safe for my child to get a COVID-19 vaccine?", "answer": "Yes. Studies show that COVID-19 vaccines are safe and effective. Like adults, children may have some side effects after COVID-19 vaccination. These side effects may affect their ability to do daily activities, but they should go away in a few days. Children 12 years and older are now eligible to get vaccinated against COVID-19. COVID-19 vaccines have been used under the most intensive safety monitoring in U.S. history, including studies in children 12 years and older. Your child cannot get COVID-19 from any COVID-19 vaccine.\nRelated page:\n\nCOVID-19 Vaccines for Children and Teens"}, {"question": "Why should my child get vaccinated against COVID-19?", "answer": "COVID-19 vaccination can help protect your child from getting COVID-19. Although fewer children have been sick with COVID-19 compared to adults, children can be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19, can get sick from COVID-19, and can spread the virus that causes COVID-19 to others. Getting your child vaccinated helps to protect your child and your family. Vaccination is now recommended for everyone 12 years and older. Currently, the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 Vaccine is the only one available to children 12 years and older.\nRelated page:\n\nCOVID-19 Vaccines for Children and Teens"}, {"question": "What are the ingredients in COVID-19 vaccines?", "answer": "Vaccine ingredients can vary by manufacturer. To learn more about the ingredients in authorized COVID-19 vaccines, see\n\nInformation about the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 Vaccine\nInformation about the Moderna COVID-19 Vaccine\nInformation about the Johnson & Johnson\u2019s Janssen COVID-19 Vaccine\nIngredients Included in COVID-19 Vaccines"}, {"question": "Do I need to wear a mask and avoid close contact with others if I am fully vaccinated?", "answer": "No. Fully vaccinated people can resume activities without wearing a mask or physically distancing, except where required by federal, state, local, tribal, or territorial laws, rules, and regulations, including local business and workplace guidance. If you are fully vaccinated, you can resume activities that you did before the pandemic.\nAdditional recommendations can be found at When You\u2019ve Been Fully Vaccinated.\nRelated pages:\n\nWhen You\u2019ve Been Fully Vaccinated\nKey Things to Know\nProtect Yourself and Others"}, {"question": "Can I choose which COVID-19 vaccine I get?", "answer": "Yes. All currently authorized and recommended COVID-19 vaccines are safe and effective, and CDC does not recommend one vaccine over another. The most important decision is to get a COVID-19 vaccination as soon as possible. Widespread vaccination is a critical tool to help stop the pandemic.\nPeople should be aware that a risk of a rare condition called thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome (TTS) has been reported following vaccination with the J&J/Janssen COVID-19 Vaccine. TTS is a serious condition that involves blood clots with low platelet counts. This problem is rare, and most reports were in women between 18 and 49 years old. For women 50 years and older and men of any age, this problem is even more rare. There are other COVID-19 vaccine options available for which this risk has not been seen (Pfizer-BioNTech, Moderna).\nLearn more about your COVID-19 vaccination, including how to find a vaccination location, what to expect at your appointment, and more.\nRelated page:\n\nYour Vaccination"}, {"question": "If I am pregnant, can I get a COVID-19 vaccine?", "answer": "Yes, if you are pregnant, you can receive a COVID-19 vaccine.\nYou might want to have a conversation with your healthcare provider to help you decide whether to get vaccinated. While such a conversation might be helpful, it is not required before vaccination. Learn more about vaccination considerations for people who are pregnant or breastfeeding.\nIf you are pregnant and have received a COVID-19 vaccine, we encourage you to enroll in v-safe, CDC\u2019s smartphone-based tool that provides personalized health check-ins after vaccination. A v-safe\u00a0pregnancy registry\u00a0has been established to gather information on the health of pregnant people who have received a COVID-19 vaccine.\nRelated pages:\n\nCOVID-19 Vaccines for Pregnant or Breastfeeding People\nMonitoring Systems for Pregnant People\nV-safe Pregnancy Registry"}, {"question": "How long does protection from a COVID-19 vaccine last?", "answer": "We don\u2019t know how long protection lasts for those who are vaccinated. What we do know is that COVID-19 has caused very serious illness and death for a lot of people. If you get COVID-19, you also risk giving it to loved ones who may get very sick. Getting a COVID-19 vaccine is a safer choice.\nExperts are working to learn more about both natural immunity and vaccine-induced immunity. CDC will keep the public informed as new evidence becomes available.\nRelated page:\n\nVaccines Work"}, {"question": "How many doses of COVID-19 vaccine will I need to get?", "answer": "The number of doses needed depends on which vaccine you receive. To get the most protection:\n\nTwo Pfizer-BioNTech vaccine doses should be given 3 weeks (21 days) apart.\nTwo Moderna vaccine doses should be given 1 month (28 days) apart.\nJohnson & Johnsons Jansen (J&J/Janssen) COVID-19 vaccine requires only one dose.\n\nIf you receive a vaccine that requires two doses, you should\u00a0get your second shot as close to the recommended interval as possible.\u00a0However, your second dose may be given up to 6 weeks (42 days) after the first dose, if necessary.. You should\u00a0not\u00a0get the second dose earlier than the recommended interval.\nRelated pages:\n\nPfizer-BioNTech\nModerna\nJohnson & Johnson / Janssen"}, {"question": "If I have an underlying condition, can I get a COVID-19 vaccine?", "answer": "People with underlying medical conditions can receive a COVID-19 vaccine as long as they have not had\u00a0an immediate or severe allergic reaction to a COVID-19 vaccine or to any of the ingredients in the vaccine.\u00a0Learn more about vaccination considerations for people with underlying medical conditions. Vaccination is an important consideration for adults of any age with certain\u00a0underlying medical conditions\u00a0because they are at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19.\nRelated pages:\n\nUnderlying Medical Conditions\nPeople at High Risk\nPeople with Allergies"}, {"question": "Can I get vaccinated against COVID-19 while I am currently sick with COVID-19?", "answer": "No. People with COVID-19 who have symptoms should wait to be vaccinated until they have recovered from their illness and have met the criteria for discontinuing isolation; those without symptoms should also wait until they meet the criteria\u00a0before getting vaccinated. This guidance also applies to people who get COVID-19 before getting their second dose of vaccine.\nRelated pages:\n\nWhen to Quarantine\nEnding Home Isolation"}]}, {"title": "Travel : General", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html", "data": [{"question": "Can people who have recently recovered from COVID-19 travel?", "answer": "If you had COVID-19 in the past 3 months, follow all requirements and recommendations for fully vaccinated travelers\u00a0except:\n\nYou can show documentation of recovery from COVID-19\u00a0instead of a negative test result before boarding an international flight to the United States.\nYou do NOT need to tested 3-5 days after travel to the United States unless you have symptoms of COVID-19.\n\nWe know that people can continue to test positive for up to 3 months after they had COVID-19 and not be infectious to others."}, {"question": "What if I recently traveled and am sick?", "answer": "See CDC\u2019s website What to Do If You Are Sick."}, {"question": "How can I protect myself from COVID-19 when using different types of transportation?", "answer": "See CDC\u2019s website Protect Yourself When Using Transportation."}]}, {"title": "Travel : General : Domestic Travel", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html", "data": [{"question": "Can traveling to visit family or friends increase my chances of getting and spreading COVID-19?", "answer": "Yes. CDC recommends delaying travel until you are fully vaccinated, because travel increases your chance of getting and spreading COVID-19. If you are not fully vaccinated and must travel, follow CDC\u2019s Domestic Travel or International Travel\u00a0recommendations for unvaccinated people."}, {"question": "Am I required to quarantine after domestic travel?", "answer": "CDC does not require travelers to undergo a mandatory federal quarantine. However, CDC recommends that unvaccinated travelers self-quarantine after travel for 7 days with a negative test and for 10 days if they don\u2019t get tested.\nCheck CDC\u2019s Domestic Travel\u00a0pages for the latest recommendations for fully vaccinated and unvaccinated travelers.\nFollow all\u202fstate and local\u202frecommendations or requirements."}]}, {"title": "Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html", "data": [{"question": "How does CDC determine the COVID-19 Travel Health Notice Level of a destination?", "answer": "CDC reviews data reported to the World Health Organization daily to determine a destination\u2019s COVID-19 Travel Health Notice level. There are a few factors that CDC considers when determining the level of a destination. To find out more about the COVID-19 Travel Health Notice levels, visit How CDC Determines the Level for COVID-19 Travel Health Notices.\nThese notices offer travel recommendations based on the level of COVID-19 in a destination. To learn more about COVID-19 travel recommendations for a specific destination, visit COVID-19 Travel Recommendations by Destination."}, {"question": "How often are international travel recommendations related to COVID-19 updated?", "answer": "Recommendations are updated weekly. CDC reviews data reported to the World Health Organization daily to determine a destination\u2019s COVID-19 Travel Health Notice level and makes appropriate level changes once a week. To find out more about the COVID-19 Travel Health Notice levels, visit How CDC Determines the Level for COVID-19 Travel Health Notices."}, {"question": "What restrictions do other countries have in place that might affect US travelers?", "answer": "Check with your destination\u2019s Office of Foreign Affairs or Ministry of Health or the U.S. Department of State, Bureau of Consular Affairs, Country Informationexternal icon\u00a0for details about entry requirements and restrictions for arriving travelers."}, {"question": "Does CDC require COVID-19 testing before coming to the United States?", "answer": "All air passengers coming to the United States, including U.S. citizens and fully vaccinated people, are required to have a negative COVID-19 test result no more than 3 days before travel or documentation of recovery from COVID-19 in the past 3 months before they board a flight to the United States."}, {"question": "Does CDC require quarantine after international travel?", "answer": "CDC does not require travelers to undergo a mandatory federal quarantine. However, CDC recommends that unvaccinated travelers self-quarantine after travel for 7 days with a negative test and for 10 days if they don\u2019t get tested.\nCheck CDC\u2019s International Travel\u00a0pages for the latest recommendations for vaccinated and unvaccinated travelers.\nFollow all\u202fstate and local\u202frecommendations or requirements."}]}, {"title": "Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel : Air or Cruise Travel", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html", "data": [{"question": "Can flying on an airplane increase my risk of getting COVID-19?", "answer": "Yes. Air travel requires spending time in security lines and airport terminals, which can bring you in close contact with other people and frequently touched surfaces. Most viruses and other germs do not spread easily on flights because of how air circulates and is filtered on airplanes. However, social distancing is difficult on crowded flights, and you may have to sit near others (within 6 feet), sometimes for hours. This may increase your risk for exposure to the virus that causes COVID-19."}, {"question": "Do I have to wear a mask when I travel?", "answer": "Masks are required on planes, buses, trains, and other forms of public transportation traveling into, within, or out of the United States and in U.S. transportation hubs such as airports and stations."}, {"question": "What happens if there is a sick passenger on an international or domestic flight?", "answer": "Under current federal regulations, pilots must report all illnesses and deaths to CDC before arriving to a U.S. destination. According to CDC protocols, if a sick traveler has a contagious disease that is a risk to others on board the airplane, CDC works with local and state health departments and international public health agencies to\u00a0contact exposed passengers and crew.\nBe sure to give the airline your current contact information when booking your ticket so you can be notified if you are exposed to a sick traveler on a flight.\nFor more information, see the CDC webpage Protecting Travelers\u2019 Health from Airport to Community: Investigating Contagious Diseases on Flights."}, {"question": "Should I delay going on a cruise?", "answer": "Yes. CDC recommends that all travelers avoid all cruise ship travel worldwide, including river boats. Reports of COVID-19 on cruise ships highlight the risk of infection to cruise ship passengers and crew. Like many other viruses, COVID-19 appears to spread more easily between people in close quarters aboard ships. At this time, cruise ship passenger operations remain suspended in U.S. waters under CDC\u2019s Framework for Conditional Sailing Order."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Who is at risk for infection with SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19?", "answer": "Currently, those at greatest risk of infection are persons who have had prolonged, unprotected close contact (i.e., within 6 feet for 15 minutes or longer) with a patient with confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, regardless of whether the patient has symptoms. Persons frequently in congregate settings (e.g., homeless shelters, assisted living facilities, college or university dormitories) are at increased risk of acquiring infection because of the increased likelihood of close contact. Those who live in or have recently been to areas with sustained transmission may also be at higher risk of infection. All persons can reduce the risk to themselves and others by wearing a mask, practicing physical distancing, washing their hands often, and taking other prevention measures. For more information, see Risk Assessment and Your Health."}, {"question": "What should healthcare providers (HCP) do outside of work to prevent transmission of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19?", "answer": "To prevent transmission of SARS-CoV-2 outside of work, HCP should follow CDC\u2019s Guidance on Public Health Recommendations for Community-Related Exposure and the general guidance at Your Health. Because of their potential for exposure to SARS-CoV-2 at work, some HCP may choose to implement extra measures when arriving home from providing healthcare, such as removing any clothing they wore while delivering healthcare, taking off their shoes, washing their clothing, and immediately showering. However, these practices are optional and based on a personal decision; there is insufficient evidence to determine whether these additional practices can lower infection risk.\nBecause person-to-person transmission through respiratory droplets within a radius of 6 feet is currently thought to be the main way the virus spreads, everyone \u2014 including HCP \u2014can reduce the risk to themselves and others by wearing a mask, practicing physical distancing, washing their hands often, and taking other prevention measures.\nCDC updates its guidance, including specific guidance in the links above, as additional information becomes available."}, {"question": "Who is at risk for severe COVID-19?", "answer": "COVID-19 is a new disease and CDC is learning more about it every day. Among adults, the risk for severe illness from COVID-19 increases with age, with older adults at highest risk. Severe illness means that the person with COVID-19 may require hospitalization, intensive care, or a ventilator to help them breathe, or they may even die. People of any age with certain underlying medical conditions\u00a0are also at increased risk for severe illness from SARS-CoV-2 infection.\nSee also Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) and Information for Healthcare Professionals: COVID-19 and Underlying Conditions."}, {"question": "If my patient has an underlying medical condition associated with an increased risk of severe disease from COVID-19, what is my patient\u2019s risk of developing severe COVID-19, and what should I tell my patient to reduce their risk?", "answer": "Stay up to date on the latest evidence about the risk for patients with underlying medical conditions. CDC analyzes data to determine the level of risk for people with underlying medical conditions and will provide updates over time as new information is available.\nYou know your patients\u2019 overall health and how well their conditions are managed. Use your clinical judgment to evaluate each patient\u2019s level of risk.\nHelp patients manage their underlying conditions to the best of their ability, encouraging them to take medicines as prescribed and ensuring that patients have sufficient medication and supplies. For example, you may prescribe 3-month supplies of medications to ensure they have access to sufficient medications.\nExplain to all patients which symptoms of their chronic conditions require emergency care or in-person visits. Stress the importance of obtaining emergency care if needed.\nReassure your patients who require emergency care that emergency departments (ED) have infection prevention plans to protect them from acquiring SARS-CoV-2 infection in the ED.\nTell patients with underlying medical conditions\u00a0that increase their risk of severe illness or poorer outcomes from COVID-19 to:\n\nTake precautions to reduce the risk of getting COVID-19.\nClosely follow your care plans for managing their chronic disease, including, for example, achieving better glycemic or blood pressure control.\nSeek emergency care if any of their underlying medical conditions worsen and require immediate attention.\n\n\nEncourage all patients, regardless of risk, to:\n\nTake steps to protect themselves.\nCall their healthcare provider if you are sick with a fever, cough, or shortness of breath.\nFollow CDC travel guidelines and the recommendations of your state and local health officials.\n\n\nFear and anxiety about a new disease can feel overwhelming, especially for those with underlying risk factors, those in close contact with infected patients, and those with sources of stress outside the workplace. Follow guidance on ways to take care of yourself and encourage your patients to do the same.\n\nAdditional resources for healthcare providers"}, {"question": "Are pregnant healthcare providers (HCP) at increased risk for adverse outcomes if they care for patients with COVID-19?", "answer": "Pregnant HCP should follow\u202frisk assessment\u202fand\u202finfection control\u202fguidelines for HCP exposed to patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19. Adherence to recommended infection prevention and control practices is an important part of protecting all HCP in healthcare settings. Based on what we know at this time,\u202fpregnant and recently pregnant people are at an increased risk for severe illness from SARS-CoV-2 infection compared to non-pregnant people. In addition,\u00a0pregnant people with COVID-19\u00a0are at increased risk for preterm birth\u00a0and\u00a0there\u00a0might be at an\u00a0increased risk of\u00a0other\u00a0poor\u202fpregnancy outcomes. Facilities may want to consider limiting exposure of\u202fpregnant HCP to patients with confirmed or suspected COVID-19, especially during higher risk procedures (e.g., aerosol-generating procedures) if feasible based on staffing availability.\nAdditional information about COVID-19 during pregnancy"}, {"question": "What is multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) and who is at risk?", "answer": "CDC continues to investigate multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) associated with COVID-19. Children and adolescents with MIS-C have presented with a persistent fever and a variety of signs and symptoms including involvement of multiple organs (e.g., cardiac, gastrointestinal, renal, hematologic, dermatologic, neurologic) and elevated inflammatory markers. CDC is collaborating with domestic and international partners to better understand this new syndrome, including how common it is and its risk factors. For more information, including a full case definition and how to report MIS-C to your health department, visit MIS-C Information for Healthcare Providers."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Are the alternatives to the 14-day quarantine described in the Options to Reduce Quarantine for Contacts of Persons with SARS-CoV-2 Infection Using Symptom Monitoring and Diagnostic Testing recommended for healthcare facilities?", "answer": "Given the need for often extensive and close contact between patients and healthcare personnel, a 14-day quarantine period continues to be recommended for patients receiving healthcare and healthcare personnel with exposures to SARS-CoV-2 warranting quarantine1 or work restrictions, respectively.\u00a0 This option maximally reduces post-quarantine transmission risk and is the strategy with the greatest collective experience at present.\nAlternatives to the 14-day quarantine period are described in the Options to Reduce Quarantine for Contacts of Persons with SARS-CoV-2 Infection Using Symptom Monitoring and Diagnostic Testing.\u00a0 Healthcare facilities could consider these alternatives as a measure to mitigate staffing shortages, space limitations, or PPE supply shortages but, due to the special nature of healthcare settings (e.g., patients at risk for worse outcomes, critical nature of healthcare personnel, challenges with social distancing), not as a preferred option.\nHealthcare facilities should understand that shortening the duration of work restriction or patient quarantine might pose additional transmission risk.\u00a0 They should also counsel patients and healthcare personnel about the need to monitor for and immediately self-isolate if symptoms occur during the 14 days after their exposure and the importance of adhering to all recommended non-pharmaceutical interventions.\n1In healthcare settings, patients under quarantine are typically isolated in a single-person room and cared for by healthcare personnel using all PPE recommended for a patient with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection.\u00a0 However, these patients should not be cohorted with patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection unless they are also confirmed to have SARS-CoV-2 infection through testing."}, {"question": "Are there circumstances in healthcare settings when repeat testing for SARS-CoV-2 or quarantining might be considered for asymptomatic patients and residents who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection but are re-exposed to SARS-CoV-2 within 3 months of their prior infection?", "answer": "CDC currently recommends that asymptomatic patients and residents who have recovered and are within 3 months of a positive test for SARS-CoV-2 infection may not need to be quarantined or tested following re-exposure to SARS-CoV-2. However, there might be clinical scenarios in which the certainty about a prior infection or the durability of the immune response exist, for which providers could consider testing for SARS-CoV-2 and recommending quarantine following an exposure that occurs less than 3 months after their initial infection. Examples could include:\n\nPatients or residents with underlying immunocompromising conditions (e.g., patient after organ transplantation) or who become immune compromised (e.g., receive chemotherapy) in the 3 months following SARS-CoV-2 infection and who might have an increased risk for reinfection. However, data on which specific conditions may lead to higher risk and the magnitude of risk are not available.\nPatients or residents for whom there is concern that their initial diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection might have been based on a false positive test result (e.g., resident was asymptomatic, antigen test positive, and a confirmatory nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) was not performed).\nPatients or residents for whom there is evidence that they were exposed to a novel SARS-CoV-2 variant (e.g., exposed to a person known to be infected with a novel variant) for which the risk of reinfection might be higher\n\nCDC continues to actively investigate the frequency of reinfection and the circumstances surrounding these episodes, including the role that new variants might play in reinfection, and will adjust guidance as necessary as more information becomes available."}, {"question": "Do CDC\u2019s interim infection prevention and control recommendations for COVID-19 apply to psychiatric hospitals or other behavioral health facilities?", "answer": "Yes. To keep patients and healthcare personnel (HCP) healthy and safe, CDC\u2019s infection prevention and control guidance applies to all settings where healthcare is delivered. However, as with any guidance, facilities can tailor certain recommendations to their setting. For example, inpatient psychiatric care includes communal experiences and group activities that may need to continue. If so, these activities might need to be adapted to align with social distancing recommendations. Other recommended infection control measures (for example, ensuring access to alcohol-based hand sanitizer, cohorting patients with COVID-19 and assigning dedicated staff, or implementing universal source control measures) might not be safe or appropriate to implement in all locations or for all patients due to security and behavioral concerns.\nChallenges and potential solutions specific to behavioral health settings might include:\n\nCohorting\n\nChallenge: To prevent transmission, it is generally recommended that patients with COVID-19 be transferred to a separate area of the facility where they can be cared for by dedicated HCP. Because of security concerns or specialized care needs, it might not be possible to cohort certain patients together or change HCP assigned to their care.\nPotential Solutions: When cohorting is not possible, implement measures to maintain social distancing (at least 6 feet) between patients with COVID-19 and others on the unit. Ideally, this would include a separate bathroom for COVID-19 patients. Ensure HCP wear all recommended personal protective equipment (PPE)\u00a0when caring for patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19.\n\n\nGroup Therapy Sessions\n\nChallenge: Group counseling, therapy, and discussion sessions are a critical component of psychiatric\u00a0treatment and care plans, but the traditional set-up for these activities is not compatible with social distancing recommendations.\nPotential Solutions: When possible, use virtual methods, or decrease group size so social distancing can be maintained. In the event that COVID-19 is transmitted in the facility, sessions should stop or move to a video discussion forum until additional infection prevention measures are in place to stop the spread.\n\n\nCloth Face Coverings\n\nChallenge: For some patients, the use of cloth face coverings or facemasks might pose an additional danger or may cause distress. Some patients may be unable or unwilling to use them as intended. Elastic and cloth straps can be used for strangling oneself or others, and metal nasal bridges can be used for self-harm or as a weapon.\nPotential Solutions: Consider allowing patients at low risk for misuse to wear cloth face coverings or facemasks, with a preference for those with short ear-loops rather than longer ties. Consider use of cloth face coverings or facemasks during supervised group activities. Ensure that HCP interacting with patients who cannot wear a cloth face covering or facemask are wearing eye protection and a facemask (or a respirator if the patient is suspected to have COVID-19 and respirators are available).\n\n\nAlcohol-based Hand Sanitizer\n\nChallenge: While alcohol-based hand sanitizer (ABHS) containing 60-95% alcohol is an important tool to increase adherence to hand hygiene recommendations, ABHS must be used carefully in psychiatric facilities to ensure it is not ingested by patients.\nPotential Solutions: Consider not placing ABHS in patients\u2019 rooms in psychiatric facilities, nor in locations where the patients have unsupervised access. Encourage frequent hand washing with soap and water for patients and HCP. Consider providing personal, pocket-sized ABHS dispensers for HCP.\n\n\nDining\n\nChallenge: As part of social distancing, communal dining is generally not recommended. However, eating needs to remain supervised due to the potential for self-harm with eating utensils and because commonly used psychiatric medications may cause side effects (e.g., tardive dyskinesia, dysphagia, hypo- and hypersalivation) that increase choking risk for patients.\nPotential Solutions: One option is to position staff in patients\u2019 rooms to monitor their dining. Another option is to allow communal dining in shifts so that staff can monitor patients while ensuring they remain at least 6 feet apart. A third option is to have patients sit in appropriately spaced chairs in the hallway outside their rooms so they can be monitored while they eat.\n\n\nSmoking\n\nChallenge: A higher proportion of psychiatric patients smoke cigarettes compared to the general population. Patients might congregate in outdoor smoking spaces without practicing appropriate social distancing.\nPotential Solutions: Limit the number of patients allowed to access smoking spaces at the same time, and position staff to observe and ensure patients are practicing appropriate physical distancing."}, {"question": "If a long-term care facility has a resident or staff member with suspected or confirmed COVID-19, how and to whom should this be communicated?", "answer": "Facilities should follow the reporting requirements of their state or jurisdiction. Those regulated by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) (e.g., nursing homes) should also follow all CMS requirementsexternal icon, which are being updated to include new requirements for reporting to CDC and to residents and their representatives.\nIn addition, CDC recommends that health departments\u00a0be promptly notified about:\n\nResidents or healthcare personnel (HCP) with suspected or confirmed COVID-19,\nResidents with severe respiratory infection resulting in hospitalization or death, and\n\u00a0\u2265 3 residents or HCP with new-onset respiratory symptoms within 72 hours of each other.\n\nThese could signal an outbreak of COVID-19 or other respiratory disease in the facility. The health department can provide important guidance to assist with case finding and halting transmission.\nThe facility should also have a plan and mechanism to regularly communicate with residents, family members, and HCP, including if cases of COVID-19 are identified in the facility. Often, information in nursing homes is communicated through town hall meetings and staff meetings, along with letters or emails. However, during the COVID-19 pandemic, in-person gatherings should not occur. Instead, communication should occur through virtual meetings over phone or web platforms. These should be supplemented with written communications that provide contact information for a staff member who can respond to questions or concerns. Communications should include information describing the current situation, plans for limiting spread within the facility, and recommended actions they can take to protect themselves and others. Facilities should make this information available in a timely manner and offer periodic updates as the situation develops and more information becomes available."}, {"question": "Is a negative test for SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, required before a hospitalized patient can be discharged to a nursing home?", "answer": "No. For patients hospitalized with SARS-CoV-2 infection, decisions about discharge from the hospital should be based on their clinical status and the ability of an accepting facility to meet their care needs and adhere to recommended infection prevention and control practices. Decisions about hospital discharge are distinct from decisions about discontinuation of Transmission-Based Precautions.\nFor patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, decisions about discontinuing Transmission-Based Precautions should be based on the strategies outlined here. The test-based strategy is recommended only for use in limited circumstances.\nIf a patient with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection has not met criteria for discontinuing Transmission-Based Precautions, they should be transferred to a facility with the ability to adhere to infection prevention and control recommendations\u00a0for the care of residents with SARS-CoV-2 infection, including placement in a unit or area of the facility designated to care for residents with SARS-CoV-2 infection and provision of recommended personal protective equipment to healthcare personnel.\nIf the patient has met the criteria for discontinuing Transmission-Based Precautions, they do not require additional restrictions.\nA patient hospitalized for non-COVID-related illnesses who is not known to have SARS-CoV-2 infection can be transferred to a nursing home without testing. To ensure a patient was not exposed and might subsequently develop SARS-CoV-2 infection, nursing homes should place the patient in Transmission-based Precautions\u00a0in a separate observation area or in a single-person room for 14 days after admission.\nAs part of universal source control measures, all residents (including those described in the scenarios above) should wear a cloth face covering or facemask (if tolerated) whenever they leave their room."}, {"question": "During the COVID-19 pandemic, are there special considerations for surgical and other procedural care settings, including performance of aerosol-generating procedures (AGPs)?", "answer": "As part of routine practices, healthcare personnel (HCP) should be applying Standard Precautions. HCP should always deliberately assess potential risks of exposure to infectious material before engaging in activities and procedures in healthcare delivery. Based on their risk assessment, safe work practices, including engineering controls that reduce the release of infectious material, administrative controls,\u00a0and use of personal protective equipment (PPE) should be implemented at the point of care according to CDC guidelines and standards of practice for the activity performed.\nTo reduce SARS-CoV-2 exposure during the COVID-19 pandemic, CDC recommends that facilities:\n\nconsider nonoperative approaches when feasible;\nminimize the use of procedures or techniques that might produce infectious aerosols when feasible;\nminimize the number of people in the operating or procedure room to reduce exposures;\nuse the extent of community transmission and an assessment of the likelihood for patient harm if care is delayed to make decisions about cancelling or postponing elective surgeries and procedures; and\nimplement universal source control measures, which includes having patients wear a cloth face covering (as tolerated) and having HCP wear a facemask at all times while they are in the healthcare facility.\n\nIf surgery or procedures cannot be postponed, HCP caring for patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 should adhere to all recommended infection prevention and control practices for COVID-19.\u00a0 This includes:\n\nUsing all recommended PPE: an N95 or equivalent or higher-level respirator (or facemask if respirators are not available), eye protection, gloves, and a gown.\n\nRespirators with exhalation valves should not be used during surgical procedures as unfiltered exhaled breath would compromise the sterile field.\nIf shortages exist, N95 or equivalent or higher-level respirators should be prioritized for procedures involving higher risk techniques (e.g., that generate potentially infectious aerosols) or that involve anatomic regions where viral loads might be higher (e.g., nose and throat, oropharynx, respiratory tract).\n\n\nAs part of routine practice, HCP should also be using additional engineering controls for source control, when applicable (e.g., smoke evacuation devices).\n\nBecause SARS-CoV-2 can be transmitted by individuals who are infected but do not have symptoms, some infected individuals will not be identified by screening for clinical signs and symptoms.\u00a0 HCP providing surgical or procedural care to patients not suspected of having SARS-CoV-2 infection should use a tiered approach based on the level of community transmission to inform the need for universal eye protection and respirator use.\u00a0 HCP should continue to use eye protection or an N95 or equivalent or higher-level respirator whenever recommended for patient care as a part of Standard or Transmission-Based Precautions.\nIn addition to the use of universal PPE and source control in healthcare settings, targeted SARS-CoV-2 testing of patients without signs or symptoms of COVID-19 might be used to identify those with asymptomatic or pre-symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection and further reduce risk for exposures in some healthcare settings. Depending on guidance from local and state health departments, testing availability, and how rapidly results are available, facilities can consider implementing pre-admission or pre-procedure diagnostic testing with authorized nucleic acid or antigen detection assays for SARS-CoV-2.\nTesting results might inform decisions about rescheduling elective procedures or about the need for additional Transmission-Based Precautions when caring for the patient. Limitations of using this testing strategy include obtaining negative results in patients during their incubation period who later become infectious and false negative test results, depending on the test method used."}, {"question": "Why does CDC continue to recommend respiratory protection equivalent or higher to the level provided by an N95 disposable filtering facepiece respirator for care of patients with known or suspected COVID-19?", "answer": "CDC\u2019s guidance to use NIOSH-approved N95 disposable filtering facepiece or higher level respirators when providing care for patients with suspected or known COVID-19 is based on the current understanding of SARS-CoV-2 and related respiratory viruses.\nCurrent data suggest that close-range aerosol transmission by droplet and inhalation, and contact followed by self-delivery to the eyes, nose, or mouth are likely routes of transmission. Long-range aerosol transmission, such as is seen with measles, has not been a feature of SARS-CoV-2.\nPotential routes of close-range transmission include splashes and sprays of infectious material onto mucous membranes and inhalation of infectious virions exhaled by an infected person. The relative contribution of each of these is not known for SARS-Co-V-2.\nFacemasks commonly used during surgical procedures will provide barrier protection against droplet sprays contacting mucous membranes of the nose and mouth, but they are not designed to protect wearers from inhaling small particles. N95 and higher level respirators, such as other disposable filtering facepiece respirators, powered air-purifying respirators (PAPRs), and elastomeric respirators, provide both barrier and respiratory protection because of their tight fit and filtration characteristics.\nRespirators should be used as part of a respiratory protection program that provides staff with medical evaluations, training, and fit testing.\nAlthough facemasks are routinely used for the care of patients with common viral respiratory infections, N95 or higher level respirators are routinely recommended for emerging pathogens like SARS CoV-2, which have the potential for transmission via small particles, the ability to cause severe infections, and no specific treatments or vaccines.\nCDC recommendations acknowledge the current challenges with limited supplies of N95s and other respirators. Facilities that do not have sufficient supplies of N95s and other respirators for all patient care should prioritize their use for activities and procedures that pose high risks of generating infectious aerosols and use facemasks for care that does not involve those activities or procedures. Detailed\u00a0strategies for optimizing the supply of N95 respirators\u00a0are available on the CDC website. Once availability of supplies is reestablished, the guidance states that the use of N95 and higher level respirators should resume."}, {"question": "What personal protective equipment (PPE) should be worn by individuals transporting patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection within a healthcare facility? For example, what PPE should be worn when transporting the patient to radiology for imaging that cannot be performed in the patient room?", "answer": "In general, transport and movement of a patient with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection outside of their room should be limited to medically essential purposes. If being transported outside of the room, such as to radiology, healthcare personnel (HCP) in the receiving area should be notified in advance of transporting the patient. For transport, the patient should wear a facemask or cloth face covering (if tolerated) to contain secretions and be covered with a clean sheet.\nIf transport personnel must prepare the patient for transport (e.g., transfer them to the wheelchair or gurney), transport personnel should wear\u00a0all recommended PPE\u00a0(gloves, a gown, respiratory protection that is at least as protective as a fit tested NIOSH-certified disposable N95 filtering facepiece respirator or facemask\u2014if a respirator is not available\u2014and eye protection [i.e., goggles or disposable face shield that covers the front and sides of the face]). This recommendation is needed because these interactions typically involve close, often face-to-face, contact with the patient in an enclosed space (e.g., patient room). Once the patient has been transferred to the wheelchair or gurney (and prior to exiting the room), transporters should remove their gown and gloves and perform hand hygiene.\nThe transporter should continue to wear a respirator or facemask.\u00a0 The continued use of eye protection by the transporter is also recommended if there is potential that the patient might not be able to tolerate their facemask or cloth face covering for the duration of transport.\u00a0 \u00a0Additional PPE should not be required unless there is an anticipated need to provide medical assistance during transport (e.g., helping the patient replace a dislodged facemask).\nAfter arrival at their destination, receiving personnel (e.g., in radiology) and the transporter (if assisting with transfer) should perform hand hygiene and wear\u00a0all recommended PPE. If still wearing their original respirator or facemask and eye protection, the transporter should take care to avoid self-contamination when donning the remainder of the recommended PPE. This cautious approach will be refined and updated as more information becomes available and as response needs change in the United States.\nInterim guidance for EMS personnel transporting patients with confirmed or suspected SARS-CoV-2 infection is\u00a0available here. EMS personnel should wear all recommended PPE because they are providing direct medical care and in close contact with the patient for longer periods of time."}, {"question": "What personal protective equipment (PPE) should be worn by environmental services (EVS) personnel who clean and disinfect rooms of hospitalized patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection?", "answer": "In general, only essential personnel should enter the room of patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection. Healthcare facilities should consider assigning daily cleaning and disinfection of high-touch surfaces to nursing personnel who will already be in the room providing care to the patient. If this responsibility is assigned to EVS personnel, they should wear all\u00a0recommended PPE\u00a0when in the room. PPE should be removed upon leaving the room, immediately followed by performance of hand hygiene.\nAfter discharge, terminal cleaning can be performed by EVS personnel. They should delay entry into the room until time has elapsed for enough air changes to remove potentially infectious particles. After this time has elapsed, EVS personnel can enter the room and should wear a facemask\u00a0(for source control) along with a gown and gloves when performing terminal cleaning. Eye protection should be added if splashes or sprays during cleaning and disinfection activities are anticipated or otherwise required based on the selected cleaning products. Shoe covers are not recommended at this time for personnel caring for patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection."}, {"question": "Which procedures are considered aerosol generating procedures in healthcare settings?", "answer": "Some procedures performed on patients are more likely to generate higher concentrations of infectious respiratory aerosols than coughing, sneezing, talking, or breathing. These aerosol generating procedures (AGPs) potentially put healthcare personnel and others at an increased risk for pathogen exposure and infection.\nDevelopment of a comprehensive list of AGPs for healthcare settings has not been possible, due to limitations in available data on which procedures may generate potentially infectious aerosols and the challenges in determining if reported transmissions during AGPs are due to aerosols or other exposures.\nThere is neither expert consensus, nor sufficient supporting data, to create a definitive and comprehensive list of AGPs for healthcare settings.\nCommonly performed medical procedures that are often considered AGPs, or that create uncontrolled respiratory secretions, include:\n\nopen suctioning of airways\nsputum induction\ncardiopulmonary resuscitation\nendotracheal intubation and extubation\nnon-invasive ventilation (e.g., BiPAP, CPAP)\nbronchoscopy\nmanual ventilation\n\nBased on limited available data, it is uncertain whether aerosols generated from some procedures may be infectious, such as:\n\nnebulizer administration*\nhigh flow O2 delivery\n\n*Aerosols generated by nebulizers are derived from medication in the nebulizer. It is uncertain whether potential associations between performing this common procedure and increased risk of infection might be due to aerosols generated by the procedure or due to increased contact between those administering the nebulized medication and infected patients.\nReferences related to aerosol generating procedures:\nTran K, Cimon K, Severn M, Pessoa-Silva CL, Conly J (2012) Aerosol Generating Procedures and Risk of Transmission of Acute Respiratory Infections to Healthcare Workers: A Systematic Review. PLoS ONE 7(4);\u00a0https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3338532/#!po=72.2222external iconexternal iconexternal icon)."}, {"question": "How long does an examination room need to remain vacant after being occupied by a patient with confirmed or suspected COVID-19?", "answer": "Although spread of SARS-CoV-2 is believed to be primarily via respiratory droplets, the contribution of small respirable particles to close proximity transmission is currently uncertain. Airborne transmission from person-to-person over long distances is unlikely.\nThe amount of time that the air inside an examination room remains potentially infectious is not known and may depend on a number of factors including the size of the room, the number of air changes per hour, how long the patient was in the room, if the patient was coughing or sneezing, and if an aerosol-generating procedure was performed. Facilities will need to consider these factors when deciding when the vacated room can be entered by someone who is not wearing PPE.\nFor a patient who was not coughing or sneezing, did not undergo an aerosol-generating procedure, and occupied the room for a short period of time (e.g., a few minutes), any risk to HCP and subsequent patients likely dissipates over a matter of minutes. However, for a patient who was coughing and remained in the room for a longer period of time or underwent an aerosol-generating procedure, the risk period is likely longer.\nFor these higher risk scenarios, it is reasonable to apply a similar time period as that used for pathogens spread by the airborne route (e.g., measles, tuberculosis) and to restrict HCP and patients without PPE from entering the room until sufficient time has elapsed for enough air changes to remove potentially infectious particles.\nGeneral guidance on\u00a0clearance rates under differing ventilation conditions\u00a0is available.\nIn addition to ensuring sufficient time for enough air changes to remove potentially infectious particles, HCP should clean and disinfect environmental surfaces and shared equipment before the room is used for another patient."}, {"question": "My hospital is experiencing a shortage of isolation gowns. To preserve our supply, can we stop using gowns for the care of patients with methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) and other endemic multidrug-resistant organisms (MDROs), and Clostridioides difficile?", "answer": "CDC has released information about\u00a0strategies to optimize the supply of isolation gowns. Healthcare facilities should refer to that guidance and implement the recommended strategies to optimize their current supply of gowns. This includes shifting toward the use of washable cloth gowns, if feasible.\nThe use of gowns as part of Contact Precautions in the context of MDROs has been implemented primarily to reduce the risk of transmission to other patients rather than to protect healthcare personnel (HCP). Facilities with shortages could consider suspending the use of gowns for the care of patients with endemic MDROs, such as MRSA, VRE, and ESBL-producing Gram-negative bacilli except as required for\u00a0Standard Precautions. Facilities should assess their local epidemiology to determine which MDROs are considered endemic. Regardless of the use of gowns, HCP at facilities should continue to wear gloves for contact with these patients and their environment. Hand hygiene should continue to be emphasized. Facilities should also attempt to place patients colonized or infected with an MDRO in a private room, if available.\n\nCaring for patients who have highly resistant Gram-negative organisms (e.g., carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriacae) and other MDROs (e.g.,\u00a0Candida auris) that are not considered endemic:\u00a0\u00a0Rather than gowns being donned for every room entry, they should be reserved for use as part of Standard Precautions\u00a0and also prioritized for high-contact patient care activities that pose highest risk for transfer of pathogens from the patient to HCP. Examples of such high-contact care activities include dressing, bathing/showering, transferring, providing hygiene, changing linens, changing briefs or assisting with toileting, device care or use (central line, urinary catheter, feeding tube, tracheostomy/ventilator), and wound care. To further preserve gowns, HCP are recommended to bundle high-contact care activities as part of individual care encounters. \u00a0Regardless of the use of gowns, HCP at facilities should continue to wear gloves for contact with these patients and their environment. Hand hygiene should continue to be emphasized. Facilities should also attempt to place patients colonized or infected with an MDRO in a private room, if available.\nCaring for patients with\u00a0Clostridioides difficile\u00a0infections (CDI):\u00a0\u00a0Facilities should continue using Contact Precautions (putting on a gown and gloves upon entry into the patient\u2019s room and placing the patient in a private room) for the care of symptomatic patients with CDI.\u00a0 As part of a\u00a0supplemental strategy to prevent transmission of CDI, some facilities have implemented Contact Precautions for the care of patients at high risk for CDI who have asymptomatic carriage of\u00a0Clostridioides difficile. There are limited data about the role of asymptomatic carriage in transmission of CDI. In this setting of a critical national shortage of gowns, facilities should consider suspending this approach until the shortage is addressed. Gowns should still be used as part of\u00a0Standard Precautions."}, {"question": "A healthcare provider at our facility was recently diagnosed with COVID-19. What time period and criteria do we use to determine the patients, visitors, and other healthcare personnel (HCP) who might have been exposed to this individual while he/she was potentially infectious?", "answer": "Anyone who had prolonged close contact (within 6 feet for a cumulative total of 15 minutes\u00a0or more over a 24-hour period) with the infected healthcare provider might have been exposed.\n\nIf the provider had COVID-19 symptoms, the provider is considered potentially infectious beginning 2 days before symptoms first appeared until the provider meets criteria to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or Home Isolation.\nIf the provider did not have symptoms, collecting information about when the provider may have been exposed could help inform the period when they were infectious.\n\nIf an exposure is identified. The provider should be considered potentially infectious beginning 2 days after the exposure until criteria to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or Home Isolation are met.\nIf the date of exposure cannot be determined. For the purposes of contact tracing, it is reasonable to use a cutoff of 2 days before the specimen testing positive for SARS-CoV-2 was collected as the starting point, continuing until the criteria to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or Home Isolation are met. Although the infectious period is generally accepted to be 10 days after onset of infection, eliciting contacts during the entire 10 days before obtaining the specimen that tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 is likely inefficient.\u00a0 In most situations an exposed provider cannot recall all contacts over the preceding 10 days.\u00a0 Also, because recent data suggest that asymptomatic persons may have a lower viral burden at diagnosis than symptomatic persons, the additional resources required may divert case investigation and contact tracing resources away from activities most likely to interrupt ongoing transmission.\n\n\n\nContact tracing is generally recommended for anyone who had prolonged close contact with the person with SARS-CoV-2 infection during these time periods. \u00a0While this question addresses exposure to a potentially infectious provider, the following actions are also recommended if the potentially infectious individual is a patient or visitor.\nRecommended actions for HCP, patients, and visitors:\n\nPerform a risk assessment and apply work restrictions for other HCP who were exposed to the infected provider based on whether these HCP had prolonged, close contact and what PPE they were wearing. More detailed information is available in the Interim U.S. Guidance for Risk Assessment and Work Restrictions for Healthcare Personnel with Potential Exposure to COVID-19.\nPlace exposed patients who are currently admitted to the healthcare facility in appropriate Transmission-Based Precautions and monitor them for onset of SARS-CoV-2 infection until 14 days after their last exposure.\nContacts who are within 3 months of onset of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection might not require quarantine or testing if they remain asymptomatic.\nPerform contact tracing of exposed patients who are not currently admitted to the healthcare facility and for visitors as described in Health Departments: Interim Guidance on Developing a COVID-19 Case Investigation and Contact Tracing Plan.\n\nHealthcare facilities should have a process for notifying the health department about known or suspected cases of SARS-CoV-2 infection, and should establish a plan, in consultation with local public health authorities, for how exposures in a healthcare facility will be investigated and how contact tracing will be performed.\u00a0 The plan should address the following:\n\nWho is responsible for identifying contacts and notifying potentially exposed individuals?\nHow will such notifications occur?\nWhat actions and follow-up are recommended for those who were exposed?\n\nContact tracing should be carried out in a way that protects the confidentiality of affected individuals to the extent possible and is consistent with applicable laws and regulations.\u00a0 HCP and patients who are currently admitted to the facility or were transferred to another healthcare facility should be prioritized for notification.\u00a0 These groups, if infected, have the potential to expose a large number of individuals at higher risk for severe disease, or in the situation of admitted patients, be at higher risk for severe illness themselves.\nInformation for health departments about case investigation and contact tracing is available in the Health Departments:\u00a0 Interim Guidance on Developing a COVID-19 Case Investigation and Contact Tracing Plan.\u00a0 This guidance could also be helpful to healthcare facilities performing such activities."}, {"question": "A healthcare provider in our facility worked while infected with SARS-CoV-2. However, the provider wore a facemask at all times while interacting with patients. Are the patients at risk for SARS-CoV-2 and should they be notified?", "answer": "Anyone who had prolonged close contact (within 6 feet for at least 15 minutes) should be considered potentially exposed.\u00a0 The use of a facemask\u00a0for source control and adherence to other recommended infection prevention and control (IPC) measures (e.g., hand hygiene) by the provider help to reduce the risk of transmission or severe illness. In areas with moderate to substantial community transmission, patients are already at risk for exposure to SARS-CoV-2 due to exposures outside their home and should be alert to the development of signs or symptoms consistent with COVID-19.\nThe following should be considered when determining which patients are at higher risk for transmission and might be prioritized for evaluation and testing:\n\nFacemask use by the patient \u2013 Mirroring the risk assessment guidance for healthcare personnel, patients not wearing a facemask would likely be at higher risk for infection compared to those that were wearing a facemask.\nType of interaction that occurred between the patient and infected provider \u2013 An interaction involving manipulation or prolonged close contact with the patient\u2019s eyes, nose, or mouth (e.g., dental cleaning) likely poses higher risk of transmission to the patient compared to other interactions (e.g., blood pressure check).\nPPE used by infected HCP \u2013 HCP wearing a facemask\u00a0(or respirator) and face shield that extends down below the chin might have had better source control than wearing only a facemask. Note that respirators with exhalation valves might not provide source control.\nCurrent status of patient \u2013 Is the patient currently admitted to a hospital or long-term care facility?\u00a0 These individuals, if infected, can be at higher risk for severe illness and have the potential to expose large numbers of individuals at risk for severe disease."}, {"question": "Questions addressing the proper handling of healthcare personnel (HCP) who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 Infection, but are still within 3 months of onset of their prior infection.", "answer": "1. If HCP have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection but have a high-risk exposure\u00a0within 3 months of their initial infection to a patient with SARS-CoV-2 infection, should they be restricted from work for 14 days after the exposure?\nCDC has posted interim guidance for risk assessment and work restrictions for HCP with potential exposure to SARS-CoV-2. Because of their often extensive and close contact with people who are at high risk for severe illness, this guidance recommends a conservative approach to HCP monitoring and applying work restrictions to prevent transmission from potentially contagious HCP to patients, other HCP, and visitors. Review of currently available evidence\u00a0suggests that most people do not become re-infected in the 3 months after SARS-CoV-2 infection. Testing of asymptomatic people during this 3-month period is complicated by the fact that some people have detectable virus from their prior infection during this period; a positive test during this period may more likely result from a prior infection rather than a new infection that poses risk for transmission.\nIn light of this, exposed HCP who are within 3 months of their initial infection, could continue to work, while monitoring for symptoms consistent with COVID-19 and following all recommended infection prevention and control practices\u00a0(e.g., universal use of well-fitting source control). If symptoms develop, exposed HCP should be assessed and potentially tested for SARS-CoV-2, if an alternate etiology is not identified. Some facilities might still choose to institute work restrictions for asymptomatic HCP following a higher risk exposure, particularly if there is uncertainty about a prior infection or the durability of the person\u2019s immune response. Examples could include:\n\nHCP with underlying immunocompromising conditions (e.g., after organ transplantation) or who become immune compromised (e.g., receive chemotherapy) in the 3 months following SARS-Cov-2 infection who might \u00a0be at increased risk for reinfection. However, data on which specific conditions may lead to higher risk and the magnitude of risk are not available.\nHCP for whom there is concern that their initial diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection might have been based on a false positive test result (e.g., individual was asymptomatic, antigen test positive, and a confirmatory nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) was not performed).\nHCP for whom there is evidence that they were exposed to a novel SARS-CoV-2 variant for which the risk of reinfection might be higher (e.g., exposed to a person known to be infected with a novel variant).\n\nCDC continues to actively investigate the frequency of reinfection and the circumstances surrounding these episodes, including the role that new variants might play in reinfection, and will adjust guidance as necessary as more information becomes available.\n2. If HCP within 3 months of their initial infection develop symptoms consistent with COVID-19, should they be excluded from work and retested?\nHCP within 3 months of a confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection who develop symptoms consistent with COVID-19 should be evaluated to identify potential alternative etiologies for their symptoms. If an alternate etiology for the symptoms cannot be identified, they may need to be retested for SARS-CoV-2 infection with the understanding that a positive viral test could represent residual viral particles from the previous infection, rather than new infection. Decisions about the need for and duration of work exclusion should be based upon their suspected diagnosis (e.g., influenza, SARS-CoV-2 infection).\n3. Do HCP within 3 months of their initial infection need to wear all recommended personal protective equipment (PPE) when caring for patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection? For example, if there are limited respirators, should respirators be prioritized for HCP who have not been previously infected?\nRegardless of suspected or confirmed immunity, healthcare personnel should always wear all recommended PPE when caring for patients. In situations of PPE shortages, facilities should refer to CDC strategies for optimizing PPE supply. However, as with other infectious diseases (e.g., measles), allocation of available PPE should not be based on whether HCP have been previously infected or have evidence of immunity.\n4. Should HCP within 3 months of their initial infection be preferentially assigned to care for patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection?\nWhile individuals who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection might develop some protective immunity, the duration and extent of such immunity are not known. Staffing decisions should be based on usual facility practices. Any HCP assigned to care for patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, regardless of history of infection, should follow all recommended infection prevention and control practices when providing care. Guidance on mitigating staff shortages\u00a0is also available."}, {"question": "If healthcare personnel (HCP) are living with someone who has been diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 infection, should they be excluded from work? If so, for how long?", "answer": "Yes. HCP who have any kind of exposure for which home quarantine is recommended should be excluded from work:\n\nIf HCP are able to quarantine away from the infected individual living with them, they should quarantine at home and not come into work for 14 days following their last exposure to the infected individual.\nIf HCP are not able to quarantine away from the infected individual living with them and have ongoing unprotected exposure throughout the duration of the individual\u2019s illness, they should remain in home quarantine and be excluded from work until 14 days after the infected individual meets criteria for discontinuation of home isolation.\nIf HCP develop SARS-CoV-2 infection while they are in quarantine, they should be excluded from work until they meet all return to work criteria for HCP with SARS-CoV-2 infection.\n\nHome quarantine and work exclusion of asymptomatic exposed HCP who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection in the prior 3 months might not be necessary.\u00a0 Additional information about this scenario is available here."}, {"question": "If a confirmatory test is performed on a person with a potential false-positive antigen test result or a potential false-negative result, what infection prevention and control (IPC) measures should be enacted while the result is pending?", "answer": "When confirmatory testing is performed on a person with a potential false-positive antigen test result, IPC measures should be maintained pending the result. Additional testing of close contacts can be delayed until results of confirmatory testing are available unless symptomatic individuals are identified.\n\nFor asymptomatic healthcare personnel (HCP), this includes continuing exclusion from work pending confirmatory testing.\nFor asymptomatic patients or residents, this includes placement on Transmission-Based Precautions\u00a0in a single room or, if single rooms are not available, remaining in their current room pending results of confirmatory testing. They should not be transferred to a COVID-19 unit or placed in another shared room with new roommates.\n\nGiven the generally lower sensitivity of antigen tests, people with COVID-19\u2013like symptoms who have a negative antigen test result should have a confirmatory nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT), such as reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), in most situations. Pending the results of confirmatory testing, maintain the following IPC measures:\n\nPatients and residents with COVID-19\u2013like symptoms should be placed on Transmission-Based Precautions\u00a0in a single room (not on the COVID-19 unit)\nHCP with COVID-19\u2013like symptoms should be excluded from work until the confirmatory test results are available.\n\nDespite the potential need for confirmatory testing of negative results, the initial use of antigen tests for symptomatic people is still preferred if turnaround time for a NAAT is >2 days because a positive antigen test would initiate contact tracing and implementation of IPC measures."}, {"question": "Using two masks at the same time, including the use of a cloth mask over a medical facemask*, to improve the fit of facemasks in healthcare settings", "answer": "CDC has recommended several ways to improve the fit and filtration\u00a0of masks, including covering a medical facemask with a cloth mask. However, layering masks requires special care in healthcare settings.\n\nAlthough a cloth mask can be used over a medical facemask to improve fit, there may be better alternatives such as framed \u201cfitters\u201d or using a knot-and-tuck\u00a0approach to achieve a good fit. If a good fit is achieved using a single medical facemask, additional approaches like adding layers to achieve a better fit might not be necessary.\nCloth masks are not personal protective equipment (PPE). They should not be used in place of medical facemasks or NIOSH-approved\u00a0respirators as part of Standard or Transmission-based Precautions.\nWearing a medical facemask or cloth mask over an N95 respirator is not recommended for healthcare personnel in healthcare settings except as a contingency or crisis strategy\u00a0during extended use of N95 respirators to protect the respirator from contamination during aerosol-generating procedures or procedures that might generate splashes and sprays.\nWearing a medical facemask or cloth mask under an N95 respirator is never recommended as it will interfere with the seal.\n\nIn healthcare settings, medical facemasks are used by healthcare personnel for two general purposes.\n\nFirst, as PPE to protect a healthcare worker\u2019s nose and mouth from exposure to splashes, sprays, splatter, and respiratory secretions, such as when treating patients on Droplet Precautions. When used as PPE, medical facemasks should be removed and discarded after each patient encounter unless extended use is being practiced as part of a crisis or contingency capacity strategy.\n\nIf a cloth mask is used over the medical facemask, it should be removed and laundered\u00a0after each patient encounter.\nCloth masks are not PPE and should not be used alone to protect against splashes and sprays, such as when used while treating patients on Droplet Precautions.\n\n\nSecond, for source control to cover a healthcare worker\u2019s nose and mouth to prevent spread of respiratory secretions from the healthcare worker to other people. When used for source control, medical facemasks, including cloth masks that are used to cover medical facemasks to improve the fit, may be used for the duration of a shift unless they become soiled, damaged, or hard to breathe through; medical facemasks, including cloth masks, used for source control should be removed and discarded (or laundered if a cloth mask) at least after each workday.\n\nOnce put on, healthcare personnel should not touch their medical facemask or cloth mask. If they touch or adjust their medical facemask or cloth mask, they must perform hand hygiene before and after contact.\nIf laundering at the intervals described above cannot be performed, then cloth masks should not be used by healthcare personnel in healthcare settings.\n*Medical facemasks are personal protective equipment (PPE) and are often referred to as surgical masks or procedure masks. Use facemasks according to product labeling and local, state, and federal requirements. FDA-cleared surgical masks are designed to protect against splashes and sprays and are prioritized for use when such exposures are anticipated, including surgical procedures. Facemasks that are not regulated by FDA, such as some procedure masks, which are typically used for isolation purposes, may not provide protection against splashes and sprays."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "When is someone infectious?", "answer": "The onset and duration of viral shedding and the period of infectiousness for COVID-19 are not yet known with certainty. Based on current evidence, scientists believe that persons with mild to moderate COVID-19 may shed replication-competent SARS-CoV-2 for up to 10 days\u00a0following symptom onset, while a small fraction of persons with severe COVID-19, including immunocompromised persons, may shed replication-competent virus for up to 20 days. It is possible that SARS-CoV-2 RNA may be detectable in the upper or lower respiratory tract for weeks after illness onset, similar to infections with MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV. However, detection of viral RNA does not necessarily mean that infectious virus is present. Based on existing literature, the incubation period (the time from exposure to development of symptoms) of SARS-CoV-2 and other coronaviruses (e.g., MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV) ranges from 2\u201314 days."}, {"question": "Which body fluids can spread infection?", "answer": "SARS-CoV-2 RNA has been detected in upper and lower respiratory tract specimens, and SARS-CoV-2 virus has been isolated from upper respiratory tract specimens and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid. SARS-CoV-2 RNA has been detected in blood and stool specimens, and SARS-CoV-2 virus has been isolated in cell culture from the stool of some patients, including a patient with pneumonia 15 days after symptom onset. The duration of SARS-CoV-2 RNA detection in upper and lower respiratory tract specimens and in extrapulmonary specimens is not yet known but may be several weeks or longer. Duration of several weeks or longer has been observed in cases of MERS-CoV or SARS-CoV infection. While viable, infectious SARS-CoV has been isolated from respiratory, blood, urine, and stool specimens, viable, infectious MERS-CoV has only been isolated from respiratory tract specimens. It is not yet known whether other non-respiratory body fluids from an infected person including blood, vomit, urine, breast milk, or semen can contain viable, infectious SARS-CoV-2."}, {"question": "Can people who recover from COVID-19 be re-infected with SARS-CoV-2?", "answer": "CDC is aware of recent reports indicating that persons who were previously diagnosed with COVID-19 can be re-infected. These reports can understandably cause concern. The immune response, including duration of immunity, to SARS-CoV-2 infection is not yet understood. Based on what we know from other viruses, including common human coronaviruses, some reinfections are expected. Ongoing COVID-19 studies will help establish the frequency and severity of reinfection and who might be at higher risk for reinfection. At this time, whether you have had COVID-19 or not, the best ways to prevent infection are to wear a mask in public places, stay at least 6 feet away from other people, frequently wash your hands with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, and avoid crowds and confined spaces."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "How do you test a patient for infection with SARS-CoV-2?", "answer": "Clinicians are able to access laboratory testing through state and local public health laboratories, as well as commercial and clinical laboratories across the country. The Association of Public Health Laboratoriesexternal icon provides a list of states and territories with laboratories that are using COVID-19 viral tests. For more information, see Testing in U.S.\u00a0Clinicians should direct testing questions to their state health departments. Commercial reference laboratories are also able to offer a larger volume of testing for SARS-CoV-2.\nCDC has guidance\u00a0for who should be tested, but decisions about testing are at the discretion of state and local health departments and/or individual clinicians.\nHealthcare providers should report positive \u00a0results to their local/state health department CDC does not directly collect these data directly."}, {"question": "Do existing commercially available multiple respiratory virus panels detect SARS-CoV-2?", "answer": "Yes. There are commercially developed respiratory panels with multi-pathogen molecular assays that can detect respiratory pathogens, including SARS-CoV-2, influenza, and other human coronaviruses that can cause acute respiratory illness. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) maintains a list of tests that includes viral tests with Emergency Use Authorizationexternal icon\u00a0(EUA)."}, {"question": "If a patient tests positive for another respiratory virus, should that exclude SARS-CoV-2 as a cause of illness?", "answer": "Patients can be infected with more than one virus at the same time. Coinfections with other respiratory viruses in people with COVID-19 have been reported. Therefore, identifying infection with one respiratory virus does not exclude SARS-CoV-2 virus infection."}, {"question": "Should chest CT be used for diagnosis of COVID-19?", "answer": "Clinicians considering use of chest CT scans for diagnosis or management of COVID-19 patients should consider whether such imaging will change clinical management. The American College of Radiology (ACR) recommends that CT should not be used to screen for COVID-19, or as a first-line test to diagnose COVID-19, and that CT should be used sparingly and reserved for hospitalized, symptomatic patients with specific clinical indications for CT. Appropriate infection control procedures should be followed before scanning subsequent patients. For more information see, ACR Recommendations for the use of Chest Radiography and Computed Tomography (CT) for Suspected COVID-19 Infectionexternal iconexternal icon."}, {"question": "Whom should healthcare providers notify if they suspect a patient has COVID-19?", "answer": "Healthcare providers should immediately notify infection control personnel at their facility if they suspect COVID-19 in a patient. If a patient tests positive, providers should report that positive result to their local/state health department."}, {"question": "How do you diagnose and report a potential case of multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C)?", "answer": "Patients with MIS-C have presented with a persistent fever and a variety of signs and symptoms including multiorgan (e.g., cardiac, gastrointestinal, renal, hematologic, dermatologic, neurologic) involvement and elevated inflammatory markers. Not all children will have the same symptoms. For children who may have MIS-C, further evaluation for signs of this syndrome may include (but are not limited to) chest radiograph, echocardiography, and blood testing to evaluate for evidence of inflammation.\nHealthcare providers who have cared or are caring for patients younger than 21 years of age meeting MIS-C criteria should report suspected cases to their local, state, or territorial health department. After hour phone numbers for health departments are available at the Council of State and Territorial Epidemiologists website.external icon \u00a0For additional reporting questions, please contact CDC\u2019s 24-hour Emergency Operations Center at 770-488-7100. For more information, including a full case definition, please visit MIS-C Information for Healthcare Providers."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "How can public health jurisdictions prioritize testing across nursing homes when resources are limited?", "answer": "Generally, nursing homes are recommended to test:\n\nResidents and healthcare personnel (HCP) with signs or symptoms of COVID-19\nResidents and HCP who are asymptomatic in response to an outbreak in the facility (i.e., a new SARS-CoV-2 infection in any HCP or any SARS-CoV-2 infection in a resident)\nAll residents and HCP once and serially test HCP who are asymptomatic in facilities without an outbreak as required by CMSexternal icon.\n\nHealth departments should have a plan on how to prioritize facilities\u00a0when testing capacity is limited.\nIf testing capacity is limited for SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, prioritize testing (1) of residents and healthcare personnel (HCP) with signs or symptoms of COVID-19 and (2) asymptomatic residents and HCP in response to an outbreak in the facility.\u00a0 When testing capacity is limited or test turnaround times are >2 days, testing HCP who are asymptomatic in facilities without an outbreak should be considered lower priority."}, {"question": "Is there an optimal frequency for testing residents and HCP who previously tested negative in nursing homes as part of an outbreak response?", "answer": "As part of an outbreak response, CDC recommends that residents and HCP\u00a0(who have not had a prior infection in the last 90 days) have viral testing (e.g., RT-PCR or antigen) immediately after the first new COVID-19 case is identified at the facility. Then the facility should perform serial testing of all residents and HCP who previously tested negative every 3\u20137 days until no new positive tests have been identified for 14 days. In nursing homes with outbreaks, most cases are identified within the first two weeks of diagnosing the first new case. These early cases likely occur among people who were previously exposed or were infected before more infection prevention and control (IPC) measures were implemented in response to the outbreak.\nFor this reason, if testing capacity allows and does not divert staff and resources away from performing other critical IPC measures (e.g., ensuring effective implementation of Transmission-Based Precautions\u00a0for infected and potentially exposed residents), the facility should consider testing more frequently (e.g., every 3 days) for the first two weeks of the outbreak, then test less frequently (e.g., every 7 days) thereafter until no new cases are identified for 14 days. As an example, testing would occur on day 0 (day the first case is identified), days 3, 6, 9, and 12, and then on days 19, 26, etc.\nThis increased frequency of testing might not be possible in many facilities (e.g., lack of testing supplies or diversion of resources from other patient care activities). A minimum frequency of testing every 7 days is recommended until no new positive tests have been identified for 14 days. The effectiveness of increased frequency of testing is substantially diminished if IPC measures are not maintained. Facilities should ensure adherence to appropriate IPC measures in outbreak settings, including use of Transmission-Based Precautions\u00a0for the care of all residents (even those who have negative tests) on affected units (or facility-wide, if cases are widespread). Facilities should also ensure rapid turnaround time of less than 2 days from specimen collection to test result."}, {"question": "Should residents in nursing homes who are asymptomatic be tested in non-outbreak settings?", "answer": "Unrecognized SARS-CoV-2 is most often introduced into a nursing home by asymptomatic healthcare personnel (HCP) or visitors with COVID-19 who work at or visit the nursing home, rather than residents. Recommendations for testing of residents who are asymptomatic in nursing homes is generally reserved for situations such as response to an outbreak in the facility (i.e., a new SARS-CoV-2 infection in any HCP or any SARS-CoV-2 infection in a resident) or evaluation of a resident who has had close contact\u00a0with someone with confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection.\nRegular testing of asymptomatic residents can result in false-positive results and potentially result in additional unnecessary testing. If testing capacity allows, consideration could be given to regular serial testing of residents who are asymptomatic and who frequently leave the facility for medical treatment and then return (e.g. residents who receive regular hemodialysis, including those who are dialyzed at an onsite facility that treats nursing home and community patients), especially in communities where there is moderate to substantial community transmission. Such residents might be at higher risk for SARS-CoV-2 infections because of their frequent exposures outside the nursing home. These exposures can be from community patients, staff members during ambulatory care or during transportation; however, the benefit of serial testing of residents is not known."}, {"question": "When should an antigen test result be considered a false positive?", "answer": "Research studies report that \u00a0the specificity of antigen tests\u00a0and nucleic acid amplification tests (NAAT), such as reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), are generally similar and high. However, false-positive results\u00a0may occur with any test, even those that have very high sensitivity and specificity.\nA point-of-care antigen test result should be considered a possible false-positive when a positive test result appears inconsistent with the clinical situation (e.g., a positive antigen test in an asymptomatic person who does not have risk factors and resides in a community with lower COVID-19 prevalence). When a false-positive test is suspected, nursing homes and health departments should also review and gather the following information:\n\nReview the FDA EUAexternal icon and instructions for use of the point-of-care antigen test to ensure correct use. For instance, the use of viral transport medium has been shown to produce false-positive results in some tests and should not be used for some antigen platforms (including BD Veritor and Quidel Sofia platforms). For further information on appropriate use of point of care tests, see Specimen Collection and Handling of Point of Care Tests.\nReview recent control results to ensure accuracy of the antigen test platform. If able, perform procedural quality control tests to ensure correct operation of the platform.\nCompare the percent positivity of the samples that were run that day (or week) to their previous percent positivity (e.g., their rolling 7-day average percent positive). Identifying many positives in one day might indicate an issue with the antigen results (either due to operator error or faulty test supplies).\nConsider the pre-test probability of disease. If testing a population with a COVID-19 prevalence of <1% (e.g., screening asymptomatic HCP in non-outbreak settings) with a single test with 99% specificity, the positive predictive value (probability that a positive test is a true-positive) could be <40%. In other words, in such situations, fewer than 4 of every 10 positive tests represent a true positive. \u00a0If the prevalence of COVID-19 in the population is >10% (e.g., testing asymptomatic residents and HCP as part of an outbreak response) with that same test with 99% specificity, the positive predictive value may be >90%. In such situations, more than 9 of every 10 positive tests represent a true positive. Therefore, testing in low-prevalence populations with antigen or RT-PCR tests might produce false positives, but that is less likely in outbreak settings."}, {"question": "If a nursing home is concerned about a false-positive antigen test result, what confirmatory test should be performed?", "answer": "In most instances, CDC guidance\u00a0currently recommends performing confirmatory testing when asymptomatic individuals are antigen positive.\nIf confirmatory testing is performed, facilities can optimize the performance of the confirmatory test by doing the following:\n\nUse nucleic acid amplification tests (NAAT), such as reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), as the confirmatory test. The utility of performing a confirmatory test with a second antigen test (either with the same platform or a different platform) is not known; repeating the test using antigen platforms might not be helpful if there are concerns about operator error contributing to false-positive results.\nOptimize sensitivity of the confirmatory test by collecting a high-quality specimen to ensure the confirmatory test does not produce a false negative result.\n\nNasopharyngeal (NP) swabs used correctly have a higher sensitivity than other specimen sources. Therefore, confirmatory tests should be performed using NP swabs.\nThe quality of the specimen can impact sensitivity, which can be lower in residents who are not able to follow instructions or those who are intolerant of being tested. If the person is unable to tolerate a NP swab, then a swab of the anterior nares or mid-turbinate could be considered as collection of these specimen types are more tolerable, and have similar or slightly\u00a0lower sensitivity.\n\n\nSelect a confirmatory test with high sensitivity. The\u00a0sensitivity of different RT-PCRNAAT platforms variesexternal icon\u00a0and the facility can check the\u00a0FDA EUAexternal icon\u00a0of the platform.\nPerform the confirmatory test within 2 days of the initial test. Tests performed >2 days apart should be considered separate tests, and discordant results may be due to changes in viral dynamics."}, {"question": "Should residents or HCP who have a positive antibody test for SARS-CoV-2 be tested as part of facility-wide testing?", "answer": "Yes. To determine if residents and HCP have a current infection, they should have a viral test (e.g., reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction [RT-PCR]) regardless of their antibody test result. A positive antibody test\u00a0result shows that an individual has antibodies from an infection with the virus that causes COVID-19, or possibly from infection with a related virus from the same family of viruses (called coronavirus), such as one that causes the common cold. We do not know yet if having antibodies to the virus that causes COVID-19 can protect someone from getting infected again or, if they do, how long this protection might last. Therefore, antibody tests should not be used to diagnose COVID-19 and should not be used to inform infection prevention actions."}, {"question": "How should facilities approach residents who decline testing?", "answer": "Residents, or their medical powers of attorney, have the right to decline testing. Clinical discussions about testing may include alternative specimen collection sources that may be more acceptable to residents than nasopharyngeal swabs (e.g., anterior nares). Providing information about the method of testing and reason for pursuing testing may facilitate discussions with residents and their medical powers of attorney.\nIf a resident has symptoms consistent with COVID-19, but declines testing, they should remain on Transmission-Based Precautions\u00a0until they meet the symptom-based criteria for discontinuation.\nIf a resident is asymptomatic and declines testing at the time of facility-wide testing, decisions on placing the resident on Transmission-Based Precautions for COVID-19 or providing usual care should be based on whether the facility has evidence suggesting SARS-CoV-2 transmission\u00a0(i.e., confirmed infection in HCP or nursing-home onset infection in a resident).\nOnly residents who have a confirmed positive viral test should be moved to COVID-19-designated units or facilities."}, {"question": "How should facilities approach HCP who decline testing?", "answer": "If HCP with symptoms consistent with COVID-19 decline testing, they should be presumed to have COVID-19 and excluded from work. Return to work decisions should be based on COVID-19 return to work guidance at the discretion of the facility\u2019s occupational health program.\nIf asymptomatic HCP decline testing, work restriction, if any, should be determined by the facility\u2019s occupational health and local jurisdiction policies. All staff should be trained in proper use of personal protective equipment, including universal facemask policies, hand hygiene, and other measures needed to stop transmission of SARS-CoV-2."}, {"question": "If HCP work at multiple facilities, do they need to receive a viral test at each facility?", "answer": "No, HCP do not need to be tested at each facility. If documentation of the test result is provided to each facility, the results from one setting are adequate to meet the testing recommendations at any facility. Each facility should maintain appropriate documentation of test results and have a plan to evaluate and manage HCP. HCP should be encouraged to tell facilities if they have had exposures at other facilities with recognized COVID-19 cases."}, {"question": "Should asymptomatic HCP who are tested as part of facility-wide testing be excluded from work while waiting for test results?", "answer": "If HCP remain asymptomatic, they may continue working while awaiting test results, unless work restrictions have been implemented by the occupational health program because of an exposure warranting exclusion from work."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Should post-exposure prophylaxis be used for people who may have been exposed to a person with COVID-19?", "answer": "There is currently no FDA-approved post-exposure prophylaxis for people who may have been exposed to COVID-19. For information about registered clinical trials of investigational therapeutics for pre- or post-exposure prophylaxis of SARS-CoV-2 infection, visit ClinicalTrials.govexternal icon.\nFor more information on movement restrictions, monitoring for symptoms, and evaluation after possible exposure to COVID-19, see Interim US Guidance for Risk Assessment and Public Health Management of Persons with Potential Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Exposure in Travel-associated or Community Settings and Interim U.S Guidance for Risk Assessment and Public Health Management of Healthcare Personnel with Potential Exposure in a Healthcare Setting to Patients with Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19).\nThe National Institutes of Health recently published guidelines on prophylaxis use for COVID-19 and testing and management of COVID-19 patients. For more information, please visit: National Institutes of Health: Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Treatment Guidelinesexternal icon."}, {"question": "How are COVID-19 patients treated?", "answer": "Not all patients with COVID-19 will require medical supportive care. Clinical management for hospitalized patients with COVID-19 is focused on supportive care for complications, including supplemental oxygen and advanced organ support for respiratory failure, septic shock, and multi-organ failure. Empiric testing and treatment for other viral or bacterial etiologies may be warranted.\nThe National Institutes of Health has published interim guidelines for the medical management of COVID-19external icon\u00a0prepared by the COVID-19 Treatment Guidelines Panel.\nFor information on investigational therapies, see Therapeutic Options for Patients with COVID-19."}, {"question": "Do patients with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 need to be admitted to the hospital?", "answer": "Not all patients with COVID-19 require hospital admission. Patients whose clinical presentation warrants in-patient clinical management for supportive medical care should be admitted to the hospital under appropriate Transmission-Based Precautions.\nSome patients with initial mild clinical presentation may worsen in the second week of illness. The decision to monitor these patients in the inpatient or outpatient setting should be made on a case-by-case basis. This decision will depend not only on the clinical presentation, but also on the patient\u2019s ability to engage in self-monitoring, the feasibility of safe isolation at home, and the risk of transmission in the patient\u2019s home environment. For more information, see Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations for Patients with Suspected or Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in a Healthcare Setting and Interim Guidance for Implementing Home Care of People Not Requiring Hospitalization for Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19).\nReferences related to hospitalization and outcomes among patients with COVID-19:\nHuang C, Wang Y, Li X, et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China.\u00a0Lancet\u00a02020;395:497-506.\nWang D, Hu B, Hu C, et al. Clinical Characteristics of 138 Hospitalized Patients With 2019 Novel Coronavirus-Infected Pneumonia in Wuhan, China.\u00a0JAMA\u00a02020.\nDong Y, Mo X, Hu Y, et al. Epidemiology of COVID-19 Among Children in China.\u00a0Pediatrics\u00a02020.\nWu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and Important Lessons From the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Outbreak in China: Summary of a Report of 72 314 Cases From the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. JAMA\u00a02020."}, {"question": "When can patients with confirmed COVID-19 be discharged from the hospital?", "answer": "Patients can be discharged from the healthcare facility whenever clinically indicated. Meeting criteria for discontinuation of Transmission-Based Precautions\u00a0is not a prerequisite for discharge from a healthcare facility. Isolation should be maintained at home if the patient returns home before the time period recommended for discontinuation of hospital Transmission-Based Precautions.\nDecisions to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or in-home isolation should be made according to the following guidance:\n\nFor hospitalized persons, see Discontinuation of Transmission-Based Precautions and Disposition of Patients with SARS-CoV-2 Infection in Healthcare Settings.\nFor non-hospitalized persons, see Interim Guidance for Implementing Home Care of People Not Requiring Hospitalization for COVID-19 and Discontinuation of Isolation for Persons with COVID-19 Not in Healthcare Settings."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What do we know about detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA after clinical recovery from COVID-19?", "answer": "Many recovered persons do not have detectable SARS-CoV-2 RNA in upper respiratory tract specimens. However, viral RNA can be persistently detected by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) in respiratory tract samples in some persons after apparent clinical recovery.\u00a0 In some persons, after testing negative by RT-PCR in two consecutive samples, later samples can test positive again. These persistent detections of viral RNA usually are associated with higher cycle threshold (Ct) values (i.e., fewer RNA copies) than Ct values found in RT-PCR results from samples collected shortly before or during clinical illness. Studies that have examined how long SARS-CoV-2 RNA can be detected in adults have demonstrated that, in some persons, it can be detected for weeks."}, {"question": "Are clinically recovered persons infectious to others if they test persistently or recurrently positive for SARS-CoV-2 RNA?", "answer": "Whether the presence of detectable but low concentrations of viral RNA after clinical recovery represents the presence of potentially infectious virus is unknown. Based on experience with other viruses, it is unlikely that such persons pose an important infectious risk to others. However, whether this is true for SARS-CoV-2 infection has not been definitively established.\nAfter the onset of illness, the detectable viral burden usually declines. After a week or more, anti-SARS-CoV-2 immunoglobulin becomes detectable and then antibody levels increase. Some of these antibodies may prevent the virus from infecting cells in cell culture. A decline in viral RNA is associated with a decreased ability to isolate live virus. For most patients with COVID-19, efforts to isolate live virus from upper respiratory tract specimens have been unsuccessful when specimens are collected more than 10 days after illness onset. Recovery of live virus between 10 and 20 days after symptom onset has been documented in some persons with severe COVID-19; in some cases, these persons were in an immunocompromised state.\nPersons who have tested persistently or recurrently positive for SARS-CoV-2 RNA have, in some cases, had their signs and symptoms of COVID-19 improve. When viral isolation in tissue culture has been attempted in such persons in South Korea and the United States, live virus has not been isolated. There is no evidence to date that clinically recovered persons with persistent or recurrent detection of viral RNA have transmitted SARS-CoV-2 to others.\nDespite these observations, it\u2019s not possible to conclude that all persons with persistent or recurrent detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA are no longer infectious. There is no firm evidence that the antibodies that develop in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection are protective. If these antibodies are protective, it\u2019s not known what antibody levels are needed to \u00a0protect against reinfection.\nThese data and experience with other viral respiratory infections indicate that most persons recovered from COVID-19 who test persistently or recurrently positive by RT-PCR are likely no longer infectious. Isolation and precautions may be discontinued for persons with COVID-19 \u00a010 days after symptom onset (the date on which symptoms first began, including non-respiratory symptoms), provided their fever has resolved for at least 24 hours, without the use of fever-reducing medications, and their other symptoms have improved. For some persons with severe or critical illness, or who are severely immunocompromised, isolation and precautions\u00a0may be maintained for up to 20 days after symptom onset."}, {"question": "Can cycle threshold (Ct) values be used to assess when a person is no longer infectious?", "answer": "No. Although attempts to culture virus from upper respiratory specimens have been largely unsuccessful when Ct values are in high but detectable ranges, Ct values are not a quantitative measure of viral burden. In addition, Ct values are not standardized by RT-PCR platform nor have they been approved by FDA for use in clinical management. CDC does not endorse or recommend use of Ct values to assess when a person is no longer infectious. However, serial Ct values may be useful in the context of the entire body of information available when assessing recovery and resolution of infection."}, {"question": "What further evidence is needed to be reassured that persistent or recurrent shedding of SARS-CoV-2 RNA after recovery does not represent the presence of infectious virus?", "answer": "Prospectively collecting serial respiratory samples and attempting to isolate live virus in tissue culture from multiple persons testing positive by RT-PCR following illness recovery is needed. If repeated attempts to recover replication-competent virus in culture from such serial samples are unsuccessful, that data would be sufficient evidence that infectious virus is absent. Then we would be sure that persons continuing to test positive do not pose an infectious risk to others."}, {"question": "Can viral culture be used to demonstrate that a person who had persistently or recurrently detectable viral RNA is not infectious to others?", "answer": "Yes. However, viral culture is not widely performed for SARS-CoV-2. It must be conducted in Biosafety Level 3 (BSL-3) laboratories using BSL-3 practices by experienced virologists and culture results can take a week or more. Therefore, while persons whose specimens do not yield live virus are considered no longer infectious, the complexity of such testing and the time required to complete it mean that culture cannot be used routinely to guide management of infected persons."}, {"question": "A person who previously tested positive by RT-PCR for SARS-CoV-2 and clinically recovered from COVID-19 is later tested again, for example, as part of a contract tracing investigation. If that person again tests positive by RT-PCR, should they be managed as potentially infectious to others, and isolated again for COVID-19?", "answer": "For persons who remain asymptomatic following recovery from COVID-19, retesting (e.g., as part of a contact tracing investigation) is not necessary during the first 3 months after the date of symptom onset. When a positive test occurs less than 3 months after the person\u2019s symptom onset of their most recent illness, it is possible that the positive test represents a new infection or a persistently positive test associated with the previous infection. If a positive test occurs more than 3 months after a person\u2019s symptom onset, clinicians and public health authorities should consider the possibility of reinfection. Until we have more information, the determination of whether a patient with a positive test in these situations is contagious to others should be made on a case-by-case basis. Consider consultation with infectious diseases specialists and public health authorities to review all available information (e.g., medical history, time from initial positive test, RT-PCR Ct values, and presence of COVID-19 signs or symptoms).\u00a0 Persons who are determined to be potentially infectious should undergo evaluation and remain isolated until they again meet criteria for discontinuation of isolation or discontinuation of transmission-based precautions, depending on their circumstances."}, {"question": "If a previously infected person has clinically recovered but later experiences symptoms consistent with COVID-19, should the person be isolated again and tested for SARS-CoV-2?", "answer": "If a previously infected person experiences new symptoms consistent with COVID-19 3 months or more after the date of the previous illness onset (or date of last positive viral diagnostic test [RT-PCR or antigen test] if the person never experienced symptoms), the person should undergo repeat viral diagnostic testing. However, serologic testing should not be used to establish the presence or absence of SARS-COV-2 infection or reinfection. These people who have a positive test result should be considered infectious and remain isolated until they again meet criteria for discontinuation of isolation or of transmission-based precautions. Contact tracing during the person\u2019s second episode of symptoms is warranted.\nFor persons who have recovered from laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection and who experience new symptoms consistent with COVID-19 within 3 months since the date of symptom onset of the previous illness episode (or date of last positive viral diagnostic test if the person never experienced symptoms), repeating viral diagnostic testing may be warranted if alternative etiologies for the illness cannot be identified. If reinfection is suspected and retesting is undertaken, the person should follow isolation recommendations for cases of COVID-19 pending clinical evaluation and testing results. Results of repeat testing should also be interpreted in consultation with an infectious disease specialist with consideration of cycle threshold values (if available) and clinical presentations. The determination of whether a patient with a subsequently positive test is contagious to others should be made on a case-by-case basis, in consultation with infectious diseases specialists and/or public health authorities, after review of available information (e.g., medical history, time from initial positive test, RT-PCR Ct values, and presence of COVID-19 signs or symptoms).\nNote: Serologic testing should not be used to establish the presence or absence of SARS-CoV-2 infection or reinfection."}, {"question": "If an infected person has clinically recovered and then later is identified as a contact of another person with COVID-19, do they need to be quarantined?", "answer": "If a person has clinically recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection and is then identified as a contact of a new case 3 months or more after the date of symptom onset of their previous illness episode (or date of positive viral diagnostic test [RT-PCR or antigen test] if the person never experienced symptoms), then they should follow general quarantine recommendations for contacts and undergo repeat viral diagnostic testing.\nThe following applies to a person who has clinically recovered from\u00a0 SARS-CoV-2 infection that was confirmed with a viral diagnostic test and then, within 3 months since the date of symptom onset of the previous illness episode (or date of positive viral diagnostic test if the person never experienced symptoms), is identified as a contact of a new case.\u00a0 If the person remains asymptomatic since the new exposure, then they do not need to be retested for SARS-CoV-2 and do not need to be quarantined. However, if the person experiences new symptoms consistent with COVID-19 and an evaluation fails to identify a diagnosis other than SARS-CoV-2 infection (e.g., influenza), then repeat viral diagnostic testing may be warranted, in consultation with an infectious disease specialist and public health authorities for isolation guidance."}, {"question": "If an infected person has clinically recovered using the symptom-based strategy, do they need a test to show they are not infectious?", "answer": "No. The symptom-based strategy\u00a0is intended to replace the need for repeated testing."}, {"question": "If an infected person has clinically recovered, should the person continue to wear a cloth face covering in public?", "answer": "Yes. It is recommended that all persons, with a few exceptions, wear\u00a0cloth face coverings\u00a0in public.1 The primary purpose of cloth face coverings is to limit transmission of SARS-CoV-2 from infected persons who may be infectious but do not have clinical symptoms of illness or may have early or mild symptoms that they do not recognize. Cloth face coverings may provide reassurance to others in public settings and be a reminder of the need to maintain social distancing. However, cloth face coverings are not personal protective equipment (PPE) and should not be used instead of a respirator or a facemask to protect a healthcare worker.\n[1] Cloth face coverings should not be placed on young children under age 2, anyone who has trouble breathing, or anyone who is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the mask without assistance."}, {"question": "What should I do if I suspect a potential case of reinfection?", "answer": "Although current understanding of reinfection remains limited, CDC is working with its partners to characterize the clinical features, transmissibility, and immunological profile around reinfection with SARS-CoV-2. Therefore, the guidance remains the same to reinfections as to primary infection with SARS-CoV-2. To further our shared understanding of reinfection, CDC has released the Investigative Criteria for Suspected Cases of SARS-CoV-2 Reinfection as well as the Common Investigation Protocol for Investigating Suspected SARS-CoV-2 Reinfection. This protocol is to support public health investigations conducted by interested institutions and jurisdictions. Clinicians with available specimens for suspected cases of reinfection meeting the above investigative criteria are also invited to contact CDC at eocevent461@cdc.gov after consulting with their local health department to pursue investigations with CDC support."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Does CDC recommend use of facemasks or respirators for healthcare personnel (HCP) caring for pregnant patients with known or suspected COVID-19 infection?", "answer": "When available, respirators (or facemasks if a respirator is not available), eye protection, gloves, and gowns should be used for the care of patients with known or suspected COVID-19 infection, including women who are pregnant. For more information, please see Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations for Patients with Suspected or Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Healthcare Settings."}, {"question": "How should the use of N95 respirators be prioritized within obstetric healthcare settings during shortages?", "answer": "During respirator shortages, care should be taken to ensure that N95 respirators are reserved for situations where respiratory protection is most important, such as performance of aerosol-generating procedures on patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 infection. In such shortage situations, facemasks might be used for other types of patient care.\nAlternatives to N95 respirators might be considered where feasible. These include other classes of NIOSH-approved filtering facepiece respirators, half facepiece or full facepiece elastomeric respirators, and powered air-purifying respirators (PAPRs) where feasible. All of these alternatives will provide equivalent or higher protection than N95 respirators when properly worn. However, PAPRs and elastomeric respirators should not be used in surgical settings due to concerns that exhaled air may contaminate the sterile field. For more information please see: Strategies for Optimizing the Supply of N95 Respirators.\nWhen respirator supplies are restored, the facility can switch back to use of N95 respirators for all care of patients with known or suspected COVID-19 infection. For more information, please see Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations for Patients with Suspected or Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Healthcare Settings."}, {"question": "Is forceful exhalation during the second stage of labor considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages?", "answer": "Based on limited data, forceful exhalation during the second stage of labor would not be expected to generate aerosols to the same extent as procedures more commonly considered to be aerosol generating (such as bronchoscopy, intubation, and open suctioning. Forceful exhalation during the second stage of labor is not considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages over procedures more likely to generate higher concentrations of infectious respiratory aerosols.\nWhen respirator supplies are restored, as with all clinical care activities for patients with known or suspected COVID-19, HCP should use respirators (or facemasks if a respirator is not available), eye protection, gloves, and gowns during the second stage of labor, in addition to other personal protective equipment that may be typically indicated for labor and delivery. For more information please see: Healthcare Infection Prevention and Control FAQs"}, {"question": "Is use of high-flow oxygen considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages?", "answer": "Based on limited data, high-flow oxygen use is not considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages over procedures more likely to generate higher concentrations of infectious respiratory aerosols (such as bronchoscopy, intubation, and open suctioning). Patients with known or suspected COVID-19 should receive any interventions they would normally receive as standard of care. When respirator supplies are restored, as with all clinical care activities for patients with known or suspected COVID-19, respirators (or facemasks if a respirator is not available), eye protection, gloves, and gowns should be used by HCP for the care of pregnant patients with known or suspected COVID-19. For more information please see: Healthcare Infection Prevention and Control FAQs"}, {"question": "Should intrapartum fever be considered as a possible sign of COVID-19 infection?", "answer": "Clinicians should use their judgment to determine if a patient has signs and symptoms\u00a0compatible with COVID-19 and whether the patient should be tested. Fever is the most commonly reported sign; most patients with confirmed COVID-19 have developed fever\u00a0and/or symptoms of acute respiratory illness (cough, difficulty breathing).\nData regarding COVID-19 in pregnancy are limited; according to current information, presenting signs and symptoms are expected to be similar to those for non-pregnant patients, including the presence of fever.\nOther considerations that may guide testing are epidemiologic factors such as the occurrence of local community transmission of COVID-19 infections. As part of evaluation, clinicians are strongly encouraged to test for other causes of respiratory illness and peripartum fever."}, {"question": "What guidance is available for labor and delivery HCP with potential exposure in a healthcare setting to patients with COVID-19 infection?", "answer": "HCP in labor and delivery healthcare settings should follow the same infection prevention and control recommendations and personal protective equipment recommendations as all other HCP. If HCP are exposed to patients with COVID-19 infection, guidance is available for HCP and healthcare facilities on steps to take. For more information, please see: Interim U.S. Guidance for Risk Assessment and Public Health Management of Healthcare Personnel with Potential Exposure in a Healthcare Setting to Patients with Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19)"}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Are empiric antibiotics recommended for patients suspected of having COVID-19?", "answer": "Several patients with COVID-19 have been reported to present with concurrent community-acquired bacterial pneumonia. Decisions to administer antibiotics to COVID-19 patients should be based on the likelihood of bacterial infection (community-acquired or hospital-acquired), illness severity, and antimicrobial stewardship issues. For more information, see Diagnosis and Treatment of Adults with Community-acquired Pneumonia: An Official Clinical Practice Guideline of the American Thoracic Society and Infectious Diseases Society of Americaexternal iconexternal icon."}, {"question": "What antiviral drugs are available to treat COVID-19?", "answer": "The National Institutes of Health (NIH) has published guidelines on testing and management of patients with COVID-19. For more information, please visit the NIH Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Treatment Guidelinesexternal icon. The recommendationsexternal icon\u00a0are based on scientific evidence and expert opinion and are regularly updated as more data become available.\nCurrent clinical management of COVID-19\u00a0includes infection prevention and control measures and supportive care, including supplemental oxygen and mechanical ventilatory support when indicated. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved one drug, remdesivir (Veklury), for the treatment of COVID-19 in certain situations.\nPersons seeking information about registered clinical trials for COVID-19 in the United States can search for such information here: ClinicalTrials.govexternal icon.\nFor more information on investigational therapies, see Therapeutic Options for Patients with COVID-19.\u200b"}, {"question": "Do nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) worsen the course of disease for people with COVID-19?", "answer": "CDC is currently not aware of scientific evidence establishing a link between NSAIDs (e.g., ibuprofen, naproxen) and worsening of COVID\u201119. FDAexternal iconexternal icon, the European Medicines Agencyexternal icon, the World Health Organization, and CDC are continuing to monitor the situation and will review new information on the effects of NSAIDs and COVID-19 disease as it becomes available. For those who wish to use treatment options other than NSAIDs, there are other over-the-counter and prescription medications approved for pain relief and fever reduction. Patients who rely on NSAIDs to treat chronic conditions and have additional questions should speak to their healthcare provider for individualized management. Patients should use NSAIDs, and all medications, according to the product labels and advice of their healthcare professional."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "If I have patients with asthma, do I need to make any changes to their daily asthma preventive management regimens to reduce their risk of getting sick with COVID-19?", "answer": "People with moderate to severe asthma, particularly if not well controlled, might be at higher risk\u00a0of getting very sick from COVID-19.\nBased on what we currently know about COVID-19, the selection of therapeutic options through guideline-recommended treatment of asthma has not been affected. National asthma guidelinesexternal icon are available. Continuation of inhaled corticosteroids is particularly important for patients already using these medications because there is no evidence of increased risk of COVID-19 morbidity with use of inhaled corticosteroids and an abundance of data showing reduced risk of asthma exacerbation with maintenance of asthma controller therapy.\nPatients with asthma but without symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19 should continue any required nebulizer treatments."}, {"question": "If my patient experiences an asthma exacerbation, should the exacerbation be treated any differently to reduce risk of COVID-19?", "answer": "Selection of therapeutic options through guideline-recommended treatment of asthma exacerbations has not been affected by what we currently know about COVID-19.\nSystemic corticosteroids should be used to treat an asthma exacerbation per national asthma guidelinesexternal icon and current standards of care, even if it is caused by COVID-19. Short-term use of systemic corticosteroids to treat asthma exacerbations should be continued. There is currently no evidence to suggest that short-term use of systemic corticosteroids to treat asthma exacerbations increases the risk of developing severe COVID-19, whereas there is an abundance of data to support use of systemic steroids for moderate or severe asthma exacerbations.\nPatients with asthma but without symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19 should continue any required nebulizer for treatments, as recommended by national professional organizations, including the American Academy of Allergy, Asthma & Immunology (AAAAI) and the American College of Allergy, Asthma & Immunology (ACAAI). If healthcare providers need to be present during nebulizer use among patients who have either symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19, use CDC\u2019s recommended precautions when performing aerosol-generating procedures (AGPs).\nClinicians may be concerned that an asthma exacerbation is related to an underlying infection with COVID-19. Clinicians can access laboratory testing for COVID-19 through a network of state and local public health laboratories across the country. Lists of states and territories with laboratories that are using COVID-19 viral tests are available. For more information, see Testing in U.S.\u00a0Clinicians should direct testing questions to their state and localexternal icon health departments."}, {"question": "Are any changes recommended to the asthma treatment plan if my patient with asthma has COVID-19?", "answer": "Patients can be referred to CDC\u2019s recommendations for caring for themselves or someone else at home sick with COVID-19.\nIf nebulizer use at home is necessary for patients with asthma who have symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19, use of the nebulizer in a location that minimizes and preferably avoids exposure to any other members of the household, and preferably a location where air is not recirculated into the home (like a porch, patio, or garage) is recommended by national professional organizations, including the American College of Allergy, Asthma & Immunology (ACAAI) by the ACAAI and the Allergy & Asthma Network (AAN). Limiting the number of people in the room or location where the nebulizer is used is also recommended by the Asthma & Allergy Foundation of America (AAFA). Nebulizers should be used and cleaned according to the manufacturer\u2019s instructions.\nIf nebulizer use in a healthcare setting is necessary for patients who have either symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19, use CDC\u2019s recommended precautions when performing aerosol-generating procedures (AGPs)."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Should people with COVID-19 and increased alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) be tested for viral hepatitis?", "answer": "Yes, for your patients with COVID-19 who have risk factors for viral hepatitis\u00a0and elevated hepatic enzymes, consider testing them for hepatitis A, B, and C, virus infections. However, ALT or AST may also be associated with COVID-19 alone and indicate greater severity of illness. For more information, review CDC\u2019s Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19)"}, {"question": "During the COVID-19 pandemic, should high-risk populations continue to be vaccinated for hepatitis A in response to the ongoing hepatitis A outbreaks?", "answer": "Yes. People who are unvaccinated and at higher risk for hepatitis A virus (HAV) infection during the widespread outbreaks of hepatitis A across the United States\u00a0should receive the hepatitis A vaccine when possible. This includes:\n\npeople who use drugs (injection or non-injection)\npeople experiencing unstable housing or homelessness\nmen who have sex with men (MSM)\npeople who are or were recently incarcerated\npeople with chronic liver disease (including cirrhosis, hepatitis B or C) and living or working in areas where the hepatitis A outbreaks are ongoing\n\nVaccination in group settings such as jails, other correctional facilities, and homeless shelters should continue if already planned and organized in a way that would follow infection control practices and where relevant social distancing standards can be maintained. When vaccinating people in non-group settings, ensure that general practices for the safe delivery of vaccination services\u00a0are followed. Whenever possible, vaccination efforts in non-group settings should continue for people at highest risk of acquiring HAV infection or developing serious complications from HAV infection, if staying at least 6 feet away from others can be maintained.\nNote: For people receiving COVID-19 vaccination, a minimum interval of 14 days is recommended\u00a0before or after receiving COVID-19 vaccination and any other vaccination. However, mRNA COVID-19 and other vaccines may be administered within a shorter period in situations where the benefits of vaccination are deemed to outweigh the potential unknown risks of vaccine coadministration, such as hepatitis A vaccination during an outbreak."}, {"question": "Should routinely recommended hepatitis A and B vaccines continue to be administered to children?", "answer": "Routine hepatitis A and B vaccination of children should continue to the extent possible, according to the CDC immunization schedules. For more information on vaccination during the COVID-19 pandemic, see the Immunizations and Well-child Care section on the Information for Pediatric Healthcare Providers page."}, {"question": "Should hepatitis B vaccination of HBV-exposed infants continue during the COVID-19 pandemic?", "answer": "Yes. Hepatitis B vaccination of all infants, especially those exposed to hepatitis B virus, should occur according to the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) recommendations.\nInterim guidance to prevent mother-to-child transmission of hepatitis B virus:\u00a0 \nLabor and Delivery Care\n\nIdentify the hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) status of all women presenting for delivery.\nIf a woman\u2019s HBsAg status is positive, hepatitis B immune globulin (HBIG) and single antigen hepatitis B vaccine should be administered to her infant within 12 hours of birth.\nIf a woman\u2019s HBsAg status is unknown, single antigen hepatitis B vaccine should be administered to her infant within 12 hours of birth. Administration of HBIG should be determined per ACIP recommendations. Infants weighing <2,000 grams should receive HBIG if the mother\u2019s HBsAg status cannot be determined within 12 hours of birth.\n\nProvide the birth dose of hepatitis B vaccine to all other newborns within 24 hours of birth to prevent hepatitis B virus transmission from household or other close contacts."}, {"question": "Should management of infants born to HBV-infected women continue during the COVID-19 pandemic?", "answer": "Yes. Management should continue to prevent mother-to-child transmission of hepatitis B.\nInterim guidance to prevent mother-to-child transmission of hepatitis B virus:\u00a0 \nPediatric Care of HBV-exposed Infants\n\nMake every effort to ensure HBV-exposed infants complete the hepatitis B vaccine series following the ACIP recommendations. Providers using single-component vaccine who are experiencing immunization service disruption should administer hepatitis B vaccine as close to the recommended intervals as possible, including series completion at 6 months, and follow ACIP recommendations for post-vaccination serologic testing.\nIf post-vaccination serologic testing is delayed beyond 6 months after the hepatitis B series is completed, consider administering a \u201cbooster\u201d dose of single antigen hepatitis B vaccine and then ordering post-vaccination serologic testing (HBsAg & antibody to HBsAg [anti-HBs]) 1-2 months after the \u201cbooster\u201d dose."}, {"question": "Should hepatitis A and B vaccines continue to be administered to adults at risk for hepatitis A or B?", "answer": "Yes. Continue to administer these vaccines if an in-person visit must be scheduled or occurs for some other purpose and the clinical preventive service can be delivered during that visit with no additional risk; or an individual patient and their clinician believe that there is a compelling need to receive the service based on an assessment that the potential benefit outweighs the risk of exposure to SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19. The vaccination status of all patients should be assessed at every clinical encounter to reduce missed opportunities for vaccination. See the Interim Guidance for Routine and Influenza Immunization Services During the COVID-19 Pandemic for more information."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Are patients with hypertension at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19?", "answer": "Many patients with severe illness from COVID-19 have underlying hypertension.1 Hypertension is common in the United States. Hypertension is more frequent with advancing age and among non-Hispanic blacks and people with other underlying medical conditions such as obesity and diabetes. At this time, people whose only underlying medical condition is hypertension might be at increased risk\u00a0 for severe illness from COVID-19.2\n\nGarg S, Kim L, Whitaker M, et al. Hospitalization Rates and Characteristics of Patients Hospitalized with Laboratory-Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 \u2014 COVID-NET, 14 States, March 1\u201330, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2020;69:458\u2013464. DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6915e3external icon.\nKillerby ME, Link-Gelles R, Haight SC, et al. Characteristics Associated with Hospitalization Among Patients with COVID-19 \u2014 Metropolitan Atlanta, Georgia, March\u2013April 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2020;69:790\u2013794. DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6925e1external icon."}, {"question": "Should angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (ACE-Is) or angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs) be stopped in patients with COVID-19?", "answer": "No. The American Heart Association, the Heart Failure Society of America, and the American College of Cardiology recommendexternal icon continuing ACE-I or ARB medications for all patients already prescribed those medications for indications such as heart failure, hypertension, or ischemic heart disease. At this time, available evidence demonstrates no indication of COVID-specific harm from these agents. Several randomized controlled trials are under way to better answer this important clinical question. Cardiovascular disease patients diagnosed with COVID-19 should be fully evaluated by a healthcare professional before adding or removing any treatments, and any changes to their treatment should be based on the latest scientific evidence. Patients who rely on ACE-Is or ARBs to treat chronic conditions and have additional questions should speak to their healthcare provider for individualized management"}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What do waste management companies need to know about wastewater and sewage coming from a healthcare facility or community setting with either a known COVID-19 patient or person under investigation (PUI)?", "answer": "Waste generated in the care of PUIs or patients with confirmed COVID-19 does not present additional considerations for wastewater disinfection in the United States. Coronaviruses are susceptible to the same disinfection conditions in community and healthcare settings as other viruses, so current disinfection conditions in wastewater treatment facilities are expected to be sufficient. This includes conditions for practices such as oxidation with hypochlorite (i.e., chlorine bleach) and peracetic acid, as well as inactivation using UV irradiation."}, {"question": "Do wastewater and sewage workers need any additional protection when handling untreated waste from healthcare or community setting with either a known COVID-19 patient or PUI?", "answer": "Wastewater workers should use standard practices including basic hygiene precautions and wear the recommended PPE\u00a0as prescribed for their current work tasks when handling untreated waste. There is no evidence to suggest that employees of wastewater plants need any additional protections in relation to COVID-19."}, {"question": "Should medical waste or general waste from healthcare facilities treating PUIs and patients with confirmed COVID-19 be handled any differently or need any additional disinfection?", "answer": "Medical waste (trash) coming from healthcare facilities treating COVID-2019 patients is no different than waste coming from facilities without COVID-19 patients. CDC\u2019s guidance states that management of laundry, food service utensils, and medical waste should be performed in accordance with routine procedures. There is no evidence to suggest that facility waste needs any additional disinfection.\nMore guidance about environmental infection control is available in section 7 of CDC\u2019s Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations\u00a0for Patients with Confirmed COVID-19 or Persons Under Investigation for COVID-19 in Healthcare Settings."}]}, {"title": "Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "How are environmental surfaces involved in the transmission of infections?", "answer": "Surfaces can become contaminated with microorganisms and potential pathogens. However, many of these surfaces are generally not directly associated with transmission of infections to either healthcare workers or patients. \u00a0The transfer of pathogens from environmental surfaces is largely due to hand contact with the surface (e.g., frequently touched surfaces). Touch contamination may lead to cross contamination of patient care items, other environmental surfaces, self-contamination, and possible infection after touching one\u2019s face or mouth."}, {"question": "How does one interrupt transmission of pathogens from environmental surfaces?", "answer": "Both hand hygiene and the cleaning and disinfection of environmental surfaces are fundamental practices to reduce the incidence of healthcare-associated infections."}, {"question": "Where can I find detailed information on cleaning and disinfection?", "answer": "For more information see our guidelines for healthcare facilities that cover cleaning, disinfection, sterilization, and hand hygiene:\n\nGuideline for Environmental Infection Control, 2003\nGuideline for Disinfection and Sterilization, 2008\nGuideline for Hand Hygiene in Healthcare Settings"}, {"question": "Why is cleaning of surfaces important?", "answer": "Cleaning is an important first step for any process that involves disinfection or sterilization because the presence of organic and inorganic soils may cause disinfection or sterilization to fail. \u00a0Cleaning is the process of removing both organic and inorganic matter from surfaces with the use of detergents (e.g., anionic, cationic, non-ionic, and zwitter ionic) or enzymatic cleaners.\u00a0 Cleaning may involve manual, automated, or a combination of manual and automated methods.\n\nDepending on the cleaning method and the surface being cleaned, a 102-106 log reduction of microorganisms may be possible.\nProper cleaning may be enough to make an environmental surface safe to handle and to prevent transmission of pathogens.\nCurrently, no cleaning guidelines apply to all devices or surfaces, nor is there a single accepted standard method to measure the effectiveness of cleaning (examples include adenosine triphosphate (ATP), fluorescent markers, blood, protein, carbohydrate, RODACTM plates, or touch plates).\nSee the CDC Environmental Toolkit\u00a0for additional information on developing a cleaning evaluation program."}, {"question": "What detergents are used for routine environmental cleaning in healthcare settings?", "answer": "Many cleaners used in healthcare settings for routine cleaning of the general environment are cationic detergents, with many of these being quaternary ammonium compounds which are also low- to intermediate-level disinfectants. For EPA registered detergent disinfectants, refer to the label to determine if the product is a one-step or multiple-step product, and follow the product label instructions for use.\n\nOne-step disinfection product and process combine cleaning and disinfection of a noncritical environmental surface or item into a single step. Depending on the instructions for product use, some do not have to be rinsed off.\nMulti-step products and processes require the user to clean the surface before it is disinfected. In some cases, the disinfectant must be rinsed from the surface following the wet contact time listed on the product label."}, {"question": "Are there ways to audit the cleaning process?", "answer": "Cleaning guidelines vary based on devices and surfaces being cleaned. Multiple methods are used to measure the residual bioburden or effectiveness of cleaning (e.g., ATP, fluorescent markers, blood, protein, carbohydrate, and RODACTM plates, or touch plates)\nSee the CDC Environmental Toolkit for additional information on developing a cleaning evaluation program."}, {"question": "What are no-touch devices or NTDs?", "answer": "No-touch devices (NTDs) are sometimes used in healthcare settings as an adjunct to terminal room cleaning (i.e., after patient discharge or transfer). They are not currently able to replace existing cleaning and disinfection processes. These devices use a variety of different disinfection technologies such as ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI) and chemical agents. They are called no-touch devices because they use a pre-determined program that allows the device to run unmanned in an unoccupied, pre-cleaned room (e.g., patient room) for a defined period.\nChemical disinfectants used for NTDs vary according to the specific device. Examples include vapor phase hydrogen peroxide, dry mist hydrogen peroxide, combined hydrogen peroxide + antimicrobial silver, dry fog hydrogen peroxide + peroxyacetic acid, ionized hydrogen peroxide, and chlorine dioxide gas.\nThe effectiveness of NTDs is still under investigation; most data are laboratory demonstrations of pathogen inactivation. Thus far, only one study of NTD use has shown a decrease in patient infection rates, the Duke BETR Disinfection Studyexternal icon (Andersen DJ, et al. Lancet Infect Dis 2018; 18(8): 845\u2013853)."}, {"question": "What information is available about the use of electrostatic sprayers or foggers for the disinfection of rooms and surfaces in healthcare environments?", "answer": "These devices are typically used as an adjunct technology to terminal room cleaning. This means that the patient has been transferred or discharged and is no longer occupying the space.\u00a0 So that EVS may begin cleaning and disinfecting the room in preparation for a new patient (e.g., terminal cleaning).\nFor information about the application of EPA List N disinfectantsexternal icon with electrostatic sprayers and foggers, refer to the EPA\u2019s Frequent Questions about Disinfectants and Coronavirus (COVID-19external icon). If a product does not have an electrostatic spraying or fogging use on a label, the EPA has not evaluated the safety and efficacy of using that product with an electrostatic sprayer or a fogger.\n\nFoggers can be hand-held or no-touch devices (NTDs).\nWhen using an electrostatic sprayer or a fogger to apply disinfectants, always follow manufacturer directions for operation and maintenance of the sprayer or fogger and the disinfectant label\u2019s use directions (e.g., application rate, distance to surface while applying, and contact time).\nFollow the disinfectant\u2019s label recommendations for appropriate personal protective equipment (PPE) for the operator, and adhere to any recommended re-entry times for bystanders, other staff members, or patients."}, {"question": "Is ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI) recommended for disinfection of air and surfaces in the healthcare setting?", "answer": "UVGI can be used as a supplemental treatment for disinfection of air in HVAC systems or above people in occupied spaces (upper-room or upper-air systems) and for supplemental disinfection of surfaces following routine cleaning and disinfection. UVGI, also known as Germicidal Ultraviolet (GUV), uses ultraviolet energy in the UV-C band (wavelengths of 220-280 nanometers), which is effective against SARS-CoV-2 under laboratory conditions. Efficacy of the applied dose (a function of irradiance and time) is highly dependent on many factors, such as the concentration of the virus, inoculum size (in experimental studies), the virus medium, contours and type of material being treated, as well as what the virus is suspended in (e.g., culture media, respiratory droplets, other proteinaceous material). These complex variables may explain the range of results presented in the published literature.\nFor more information on these technologies see the CDC Business FAQs under the heading \u201cCleaning and Disinfection in the Workplace\u201d\nUV-C can be applied on healthcare environmental surfaces using robots as NTDs following terminal cleaning and is still considered investigational; one study mentioned above the Duke BETR Disinfection Studyexternal icon\u00a0(Andersen DJ, et al. Lancet Infect Dis 2018; 18(8): 845\u2013853) has shown a decrease in Healthcare-associated infections."}]}, {"title": "General Business : Ventilation", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Can COVID-19 be transmitted through HVAC (ventilation) systems?", "answer": "The risk of spreading the virus that causes coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) through ventilation systems is not well-known at this time. Viral RNA has reportedly been found on return air grilles, in return air ducts, and on heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) filters, but detecting viral RNA alone does not imply that the captured virus was capable of transmitting disease. One research group reported that the use of a new air-sampling method allowed them to find viable viral particles within a COVID-19 patient\u2019s hospital roomexternal icon with good ventilation, filtration and ultraviolet (UV) disinfection (at distances as far as 16 feet from the patient). However, the concentration of viable virus detected was believed to be too low to cause disease transmission. There may be some implications for HVAC systems associated with these findings, but it is too early to conclude that with certainty. While airflows within a particular space may help spread disease among people in that space, there is no evidence to date that viable virus has been transmitted through an HVAC system to result in disease transmission to people in other spaces served by the same system.\nHealthcare facilities have ventilation requirements in place to help prevent and control infectious diseases that are associated with healthcare environments. For more information, see the CDC Guidelines for Environmental Infection Control in Health-Care Facilities.\nNon-healthcare (businesses and schools) building owners and managers should maintain building ventilation systems according to state/local building codes and applicable guidelines. Ensuring appropriate outdoor air and ventilation rates is a practical step building owners and managers can take to ensure good indoor air quality. Considerations for ventilation and related engineering control interventions for businesses and schools may be found on the following CDC webpages: COVID-19 Employer Information for Office Buildings and Strategies for Protecting K-12 School Staff from COVID-19."}, {"question": "How long will it take to dilute the concentration of infectious particles in a room once they are generated?", "answer": "While large droplets (100 micrometers [\u00b5m] and larger) will settle to surrounding surfaces within seconds, smaller particles can stay suspended in the air for much longer. It can take several minutes for particles 10 \u00b5m in size to settle, while particles 5 \u00b5m and smaller may not settle for hours or even days. Dilution ventilation and particle filtration are commonly used to remove these smaller particles from the air. Larger particles can also be removed using these strategies, but since they fall out of the air quickly, they might not have a chance to get captured by filtration systems. The time required to remove airborne particles from a space can be estimated once the source of infectious particles is no longer present and the dilution air is free of new infectious particles (e.g. it is uncontaminated supply air or it is the clean exhaust from a High Efficiency Particulate Air (HEPA) fan/filtration system [See HEPA filtration discussion below]). Table B.1\u00a0in the CDC\u2019s Guidelines for Environmental Infection Control in Health-Care Facilities (2003) provides estimates of the time required to remove airborne contaminants, including airborne viral particles, from the air through ventilation dilution, exhaust and filtration. The table provides estimates of the time required for airborne-contaminant removal based upon the room\u2019s ventilation rate, measured in air changes per hour (ACH) and the desired removal efficiency (99% or 99.9%).\nAlthough there are some highly contagious airborne diseases (like measles) where CDC provides specific guidance for 99.9% clearance wait times, the general recommendation in CDC\u2019s Guidelines for Environmental Infection Control in Health-Care Facilities is to wait to allow for a 99% reduction of any generated airborne particles before re-entering the room. In the absence of specific guidance specifying a longer wait period for the virus that causes COVID-19, SARS-CoV-2, the wait time associated with 99% clearance is appropriate for healthcare and other spaces. Regardless of whether the 99% or 99.9% column on Table B.1 is used, the value in the table is usually an under-estimation of the actual dilution clearance time as noted in the table\u2019s footnotes which include the following statement: \u201cThe times given assume perfect mixing of the air within the space (i.e., mixing factor = 1). However, perfect mixing usually does not occur. Removal times will be longer in rooms or areas with imperfect mixing or air stagnation.\u201d Appropriate use of Table B.1 to establish clearance times from any space requires multiplying the time in the table by a mixing factor (k) that ranges between 1 and 10. This factor represents how well the ventilation system mixes and dilutes the concentration of airborne particles within the room. As a rule of thumb, rooms with higher airflow rates (6 ACH and higher) and good placement of supply and exhaust grilles (hospital airborne infection isolation rooms) are considered to have \u201cgood\u201d mixing and thus a mixing factor of k = 3 is often used for these spaces. In that case, the time identified from Table B.1 should be multiplied by 3 in order to determine the actual clearance time prior to re-entry.\u00a0 Nonventilated or poorly ventilated spaces have typical values of k ranging from 8 to 10. Increased ACH generally leads to reductions in k, although k can also be reduced by the use of a fan in the space, which does not have an impact on ACH.\u00a0 Ultimately, wait times can be reduced by increasing ACH, reducing k, or a combination of both.\nExample 1: A room measuring 12 feet x 10 feet with a ceiling height of 9 feet is served with a 100% outdoor air ventilation system that delivers 65 cubic feet per minute (cfm) of supply air (Qs = 65 cfm) and exhausts 72 cfm of air from the room (Qe = 72 cfm). The room has average air mixing, so assign k = 5. How much time is required to reduce the airborne particle concentration by 99 percent?\nSince Qe is larger than Qs by 7 cfm, the heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) system is pulling 7 cfm of air into the room from adjacent areas (i.e., the room is under negative pressure). For this example, the 7 cfm of transfer air is assumed to be free of infectious airborne particles. The clean volumetric air flow rate (Q) is the larger value between Qs and Qe, so Q = 72 cfm. Now, calculate the air changes per hour:\nACH = [Q x 60] / (room volume) = (72 cfm x 60) / (12\u2019 x 10\u2019 x 9\u2019) = 4320/1080 = 4.0 ACH\nUsing Table B.1\u00a0the perfect mixing wait time based on 4 ACH and a 99% reduction of airborne particles is 69 minutes.\nUsing the mixing factor of 5, the estimated wait time for 99% reduction of airborne contaminants in the room is 5 x 69 = 345 minutes or 5 hours and 45 minutes.\nNote:\u00a0 Determining the true value of the mixing factor is difficult and requires special equipment to measure air flows and conduct tracer gas decay testing. Thus, conservative estimates of k are often used (as described above).\u00a0 Also, the addition of an air cleaning device (e.g., a portable HEPA filtration unit) within the same room will reduce the wait time.\u00a0 The flow rate from the air cleaning device can be added to Q determined above, which will increase the overall ACH in the room.\u00a0 The air movement created by the air cleaning device can also decrease the value of k.\u00a0 Together, the increased ACH and decreased k can help substantially reduce wait times. See Example 2 for more information, including an example of the calculations."}, {"question": "Can ventilation filters effectively capture SARS-CoV-2 viral particles?", "answer": "Filters for use in heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems are generally tested under procedures outlined in ANSI/ASHRAE Standard 52.2-2017-Method of Testing General Ventilation Air-Cleaning Devices for Removal Efficiency by Particle Size. To access the standard, the end user typically must purchase it, but ASHRAE, which is a global society focused on building systems, indoor air quality, and sustainability in the built environment, has made it available for free online viewingexternal icon during the ongoing pandemic. Based on the filtration efficiency determined by the testing procedures, filters are assigned a Minimum Efficiency Reporting Value (MERV). The MERV provides a measure of the \u201cfilter efficiency\u201d over the range of particle sizes prescribed in the test procedure. MERV values range from 1 to 16 and higher MERV values correspond to more efficient filters.\nResearch shows that the particle size of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, is around 0.1 micrometer (\u00b5m). However, the virus generally does not travel through the air by itself. These viral particles are human-generated, so the virus is trapped in respiratory droplets and droplet nuclei (dried respiratory droplets) that are larger than an individual virus. Most of the respiratory droplets and particles exhaled during talking, singing, breathing, and coughing are less than 5 \u00b5m in size. CDC recommends using the highest efficiency ventilation filters possible, without having detrimental effects on overall HVAC system performance. ASHRAE, has similar guidance, however, they recommend a minimum filtration efficiency target of MERV 13, provided there are not substantial negative impacts on the HVAC system performance and occupant comfort. A MERV 13 filter is at least 50% efficient at capturing particles in the 0.3 \u00b5m to 1.0 \u00b5m size range and 85% efficient at capturing particles in the 1 \u00b5m to 3 \u00b5m size range.\u00a0 Collectively these particles are capable of remaining airborne for hours and are most associated with deep lung penetration. A MERV 14 filter is at least 75% and 90% efficient, respectively, at capturing those same particles. Efficiencies for MERV 15 and MERV 16 filters are even higher. Thus, the recommended filters are significantly more efficient at capturing particles of concern than a typical MERV 8 filter, which is only around 20% efficient in the 1 \u00b5m to 3 \u00b5m size range and is not rated for capture efficiency of the smaller 0.3 \u00b5m to 1.0 \u00b5m particles.\nIncreasing filtration efficiency can increase the pressure drop across the filters. This can lead to increased fan energy, reduced airflow rates, and/or issues controlling indoor temperature and relative humidity levels. Scientific developments in filter design have reduced the amount of the increased pressure drop and its resulting impact on HVAC operations, but not all filters have adopted the newer technology. Prior to a filtration upgrade, the specific filter under consideration should be investigated for its pressure drop ratings at the flow rate(s) of intended use and the potential impacts of that pressure drop evaluated against the capabilities of the existing HVAC system.\nHigh-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filters are even more efficient at filtering human-generated infectious particles than MERV 16 filters. However, outside of a few unique applications, HEPA filters are rarely used in central HVAC systems. [See the question on Portable HEPA Filtration to learn more about them and their application in protective air cleaning]."}, {"question": "What is meant by \u201cdirectional airflow?\u201d How and where should we use it?", "answer": "Directional Airflow is a protective ventilation concept where air movement flows in a clean-to-less-clean direction. This ventilation concept is applied to areas where the \u201cclean\u201d environment requires a higher level of protection and/or where the \u201cless-clean\u201d environment has a higher risk of containing airborne contaminants (activities or occupancy by individuals with a higher risk of being infectious). Examples of \u201cclean\u201d spaces might include healthcare facility triage stations or rooms/corridors adjacent to higher risk activities. Examples of \u201cless-clean\u201d spaces might include spaces that contain known/suspect infectious persons or spaces where a known activity has increased likelihood of generating infectious airborne particles.\nThe creation of directional airflow can be accomplished within a particular space or between two adjacent spaces. This can be done passively, through intentional placement of supply and exhaust heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) grills or by the intentional creation of pressure differentials between adjacent spaces through specification of offset exhaust and supply air flow rates. Creation of the directional airflow can also be done actively, through the use of fans exhausting through open windows, strategic placement of ductwork attached to portable HEPA filtration units, or dedicated exhaust systems (installed or portable) that generate a desired airflow by exhausting air out of windows, doorways, or through temporary ducts.\u00a0 In specific settings, specialized local control ventilation interventions that establish the desired airflow directions can also be used (see the NIOSH Ventilated Headboard).\nDirectional airflows must be evaluated carefully. Testing of the directional airflow effectiveness can be accomplished using visual tracer techniques that use \u201csmoke tubes\u201d or handheld \u201cfog generators.\u201d Other tools, such electronic monitors or visual aids to monitor pressure differences can be used when directional airflow is established between two adjacent spaces. To reduce the potential for directing airflow from infectious towards non-infectious space occupants, it is important that the \u201cclean\u201d and \u201cless-clean\u201d space determinations be established using infection control risk assessment considerations."}, {"question": "What is a HEPA filter and why would I want to use a portable HEPA air cleaner?", "answer": "Research shows that the particle size of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, is around 0.1 micrometer (\u00b5m). However, the virus generally does not travel through the air by itself. These viral particles are human-generated, so the virus is trapped in respiratory droplets and droplet nuclei (dried respiratory droplets) that are larger. Most of the respiratory droplets and particles exhaled during talking, singing, breathing, and coughing are less than 5 \u00b5m in size. By definition, a High Efficiency Particulate Air (HEPA) filter is at least 99.97% efficient at capturing particles 0.3 \u00b5m in size. This 0.3 \u00b5m particle approximates the most penetrating particle size (MPPS) through the filter. HEPA filters are even more efficient at capturing particles larger and smaller than the MPPS. Thus, HEPA filters are no less than 99.97% efficient at capturing human-generated viral particles associated with SARS-CoV-2.\nPortable HEPA filtration units that combine a HEPA filter with a powered fan system are a great option for auxiliary air cleaning, especially in higher risk settings such as health clinics, medical testing locations, workout rooms, or public waiting areas. Other settings that could benefit from portable HEPA filtration can be identified using typical risk assessment parameters, such as community incidence rates, facemask compliance expectations and room occupant density. In choosing a portable HEPA unit, you want to select a system that is appropriately sized for the area in which it is installed. One way to do this for room air cleaners is to select a HEPA fan system with a Clean Air Delivery Rate (CADR) [See EPA\u2019s Guide To Air Cleaners In The Homepdf iconexternal icon] that meets or exceeds the square footage of the room in which it will be used. The larger the CADR, the faster it will clean the room air. If the room in which the air cleaner will be used is taller than 8 feet, choose an air cleaner with a proportionally higher CADR than that based simply on square footage. While these systems do not bring in outdoor dilution air, they are very effective at cleaning air within spaces to reduce the concentration of airborne particulates, including SARS-CoV-2 viral particles. Thus, they give effective air exchanges without the need for conditioning outdoor air.\nHEPA fan systems can be used as stand-alone units, or many larger units allow flexible ductwork to be attached to the air inlet and/or outlet (note that larger ducted units don\u2019t fall under the \u201croom air cleaner\u201d description and may not have a CADR rating). Using ductwork and placing the HEPA system strategically in the space can help provide desired clean-to-less-clean airflow patterns where needed. Ducted HEPA systems can also be used to establish direct source capture interventions for patient treatment and /or testing scenarios (See CDC/NIOSH discussion on Ventilated Headboard). Depending on the size of the HEPA fan/filter units and how the facility in which they are being used is configured, multiple small portable HEPA units deployed to high risk areas may be more useful than one large HEPA unit serving a combined space.\nExample 2: \u00a0The room described in Example 1 is now augmented with a portable HEPA air cleaning device with a CADR of 145 cfm (Qhepa = 145 cfm). The added air movement within the room improves overall mixing, so assign k = 3. How much time is saved to achieve the same 99% reduction in airborne contaminants by adding the portable HEPA device to the room?\nThe addition of the HEPA filter device provides additional clean air to the room.\u00a0 Here, the clean volumetric air flow rate (Q) is:\u00a0 Q = Qe + Qhepa = 72 cfm + 145 cfm = 217 cfm.\nACH = [Q x 60] / (room volume) = (217 cfm x 60) / (12\u2019 x 10\u2019 x 9\u2019) = 13,020/1080 = 12.06 ACH (round down to 12).\nUsing Table B.1, the perfect mixing wait time based on 12 ACH and a 99% reduction of airborne particles is 23 minutes.\nUsing the mixing factor of 3, the estimated wait time for 99% reduction of airborne contaminants in the room is 3 x 23 = 69 minutes.\u00a0 Thus, the increased ACH and lower k value associated with the portable HEPA filtration unit reduced the wait time from the original 5 hours and 45 minutes to only 1 hour and 9 minutes, saving a total of 4 hours and 36 minutes before the room can be safely reoccupied.\nIn conclusion, adding the portable HEPA unit increased the effective ventilation rate and improved room air mixing, resulting in an 80% reduction in time for the room to be cleared of potentially-infectious airborne particles."}, {"question": "Does germicidal ultraviolet (GUV) disinfection kill the virus that causes COVID-19?", "answer": "Yes.\nGermicidal Ultraviolet (GUV), or Ultraviolet Germicidal Irradiation (UVGI), is a disinfection tool used in many different settings, such as residential, commercial, educational, and healthcare. The technology uses ultraviolet (UV) energy to inactivate (kill) microorganisms, including viruses, when designed and installed correctly.\nThere is still a lot to learn about SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, and the possibility of airborne viral particles and spread. However, GUV can inactivate viruses in the air and on surfaces*. The design and sizing of effective GUV disinfection systems requires specific knowledge and experience.\nBe sure to seek consultation with a reputable GUV manufacturer or an experienced GUV system designer prior to installing GUV systems. These professionals can assist by doing necessary calculations, making fixture selections, properly installing the system, and testing for proper operation specific to the setting.\n*Note: CDC\u2019s recommendation for primary surface disinfection in occupied environments is to follow the CDC/EPA guidance for surface disinfection."}, {"question": "What are types of germicidal ultraviolet (GUV) for cleaning and disinfection in the workplace?", "answer": "Upper-room GUV\nUpper-room (or upper-air) GUV uses specially designed GUV fixtures mounted on walls or ceilings to create a disinfection zone of ultraviolet (UV) energy that is focused up and away from people. These fixtures disinfect air as it circulates from mechanical ventilation, ceiling fans, or natural air movement. The advantage of upper-room GUV is that it disinfects the air closer to and above people who are in the room. Since the 1980s, GUV systems have been widely used for control of tuberculosis (TB). The CDC guidance\u00a0Environmental Control for Tuberculosis: Basic Upper-Room Ultraviolet Germicidal Irradiation Guidelines for Healthcare Settingspdf icon provides information on appropriate GUV system design, related safe operation, and maintenance. Based on data from other human coronaviruses, a GUV system designed to protect against the spread of TB should be effective at inactivating SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, and therefore prevent spread. GUV systems usually require a few GUV fixtures to be effective. For example, a rectangular-shaped waiting room with 10\u201330 occupants will require 2\u20133 upper-air GUV fixtures. Of note, the potential for reflection of UV energy into the lower occupied space is a potential safety concern with upper-room GUV systems. However, a reputable GUV manufacturer or an experienced GUV system designer should know the precautionary techniques to prevent harmful UV exposures to people in the space. [Potential Application:\u00a0Can be used in any indoor environment; most useful in spaces highly occupied with people who are or may be sick.]\nIn-Duct GUV\nIn-duct GUV systems are installed within a heating, ventilation, and air-conditioning (HVAC) system. These systems are designed to serve one of two purposes:\n\nCoil treatment GUV\u00a0keeps HVAC coils, drain pans, and wetted surfaces free of microbial growth. These devices produce relatively low levels of UV energy. This energy is continually delivered 24 hours a day, which is why they are effective. Coil treatment GUV devices are not designed for disinfecting the air and should not be installed for the purpose of air disinfection. [Potential Application: Can be used to reduce HVAC maintenance and improve operational efficiency within large, commercial HVAC systems or residential HVAC systems; not recommended for inactivating airborne pathogens.]\nAir disinfection GUV\u00a0systems can be effective at inactivating airborne pathogens as they flow within the HVAC duct. HVAC air disinfection GUV systems generally require more powerful UV lamps or a greater number of lamps, or both, to provide the necessary GUV required to inactivate pathogens in a short period of time. Air disinfection systems are often placed downstream of the HVAC coils. This location keeps the coil, drain pan, and wetted surfaces free of microbial growth and also disinfects the moving air. [Potential Application:\u00a0Can be used inside any HVAC system to disinfect infectious airborne pathogens.]\n\n\nFar-UV (or Far-UVC)\nFar-UV is one of many emerging technologies that have become popular during the COVID-19 pandemic. While standard GUV fixtures emit UV energy at a wavelength around 254 nanometers (nm), far-UV devices use different lamps to emit UV energy at a wavelength around 222 nm. Aside from the wavelength, a major difference between the two technologies is that standard GUV systems are specifically designed to avoid exposing people to the UV energy, while many far-UV devices are marketed as safe for exposing people and their direct environment to UV energy. A review of peer-reviewed literature indicates that far-UV wavelengths can effectively inactivate microorganisms, including human coronaviruses, when appropriate UV doses are applied. Questions remain about the mechanisms of killing microorganisms and overall safety. Far-UV might prove to be effective at disinfecting air and surfaces, without some of the safety precautions required for standard GUV. Far-UV devices are best viewed as new and emerging technology. [Potential Application: Yet to be determined.] Consumers considering an emerging technology such as Far-UV can research the proposed system. Ask the vendor to provide proof of effectiveness and performance that demonstrates a clear protective benefit. Engage with a ventilation engineer, and if the engineer recommends installing such a system, obtain a guarantee as to expected disinfection performance. When evaluating evidence of system effectiveness, place emphasis on research publications over anecdotal claims and consider the following questions:\n\nAre there independent studies that prove the desired performance of the technology?\nDid the study environments represent your environment and intended use?\nHave performance results been published in a scientific or medical journal?\nWas the technology evaluated for potential adverse health effects or occupational exposures?\nWhere is the technology being used?"}, {"question": "Many new air disinfection devices are being marketed for their ability to inactivate the virus that causes COVID-19. How can I tell if they work as advertised?", "answer": "CDC does not provide recommendations for, or against, any manufacturer or product. There are numerous devices being heavily marketed to provide air cleaning during the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. Some of the most common are ionization and/or dry hydrogen peroxide devices. Some devices even include both technologies. While variations of these technologies have been around for decades, relative to other air cleaning or disinfection technologies, they have a less-documented track record when it comes to cleaning/disinfecting large and fast volumes of moving air within heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems or even inside individual rooms. This does not necessarily imply the technologies do not work as advertised. However, in the absence of an established body of peer-reviewed evidence showing proven efficacy and safety under as-used conditions, the technologies are still considered by many to be \u201cemerging.\u201d As with all emerging technologies, consumers are encouraged to exercise caution and to do their homework. Consumers should research the technology, attempting to match any specific claims against the intended use of the product. Consumers should request testing data that quantitively demonstrates a clear protective benefit and occupant safety under conditions consistent with the intended use. Preferably, the documented performance data under as-used conditions should be available from multiple sources, some of which should be independent, third party sources. Unsubstantiated claims of performance or limited case studies with only one device in one room and no reference controls should be questioned. At a minimum, if you are considering the acquisition and use of these devices, you will want to be sure the equipment meets UL 867 standard certification (Standard for Electrostatic Air Cleaners) for production of acceptable levels of ozone, or preferably UL 2998 standard certification (Environmental Claim Validation Procedure (ECVP) for Zero Ozone Emissions from Air Cleaners) which is intended to validate that no ozone is produced."}]}, {"title": "Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html", "data": [{"question": "Should I wear a respirator in public?", "answer": "Most often,\u202fspread\u202fof respiratory viruses from person-to-person happens among close contacts\u202f(within 6 feet). Recent studies indicate that people who are infected but do not have symptoms likely also play a role in the spread of COVID-19. CDC recommends everyday preventive actions to prevent the spread of respiratory viruses, such as avoiding people who are sick, avoiding touching your eyes or nose, and covering your cough or sneeze with a tissue. People who are sick should\u202fstay home\u202fand not go into crowded public places or visit people in hospitals. Workers who are sick should follow CDC guidelines and\u202fstay home when they are sick."}, {"question": "What is a respirator?", "answer": "A respirator is a personal protective device that is worn on the face or head and covers at least the nose and mouth. A respirator is used to reduce the wearer\u2019s risk of inhaling hazardous airborne particles (including infectious agents), gases or vapors. Respirators, including those intended for use in healthcare settings, are certified by the CDC/NIOSH."}, {"question": "What is an N95 filtering facepiece respirator (FFR)?", "answer": "An N95 FFR is a type of respirator which removes particles from the air that are breathed through it. These respirators filter out at least 95% of very small (0.3 micron) particles. N95 FFRs are capable of filtering out all types of particles, including bacteria and viruses."}, {"question": "What makes N95 respirators different from facemasks (sometimes called a surgical mask)?", "answer": "Infographic: Understanding the difference between surgical masks and N95 respiratorspdf icon\nN95 respirators reduce the wearer\u2019s exposure to airborne particles, from small particle aerosols to large droplets. N95 respirators are tight-fitting respirators that filter out at least 95% of particles in the air, including large and small particles.\nNot everyone is able to wear a respirator due to medical conditions that may be made worse when breathing through a respirator. Before using a respirator or getting fit-tested, workers must have a medical evaluation to make sure that they are able to wear a respirator safely.\nAchieving an adequate seal to the face is essential. United States regulations require that workers undergo an annual fit test and conduct a user seal check each time the respirator is used. Workers must pass a fit test to confirm a proper seal before using a respirator in the workplace.\nWhen properly fitted and worn, minimal leakage occurs around edges of the respirator when the user inhales. This means almost all of the air is directed through the filter media.\nUnlike NIOSH-approved N95s, facemasks are loose-fitting and provide only barrier protection against droplets, including large respiratory particles. No fit testing or seal check is necessary with facemasks. Most facemasks do not effectively filter small particles from the air and do not prevent leakage around the edge of the mask when the user inhales.\nThe role of facemasks is for patient source control, to prevent contamination of the surrounding area when a person coughs or sneezes.\u202f Patients with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 should wear a facemask until they are isolated in a hospital or at home. The patient does not need to wear a facemask while isolated."}, {"question": "What is a Surgical N95 respirator and who needs to wear it?", "answer": "A surgical N95 (also referred as a medical respirator) is recommended only for use by healthcare personnel (HCP) who need protection from both airborne and fluid hazards (e.g., splashes, sprays). These respirators are not used or needed outside of healthcare settings. In times of shortage, only HCP who are working in a sterile field or who may be exposed to high velocity splashes, sprays, or splatters of blood or body fluids should wear these respirators, such as in operative or procedural settings. Most HCP caring for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 patients should not need to use surgical N95 respirators and can use standard N95 respirators.\nIf a surgical N95 is not available for use in operative or procedural settings, then an unvalved N95 respirator may be used with a faceshield to help block high velocity streams of blood and body fluids."}, {"question": "My employees complain that Surgical N95 respirators are hot and uncomfortable - what can I do?", "answer": "The requirements for surgical N95 respirators that make them resistant to high velocity streams of body fluids and help protect the sterile field can result in a design that has a higher breathing resistance (makes it more difficult to breath) than a typical N95 respirator. Also, surgical N95 respirators are designed without exhalation valves which are sometimes perceived as warmer inside the mask than typical N95 respirators. If you are receiving complaints, you may consider having employees who are not doing surgery, not working in a sterile field, or not potentially exposed to high velocity streams of body fluids wear a standard N95 with an exhalation valve."}, {"question": "My N95 filtering facepiece respirator has an exhalation valve. Is that okay? Will it protect both me and others?", "answer": "Yes, an N95 filtering facepiece respirator will protect you and provide source control to protect others. A NIOSH-approved N95 filtering facepiece respirator with an exhalation valve offers the same protection to the wearer as one that does not have a valve. As source control, findings from NIOSH research suggest that, even without covering the valve, N95 respirators with exhalation valves provide the same or better source control than surgical masks, procedure masks, cloth masks, or fabric coverings. In general, individuals wearing NIOSH-approved N95s with an exhalation valve should not be asked to use one without an exhalation valve or to cover it with a face covering or mask. However, NIOSH-approved N95 respirators with an exhalation valve are not fluid resistant. Therefore, in situations where a fluid resistant respirator is indicated (e.g., in surgical settings), individuals should wear a surgical N95 or, if a surgical N95 is not available, cover their respirator with a surgical mask or a face shield.\u00a0 Be careful not to compromise the fit of the respirator when placing a facemask over the respirator."}, {"question": "Can I use an elastomeric respirator as source control?", "answer": "Until more is understood on exhalation valves, elastomeric respirators with unfiltered exhalation valves should not be used as source control in surgical and other healthcare settings due to concerns that air coming out of the exhalation valve may contaminate the sterile field. The NIOSH Certified Equipment List identifies the elastomeric respirators without exhalation valves or with filtered exhalation valves that may be used in surgical settings."}, {"question": "How can I tell if a respirator is NIOSH-approved?", "answer": "The NIOSH approval number and approval label are key to identifying NIOSH-approved respirators. The \u00a0NIOSH approval label can be found on or within the packaging of the respirator or sometimes on the respirator itself. The required labeling of NIOSH-Approved N95 filtering facepiece respiratorspdf icon\u00a0 includes the NIOSH name, the approval number, filter designations, lot number, and model number to be printed on the respirator. You can verify that your respirator approvals are valid by checking the NIOSH Certified Equipment List (CEL)."}, {"question": "How do I know if a respirator is falsely advertising NIOSH-approval?", "answer": "When NIOSH becomes aware of counterfeit respirators or those misrepresenting NIOSH approval on the market, these respirators are posted on the Counterfeit Respirators / Misrepresentation of NIOSH-Approval\u00a0webpage to alert users, purchasers, and manufacturers."}, {"question": "How do I know if my respirator is expired?", "answer": "NIOSH does not require approved N95 filtering facepiece respirators (FFRs) be marked with an expiration date. If an FFR does not have an assigned expiration date, you should refer to the user instructions or seek guidance from the specific manufacturer on whether time and storage conditions (such as temperature or humidity) are expected to have an effect on the respirator\u2019s performance and if the respirators are nearing the end of their shelf life."}, {"question": "What do I do with an expired respirator?", "answer": "In times of increased demand and decreased supply, consideration can be made to use N95 respirators past their intended shelf life. However, the potential exists that the respirator will not perform to the requirements for which it was certified. Over time, components such as the strap and nose bridge may degrade, which can affect the quality of the fit and seal. Prior to use of N95 respirators, the HCP should inspect the respirator and perform a seal check. Additionally, expired respirators may potentially no longer meet the certification requirements set by NIOSH. For further guidance, visit Release of Stockpiled N95 Filtering Facepiece Respirators Beyond the Manufacturer-Designated Shelf Life: Considerations for the COVID-19 Response."}, {"question": "What methods should healthcare facilities consider in order to avoid unintentional loss of PPE during COVID-19?", "answer": "Monitoring PPE supply inventory and maintaining control over PPE supplies may help prevent unintentional product losses that may occur due to theft, damage, or accidental loss. Inventory systems should be employed to track daily usage and identify areas of higher than expected use.\u00a0 This information can be used to implement additional conservation strategies tailored to specific patient care areas such as hospital units or outpatient facilities.\u00a0 Inventory tracking within a health system may also assist in confirming PPE deliveries and optimizing distribution of PPE supplies to specific facilities."}]}, {"title": "Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What actions can residents and staff take to prevent the spread of COVID-19?", "answer": "Encourage residents and staff to take everyday preventive actions\u00a0to prevent the spread of respiratory illnesses. Actions include staying home when sick; appropriately covering coughs and sneezes;\u00a0cleaning and then disinfecting frequently touched surfaces; and washing hands often with soap and water."}, {"question": "How can my retirement community or independent living facility prepare for COVID-19?", "answer": "Administrators should take the following actions to prevent a COVID-19 outbreak in their community or facility:\n\nPromote social distancing\n\nCancel public or group activities and events\nInform workers and volunteers to avoid close contact with residents\nWhen possible, limit visitors and volunteers to essential persons\nAdvise residents to stay home and avoid public places\nAlter schedules to reduce mixing (e.g., stagger meal, activity, arrival/departure times)\n\n\nSupport residents in preparing\n\nEstablish the \u2018buddy\u2019 system to ensure residents stay connected.\nEncourage residents to have extra medications and supplies.\nIdentify residents with unique needs and work with them to tailor these strategies.\nFind ways to support residents in\u00a0managing stress and anxiety.\nInform residents using print materials and high-visibility posters\n\n\nEncourage everyone to take\u00a0everyday preventive actions\u00a0to prevent the spread of respiratory illnesses.\n\nCover coughs and sneezes\nClean and disinfect frequently touched surfaces\nWash hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds\nEnsure hand hygiene supplies (e.g., hand sanitizer containing at least 60% alcohol) are readily available in all buildings.\n\n\nMonitor for cases and take action when someone is sick.\n\nScreen workers and when possible volunteers\nAsk residents to self-monitor for symptoms\nReview the usual absenteeism patterns at your facility among staff, so you can identify if the rate of absenteeism increases.\nImplement flexible sick-leave policies and actively encourage sick employees to stay home\nCoordinate with local health facilities if you suspect a resident or staff member may have COVID-19"}, {"question": "What resources does CDC have available to share with facilities?", "answer": "Share resources with the community to help them understand COVID-19 and steps they can take to protect themselves:\n\nCDC\u00a0COVID-19 business guidance\nCDC\u00a0COVID-19 healthcare guidance\nCDC\u00a0COVID-19 household guidance\nCDC\u00a0Make a Kit\nCDC\u2019s\u00a0health communication resources\nCDC offers several free handwashing resources that include\u00a0health promotion materials\u00a0and information on\u00a0proper handwashing technique."}, {"question": "Does CDC have recommendations for cleaning and disinfecting surfaces?", "answer": "Clean high-touch surfaces and objects regularly (for example, daily or after each use) and after you have visitors in your home. Focus on high- touch surfaces and objects (doorknobs, tables, light switches, phones, remote controls and countertops) with cleaners that you typically use.\u00a0Practice strict infection control procedures if there is a case in your facility.\nFollow CDC\u2019s Cleaning Recommendations for Communities."}]}, {"title": "Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness : If there is a case in the facility", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What should administrators do if a resident or staff shows symptoms of COVID-19?", "answer": "Ask residents to actively monitor (at least daily) for\u00a0COVID-19 symptoms, including fever and respiratory symptoms (shortness of breath, new or change in cough).\u00a0Administrators should work with local health authorities to establish procedures for those who become sick. Sick residents should avoid contact with individuals who are healthy. If you think someone may have COVID-19, ask them to self-isolate and you should contact local health officials."}, {"question": "What should administrators do if there is a case of COVID-19 in our facility?", "answer": "Work with local health authorities to communicate the possible exposure to residents, staff, and visitors. Clean and disinfect all shared facilities and high-touch surfaces. Limit visitors to essential staff \u00a0and visitors. Staff and, when possible, visitors should be screened for signs and symptoms of COVID-19 before entering the facility. Residents will need to actively monitor their health for COVID-19 symptoms. Cancel group activities. Residences that become ill should be advised to call the medical facility in advance of their visit.\u00a0See CDC\u2019s full interim guidance for more details."}]}, {"title": "Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What steps should I take to prepare my facility?", "answer": "Because of close contact and the number of people in correctional and detention facilities (including prisons and jails), staff and people who are incarcerated are at greater risk for the spread of germs. To help your facility prepare for the possible spread of COVID-19, update your emergency operations plan. This includes:\n\nAdding key COVID-19 prevention strategies and posting information in the facility on how to limit the spread of germs.\nReminding staff to stay home when sick.\nIdentifying points of contact for local public health agencies.\nIdentifying physical locations (dedicated housing areas and bathrooms) where you can medically isolate incarcerated persons, as well as where to quarantine known close contacts of people with COVID-19.\n\nFollow guidance on medical isolation and quarantine.\nMedical isolation and quarantine locations should be separate.\n\n\nOffering flu shots to staff and people who are incarcerated, because limiting cases of flu can help speed the identification of people with COVID-19.\nDeveloping ways to continue providing critical services, such as mental health support.\nEnsuring adequate stocks of hygiene, cleaning, and medical supplies.\n\nHygiene: Soap (preferably liquid to promote use), tissues, and hand drying supplies, as well as hand sanitizers, when possible. Ensure no-cost access to soap.\nCleaning: EPA-registered disinfectantsexternal icon effective against the virus that causes COVID-19\nMedical supplies: Supplies for daily clinic needs, personal protective equipment (PPE), and testing\n\n\nCreating and testing communications plans to share critical information.\nSetting up systems to safely transfer people between facilities and identifying alternative strategies to in-person court appearances, when possible.\n\nPrevent confirmed and suspected COVID-19 cases and their close contacts\u00a0from being transferred between jurisdictions and facilities unless necessary for medical evaluation, medical isolation/quarantine, clinical care, extenuating security concerns, or to prevent overcrowding.\n\n\nPlanning for staff absenteeism.\n\nFollow CDC guidance\u00a0on recommended PPE for staff who will have direct contact with an individual with possible COVID-19 infection, or infectious materials. Make contingency plans for the likely event of PPE shortages.\nFollow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19)\u00a0and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates for staff evaluating and providing care for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 cases. When no on-site healthcare capacity is available, make a plan for how to ensure that people suspected to have COVID-19 will be medically isolated, evaluated, tested (if indicated), and provided medical care. Contact and collaborate with your state, local, tribal and territorial health departments for more specific guidance."}, {"question": "How can I lower the chance that my staff will get COVID-19?", "answer": "The best way to protect your staff is to prevent exposure. Start by:\n\nStaying informed about updates to CDC guidance via the CDC COVID-19 website.\nMaking sure staff are aware of COVID-19 symptoms and requiring staff with any flu-like symptoms to stay home (or be sent home if they develop symptoms while at the facility).\nOffering telework for staff when feasible, and exploring ways to revise duties that require face-to-face interaction for staff at high-risk for severe illness.\nEnsuring staff use everyday preventive actions\u00a0(such as washing hands, avoiding touching their eyes, nose, and mouth, covering their cough).\nManaging and monitoring staff absenteeism.\n\nAlert local public health officials about large increases in staff absenteeism, particularly if absences appear due to respiratory illnesses (like the common cold or the flu, which have symptoms similar to COVID-19).\n\n\nOffering flu shots to staff, as limiting cases of flu can speed up the identification of people with COVID-19.\nStocking and providing supplies that help prevent the spread of germs.\nRoutinely cleaning and disinfecting\u00a0the facility.\nConsult CDC guidance\u00a0on recommended PPE for persons in direct contact with COVID-19 cases.\n\nReview the\u00a0Occupational Safety and Health Administration websiteexternal iconexternal icon and guidance for businesses and employers\u00a0to identify any additional strategies the facility can use within its role as an employer.\nStaff evaluating and providing care for people with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 should follow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19)\u00a0and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates to these recommendations. Facilities without on-site health care capacity should make a plan for how they will ensure that suspected COVID-19 cases will be medically isolated, evaluated, tested (if indicated), and provided medical care. Contact and collaborate with your state, local, tribal, and territorial health departments for more specific guidance."}, {"question": "How can I lower the chance that people who are incarcerated will get COVID-19?", "answer": "The best way to prevent illness among people who are incarcerated is to prevent exposure to the virus that causes COVID-19. Start by:\n\nStaying informed about updates to CDC guidance via the CDC COVID-19 website.\nMaking sure people who are incarcerated are aware of COVID-19 symptoms and remind them to notify staff right away if they might be sick.\nPosting information about and ensuring they use everyday preventive actions\u00a0(such as washing hands, avoiding touching their eyes, nose, and mouth, covering their cough).\nStocking up and providing free access to soap (preferably liquid soap to promote use), tissues, and hand drying supplies, as well as hand sanitizer (where permitted based on security restrictions).\nConducting temperature checks and screening all new entrants, staff, and visitors for flu-like symptoms during the last 24 hours, and any contact they may have had with someone infected with COVID-19 in the last 14 days.\nOffering flu shots to people who are incarcerated, as limiting cases of flu can help speed the identification of people with COVID-19.\nRoutinely cleaning and disinfecting\u00a0surfaces and objects that are frequently touched."}]}, {"title": "Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "How can I find out if the virus has spread to the local community close to my facility?", "answer": "You can get up-to-date information about local COVID-19 activity by keeping in touch with your local and state public health officialsexternal iconexternal icon, and keeping up-to-date with the CDC website."}, {"question": "What steps should I take to protect my staff and people who are incarcerated if there is spread of COVID-19 in the local community close to my facility?", "answer": "If COVID-19 is known to be spreading in the local community close to your facility, but there are no confirmed cases among people who are incarcerated, staff, or visitors who have been inside the facility within the past 14 days:\n\nImplement operational actions:\n\nRestrict non-essential transfers of people between facilities and systems.\nUse alternative strategies to limit in-person court appearances where possible.\nConsider suspending co-pays for incarcerated persons seeking medical evaluation for COVID-19 symptoms.\nRequire staff to stay home if they are sick.\nConsider suspending visitation or offering non-contact visits only.\nDo not allow non-essential vendors, volunteers, or tours into the facility.\nConsider suspending work release programs.\n\n\n\n\nClean and disinfect the facility:\n\nUse CDC recommendations for cleaning and disinfection during the COVID-19 response\u00a0to routinely clean and disinfect surfaces and objects that are frequently touched, especially in common areas.\nUse household cleaners and EPA-registered disinfectants effective against the virus that causes COVID-19external iconexternal icon\n\n\nFocus on good hygiene:\n\nRemind staff, visitors, and people who are incarcerated to use everyday preventive actions\u00a0(such as washing hands, avoiding touching their eyes, nose, and mouth, covering their cough).Provide free access to soap (preferably liquid soap) and access to running water, hand dryers, tissues, and no-touch trash cans, when possible.\n\n\nContinually restock hygiene supplies throughout the facility.\nConsider increasing the number of staff and/or other people who are trained to clean common areas to ensure they are cleaned on a continual basis.\nConduct screenings\u00a0for symptoms and fever on all new entrants, staff, and visitors prior to entering the facility and follow guidance.\nUse options to increase social distancing (increasing the physical space between people in the facility, ideally at least 6 feet between people, regardless of whether or not they have symptoms):\n\nIncrease space between people who are incarcerated in holding cells and when in line.\nStagger mealtimes and time in recreation spaces.\nLimit interactions in large group settings and group programs.\nWhen possible, place beds at least 6 feet apart and have people sleep head-to-foot.\nFind a separate space to check people for COVID-19 that is close to each housing unit instead of having people who are sick walk through the facility to be medically evaluated.\nRemind staff to keep 6 feet apart from an individual with respiratory symptoms when possible.\n\n\n\u00a0Communicate regularly:\n\nProvide up-to-date information and remind and encourage people who are incarcerated and staff to report COVID-19 symptoms to staff right away."}, {"question": "What should be included in my screening procedures for new entrants to the facility?", "answer": "New entrants should undergo temperature screening in addition to the following verbal screening questions:\n\n\u201cToday or in the past 24 hours, have you had any of the following symptoms? Fever, felt feverish, or had chills? Cough? Difficulty breathing?\u201d\n\nIf yes, give them a clean, disposable facemask, separate them from others, and notify medical staff. Ensure only trained personnel wearing recommended PPE\u00a0have contact with individuals who have or may have COVID-19.\nFacilities without on-site healthcare staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective medical isolation and necessary medical care.\n\n\n\u201cIn the past 14 days, have you had contact with a person known to be infected with the novel coronavirus (COVID-19)?\u201d\n\nIf yes (but no COVID-19 symptoms): Quarantine the individual and monitor for symptoms two times per day for 14 days. During quarantine, facility staff should follow guidance on quarantine, and monitor the person for symptoms two times per day for 14 days.\nFacilities without on-site health care staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective medical isolation and necessary medical care."}, {"question": "What is a safe way to perform temperature checks?", "answer": "Staff performing temperature checks should follow these steps:\n\nWash hands thoroughly.\nPut on a face mask, eye protection (goggles or disposable face shield that fully covers the front and sides of the face), gown/coveralls, and a single pair of disposable gloves.\nCheck the person\u2019s temperature.\n\n\n\n\nIf performing a temperature check on multiple individuals, ensure that a clean pair of gloves is used for each individual and that the thermometer has been thoroughly cleaned in between each check.\nIf disposable or non-contact thermometers are used and the screener did not have physical contact with an individual, gloves do not need to be changed before the next check. If non-contact thermometers are used, they should be cleaned routinely as recommended by CDC for infection control.\n\n\n\n\nRemove and discard PPE.\nWash hands thoroughly."}, {"question": "Should I allow visitors into the facility if there is spread of COVID-19 in the community close to my facility?", "answer": "If there is spread of COVID-19 in the community close to your facility, consider suspending contact visits. If contact visits continue, all potential visitors should be asked:\n\n\u201cToday or in the past 24 hours, have you had any of the following symptoms? Fever, felt feverish, or had chills? Cough? Difficulty breathing?\u201d\n\u201cIn the past 14 days, have you had contact with a person known to be infected with the novel coronavirus (COVID-19)?\u201d\n\nStaff should also perform temperature checks for all visitors and volunteers. Any visitor who answers yes to one of these questions or who declines screening should not be allowed into the facility. When possible, facilities should let potential visitors know about these rules before they travel to the facility. Facilities can place posters in visiting areas and ask people who are incarcerated to inform their family members and visitors about these rules."}, {"question": "How should the facility be cleaned to limit spread of the virus?", "answer": "Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may also weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. Cleaning high touch surfaces and shared objects once a day is usually enough to sufficiently remove virus that may be on surfaces unless someone with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 has been in your facility. For more information on cleaning your facility regularly and cleaning your facility when someone is sick, see Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Facility."}]}, {"title": "Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What should I do if a person who is incarcerated in my facility may have COVID-19?", "answer": "If you think someone who is incarcerated in the facility is sick with COVID-19 (see COVID-19 symptoms), activate your emergency plan and notify local public health officials. Ensure that the sick person is wearing a clean, disposable facemask, and separate the sick person from others, ideally within an individual housing space and bathroom. Provide them with tissues for when they cough or sneeze, and a lined trash receptacle when possible.\nStaff evaluating and providing care for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 cases should follow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates to these recommendations. Facilities without on-site healthcare staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective isolation and necessary medical care. Ensure only trained personnel wearing recommended personal protective equipment (PPE)\u00a0have contact with or transport individuals who have or may have COVID-19.\nPeople who are incarcerated and have COVID-19 should be placed under medical isolation in a separate room, ideally with solid walls and a solid door that closes fully. If not available, refer to the full guidance document\u00a0for other options for medical isolation. If multiple people become ill with COVID-19:\n\nMake every effort to house each ill person individually, with their own bathroom. Refer to the full guidance document\u00a0for additional options if individual spaces are not available.\nPrioritize those at high risk for complications\u00a0of COVID-19 (older adults, people with severe underlying chronic medical conditions) for individual spaces that are available.\n\nTo prevent further spread:\n\nUse options for virtual court appearances, if possible.\nSuspend group gatherings.\nLimit non-medical transfers of people within and between facilities. Ensure that anyone transferred out is screened for symptoms and contact with a COVID-19 case before leaving the facility.\nEnsure that release planning includes screening for COVID-19 symptoms and contact with a case. Coordinate with local public health officials if releasing a symptomatic person to the community.\nUse multiple social distancing strategies.\nHandle laundry and food items of possible or confirmed cases of COVID-19 with recommended PPE.\nSuspend visitation or offer non-contact visitation only.\nConsider quarantining all new entrants for 14 days before they enter the facility. (Make sure that new entrants under quarantine are housed separately from other incarcerated people already under quarantine due to contact with a COVID-19 case.)\nIf releasing someone to a community facility (e.g., a homeless shelter), contact the facility\u2019s staff to ensure adequate time for them to prepare to continue medical isolation, and coordinate with local public health officials.\n\nProvide clear information to staff and people who are incarcerated about the presence of COVID-19 cases within the facility. Close contacts of the sick person (who have been within 6 feet of the sick person or had direct contact with infectious droplets, such as from a cough or sneeze) should be placed under quarantine for at least 14 days. Follow CDC guidance\u00a0on quarantining close contacts of people with COVID-19.\nIf separate spaces for individual quarantined people are not available, refer to the full guidance document for other options. Monitor symptoms twice per day and move anyone developing symptoms to medical isolation right away (after ensuring they are wearing a face mask). Quarantined people at high risk for complications of COVID-19 (older adults, people with severe underlying chronic medical conditions) should not be housed with other quarantined people if at all possible."}, {"question": "What should I do if one of my staff might have COVID-19?", "answer": "If you think someone on your staff is sick with COVID-19 (see COVID-19 symptoms), activate your emergency plan and notify public health officials. Give them a clean,\u00a0disposable facemaskpdf icon and send them home right away. Close contacts of the sick person (who have been within 6 feet of the sick person or have had direct contact with infectious droplets, such as from a cough or sneeze) should self-quarantine at for 14 days home and follow CDC recommended steps for people who are sick with COVID-19 symptoms."}, {"question": "What is the best way to clean and disinfect my facility after a confirmed case of COVID-19?", "answer": "Clean and Disinfect Your Facility When Someone is Sick\nIf there has been a sick person or someone who has COVID-19 in your facility within the last 24 hours, you should clean and disinfect\u00a0the spaces they occupied.\nBefore cleaning and disinfecting\n\nClose off areas used by the person who is sick and do not use those areas until they have been cleaned and disinfected.\nWait as long as possible\u00a0(at least several hours) before you clean and disinfect.\n\nWhile cleaning and disinfecting\n\nOpen doors and windows and use fans or HVAC (heating, ventilation, and air conditioning) settings to increase air circulation in the area.\nUse products from\u202fEPA List Nexternal icon\u00a0according to the instructions on the product label.\nWear a mask and gloves while cleaning and disinfecting.\nFocus on the immediate areas occupied by the person who is sick or diagnosed with COVID-19 unless they have already been cleaned and disinfected.\nVacuum the space if needed. Use a vacuum equipped with high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter and bags, if available.\n\nWhile vacuuming, temporarily turn off in-room, window-mounted, or on-wall recirculation heating, ventilation, and air conditioning systems to avoid contamination of HVAC units.\nDo NOT deactivate central HVAC systems. These systems provide better filtration capabilities and introduce outdoor air into the areas that they serve.\n\n\n\n\nIt is safe to wash dirty laundry from a person who is sick with COVID-19 with other people\u2019s items, if needed.\nEnsure\u202fsafe and correct use\u202fand storage of\u202fcleaning and disinfectant products, including storing such products. Store these products securely and use the necessary PPE.\n\n\u00a0\n\nTime since person who was sick or diagnosed with COVID-19 was in the facility\n\n\nTime since person who was sick or diagnosed with COVID-19 was in the facility\nWhat to do\n\n\nLess than 24 hours\nClean and disinfect the space\n\n\nMore than 24 hours\nCleaning is enough. You may choose to also disinfect depending on certain conditions or everyday practices required by your facility\n\n\nMore than 3 days\nNo additional cleaning (beyond regular cleaning practices)"}, {"question": "Should I allow visitors into the facility?", "answer": "If there is a case of COVID-19 in your facility, suspend contact visitation programs. Instead, use virtual visitation when possible."}, {"question": "What do medical staff need to know about caring for a person with COVID-19 in my facility?", "answer": "Facilities should ensure that incarcerated individuals receive medical evaluation and treatment at the first sign of COVID-19 symptoms. Staff evaluating and providing care for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 cases should follow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates to these recommendations. Facilities without on-site healthcare staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective medical isolation and necessary medical care. Facilities should have a plan in place to safely transfer persons with complications from COVID-19 to a local hospital if they require care beyond what the facility is able to provide. When evaluating and treating persons with symptoms of COVID-19 who do not speak English, provide a translator when possible. Spanish and Simplified Chinese materials\u00a0are available for those who need them."}, {"question": "What steps do I need to take to implement quarantine in my facility?", "answer": "Close contacts of a sick person (who have been within about 6 feet of the sick person or have had direct contact with infectious droplets, such as from a cough or sneeze) should be placed under quarantine for 14 days to determine if they develop symptoms. CDC has developed guidance on quarantining close contacts of people with COVID-19. Be sure to monitor symptoms twice a day and move anyone developing symptoms to medical isolation right away, after ensuring that they are wearing a face mask. Individuals under quarantine should stay within the quarantine space, including when eating their meals, using the bathroom, and receiving medical evaluation. Laundry of people in quarantine can be washed with the laundry of others. Individuals handling laundry should wear recommended PPE, should not shake the laundry, and should clean their hands often.\nIdeally, people under quarantine due to contact with a COVID-19 case should be housed individually. If separate spaces in a facility are not available, refer to CDC\u2019s full guidance document for correctional and detention centers for other options. People at high risk for complications of COVID-19\u00a0(older adults, people with severe underlying chronic medical conditions) should not be housed with other quarantined people if at all possible. Facilities without enough space or without onsite healthcare capacity should coordinate with local public health officials.\nIndividuals in quarantine can be released from quarantine back to their previous housing arrangement in the facility if they have not developed symptoms during the 14-day time period."}]}, {"title": "Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "How can I lower the chance that I will get COVID-19?", "answer": "The best way to prevent illness is to take steps to avoid being exposed to this virus. Start by ensuring you and others around you use everyday preventive actions (such as washing hands often, avoiding touching your eyes, nose, and mouth, and covering your cough). Read How to Protect Yourself\u00a0to learn more.\nIf there is spread of COVID-19 in the community close to the facility, you will be asked daily about symptoms over the last 24 hours and any contact you had with someone infected with COVID-19 in the last 14 days. Your temperature will also be checked daily."}, {"question": "Do I have a greater chance of getting COVID-19?", "answer": "Staff and people incarcerated in correctional and detention facilities are at greater risk for some illnesses, such as COVID-19, because of the close living arrangements inside the facility. The virus is thought to spread mainly from person-to-person, through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs or sneezes. These droplets can land in the mouths or noses of people who are nearby or possibly be inhaled into the lungs. It may be possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads. This is why washing your hands regularly and avoid close contact with other people when possible prevents illness."}, {"question": "What should I do if I think I may be sick with COVID-19?", "answer": "If you think you have been exposed to COVID-19 and develop a fever or symptoms of respiratory illness, such as cough or difficulty breathing, stay home. If you are at work, alert your supervisor right away and go home. Read What To Do if You Are Sick\u00a0to learn more."}, {"question": "What does it mean to be in quarantine?", "answer": "Anyone who has close contact with a person with COVID-19 will need to stay away from other people for at least 14 days to see whether symptoms develop. If you are a close contact of a person with COVID-19, you should self-quarantine at home by staying in a separate room away from others. Read Caring for Yourself at Home and What To Do if You Are Sick\u00a0to learn more."}]}, {"title": "Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What do I need to know about COVID-19?", "answer": "For information on what you need to know about COVID-19, please visit What You Need to Know about COVID-19 if You are Incarcerated/Detained pdf icon[PDF \u2013 253 KB] | Spanish version pdf icon[PDF \u2013 227 KB]"}, {"question": "How can I lower the chance that I will get COVID-19?", "answer": "The best way to prevent illness is to take steps to avoid being exposed to this virus. Start by ensuring you and others around you use everyday preventive actions (such as washing hands often, avoiding touching your eyes, nose, and mouth, and covering your cough). Read How to Protect Yourself\u00a0to learn more."}, {"question": "Do I have a greater chance of getting COVID-19?", "answer": "People in correctional and detention facilities are at greater risk for some illnesses, such as COVID-19, because of close living arrangements with other people. The virus is thought to spread mainly from person-to-person, through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs or sneezes. These droplets can land in the mouths or noses of people who are nearby or be launched into the air and inhaled into someone\u2019s lungs. It is possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or eyes; however, this is not the most likely way the virus spreads."}, {"question": "What should I do if I think I may be sick with COVID-19?", "answer": "If you think you have been exposed to COVID-19\u00a0and develop a fever or symptoms of respiratory illness, such as cough or difficulty breathing, alert facility staff right away to make sure you receive medical care and protect the people around you from being exposed to the virus."}, {"question": "What does it mean to be in quarantine?", "answer": "Anyone who has close contact with a person with COVID-19 will need to stay away from other people for at least 14 days to make sure they aren\u2019t sick as well. This means that they will be placed in a room separate from others, or just with other people who have also been exposed to the same sick person. During this time, they will be checked for COVID-19 symptoms. If testing is available, a person in quarantine may be tested several times until medical staff are sure they do not have the virus."}, {"question": "Is it ok for people to visit me?", "answer": "Anyone who has had flu-like symptoms in the last 24 hours or has been in contact with someone who has or is suspected to have COVID-19 in last 14 days should not visit a correctional or detention facility. All visitors will be screened for symptoms and contact with someone with COVID-19. Staff will also perform temperature checks on all visitors. Visitors should contact the facility about their rules on visits before they travel. If a person in the facility has COVID-19, visitors may not be allowed to enter the facility. Instead, non-contact visits can be used, when possible."}]}, {"title": "Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "When I get out of prison or jail during the COVID-19 pandemic (worldwide disease outbreak), what steps should I take to protect myself and others from COVID-19?", "answer": "You may have received a COVID-19 test in prison or jail. If you test negative, you probably were not infected at the time they took your sample. The test result only means that you did not have COVID-19 at the time of testing. Also, you may have been exposed to COVID-19 between the time you were last tested and the time you got out. So, you should stay away from others (quarantine) as much as you can for 14 days after release to protect yourself and others. Visit Test for current infection.\nIf you get sick with COVID-19 during the 14 days you are staying away from others, ask for a COVID-19 test. If you do not have a doctor, contact a health center or health department. See how under the next question: \u201cAfter I get out of prison or jail, \u00a0where can I get help during the COVID-19 pandemic?\u201d\nSymptoms of COVID-19 include\n\n\nSymptoms of COVID-19\n\n\nFever/chills\nCough\nFeeling tired\nHaving a hard time breathing\nPain in the head or body\nLoss of taste or smell\nSore throat\nStuffy or runny nose\nNausea/vomiting\nDiarrhea\n\n\n\n\nDuring quarantine it is best to stay alone in a private living space, if you can, to avoid contact with other people. Ideally, your space should include your own bedroom and bathroom. Before you are released, contact friends or family to find a place to stay. If you cannot find space with family or friends, find homeless shelters in the area.\nIf you can find housing before you are released, set up a space with clothing, food, medicine, cleaning supplies, and any other items you may need while in quarantine. Get things that will help protect you and others from getting COVID-19 once you are released. Items include face masks, hand sanitizer, soap, and paper towels, or a cloth towel that only you use or that you change often. Visit COVID-19 prevention link to learn more about how to protect yourself and others.\nYou may also need other items to help you get health and social services once you get out. Before release, ask a prison or jail worker about how to get these things upon release:\n\nPrison ID card, or birth certificate or social security card\nSmall supply of your medicines\nCopy of your medical records\n\nIf you can, ask a doctor or nurse; if there is not a doctor or nurse, ask a prison or jail worker."}, {"question": "After I get out of prison or jail, where can I get help during the COVID-19 pandemic?", "answer": "The COVID-19 pandemic has changed many parts of life. For example, some stores and offices may have closed, changed their hours, or you may need to make an appointment to visit. You may want to contact offices or businesses before you visit. Court appearances may be held through video calls.\nSocial services, such as healthcare, food, and housing assistance, can support you after your release to help you adjust during the COVID-19 pandemic. Many cities have a phone line you can contact by dialing 2-1-1 or by visiting the 2-1-1 websiteexternal icon where you can also get help.\n\u00a0\nYour library or community center may offer free phone and internet, or\naccess these resources through a smart phone.\n\u00a0\nHealthcare services: You can contact your local health departmentexternal icon if you\n\nGet sick with COVID-19\nHave questions about COVID-19 and the pandemic\nNeed low-cost or free healthcare services in your area\n\nAccess to healthcare is important, especially if you are near someone with COVID-19 or get sick with COVID-19. Some health centers provide healthcare for little or no cost. Contact your local clinic to learn more about which services they offer during the COVID-19 pandemic. Check to see if you can sign up for Medicareexternal icon and/or Medicaidexternal icon to help pay for healthcare costs and services.\n\u00a0\nFood: Many people struggle to buy or find food where they live, especially during the COVID-19 pandemic. Meal sites, food banks and other services may help \u00a0you and your family during this time.\n\u00a0\nStress and coping: Being released from prison or jail can be very tough. The COVID-19 pandemic may add stress to your situation. Visit managing stress and coping during COVID-19 and How Right Now resiliencyexternal icon for help.\nGet help right away in a crisis:\n\nCall 911\nDisaster Distress Helpline: 1-800-985-5990 (press 2 for Spanish), or\ntext TalkWithUs for English or text Hablanos for Spanish to 66746\nSpanish speakers in Puerto Rico can text Hablanos to 1-787-339-2663\nNational Suicide Prevention Lifeline: 1-800-273-TALK (8255) for English,\n1-888-628-9454 for Spanish\nNational Domestic Violence Hotline: 1-800-799-7233 or text LOVEIS to 22522\nNational Child Abuse Hotline: 1-800-4AChild (1-800-422-4453) or text 1-800-422-4453\nNational Sexual Assault Hotline: 1-800-656-HOPE (4673)\n\n\u00a0\nTransportation: Getting to and from places, such as the doctor\u2019s office or clinic, can be tough. The COVID-19 pandemic may affect your local public transportation schedule or routes. If you take a bus or train, wear a face mask and stay at least 6 feet (about two arm lengths) from other people. As much as you can, try not to touch items such as handrails, credit card machines, elevator buttons, or benches. If you must touch these items, wash your hands as soon as you can for 20 seconds with soap and water, or use hand sanitizer that contains at least 60% alcohol. Visit Transportation_during_COVID19 for more information.\n\u00a0\nAccess to phones and internet: Many clinics, hospitals, counseling services, and substance use treatment providers now offer appointments through phone and video calls to protect patients from getting exposed to COVID-19. Some people may not have phone or internet services because it costs too much. For people without the internet right now, the links below are for when you do have internet.\n\u00a0\n\n\nDescription of Links\n\n\nDescription of the link \nURL\n\n\nWhat are the symptoms of COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/symptoms-testing/symptoms.html\n\n\nWhere can I find information about how to protect myself and others from COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/prevent-getting-sick/prevention.html\n\n\nHow can I get information on social services?\nCall 2-1-1.\nhttps://www.211.org/external icon\n\n\nHow do I contact the Department of Motor Vehicles (DMV) office?\nTo access health and social services, you need personal identification, or ID.\nCall 1-844-872-4681 to connect you to your local DMV officeexternal icon before you visit to know the hours of operation during the COVID-19 pandemic.\n\n\nWhere can I find a health center?\nLocal health department or federally qualified health centers: 1-800-232-4636\nCommunity Health Centers: 1-800-318-2596\nHRSA Locator: https://findahealthcenter.hrsa.gov/external icon\n\n\nWhere can I find information about Medicare?\nMedicare: 1-800-MEDICARE (1-800-633-4227)\nTTY 1-877-486-2048https://www.medicare.gov/medicare-coronavirusexternal icon\n\n\nWhere can I find information about Medicaid?\nMedicaid: 1-877-267-2323\nTTY: 1-866-226-1819\nhttps://www.medicaid.gov/medicaid/eligibility/index.htmlexternal icon\n\n\nHow can I deal with stress during COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/managing-stress-anxiety.html\nCDC Foundation site to address feelings of grief, loss, and worry during COVID-19 https://howrightnow.org/external icon\n\n\nHow can I get help for alcohol and substance use?\nStress can lead to alcohol and substance use. If you need help, including medicine for opioid use disorder such as buprenorphine or methadone, contact your local behavioral treatment centersexternal icon for help.\nNational Harm Reduction Coalition\nhttps://harmreduction.org/external icon\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/stress-coping/alcohol-use.html\nhttps://www.samhsa.gov/find-treatmentexternal icon\n\n\nIf I need help getting food resources during COVID-19, where can I go?\nHunger Hotline: 1-866-3-HUNGRY\n1-877-8-HAMBRE (for Spanish) or Text 97779 with a question that includes a keyword such as \u201cfood\u201d or \u201cmeals\u201dhttps://www.cdc.gov/nutrition/resources-publications/food-and-food-system-resources-during-covid-19-pandemic.html\n\n\nHow can I protect myself when using transportation during COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/using-transportation.html\n\n\nWhere can I find support for veterans during COVID-19, including those who need housing assistance?\nDepartment of Veteran\u2019s Affairs: 1-800-698-2411, TTY: 711\nVeteran\u2019s Crisis Line: 1-800-273-TALK (8255) or\ntext: 8388255https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/stress-coping/veterans.htmlU.S. Department of Veterans Affairs: Veterans Justice Outreach Program https://www.va.gov/homeless/vjo.aspexternal icon"}]}, {"title": "Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail : Family Members of People Who Are Incarcerated at Correctional and Detention Facilities", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html", "data": [{"question": "My family member doesn't have access to the internet. How can I provide them information on COVID-19?", "answer": "A printable resource is available at What You Need to Know about COVID-19 if You are Incarcerated/Detained pdf icon[PDF \u2013 253 KB] | Spanish version pdf icon[PDF \u2013 227 KB] that you can print and send to your family member.\u200b"}, {"question": "Do people who are incarcerated (in prison, jail, or detention facilities) have a greater chance of getting COVID-19 than others?", "answer": "Incarcerated and detained people spend almost all of their time within congregate environments where groups of people share the same space, which increases the chance for COVID-19 to spread once introduced. The virus that causes COVID-19 is thought to spread mainly from person-to-person through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs, sneezes, or talks. These droplets can land in the mouths or noses of people who are nearby or possibly be inhaled into someone\u2019s lungs. Spread is more likely when people are in close contact with one another (within about 6 feet). It is possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes; however, this is not the most likely way the virus spreads. COVID-19 may also be spread by people who are not showing symptoms. Learn more about how COVID-19 spreads."}, {"question": "What does it mean if someone I know is in quarantine?", "answer": "Anyone who has had close contact with a person with COVID-19 will need to be put into quarantine for 14 days. This means that they will be placed in a room separate from others, until staff are sure that they don\u2019t have symptoms. If symptoms develop during the 14-day period, and/or the person in quarantine tests positive for COVID-19, they should be placed under medical isolation and evaluated. If symptoms do not develop and they do not test positive for COVID-19, quarantine restrictions can be lifted, or removed, after the 14-day period ends. Quarantine procedures may differ by facility."}, {"question": "Is it ok for me to visit?", "answer": "To help protect each visitor\u2019s health and the health of staff, family members, or friends inside the facility, contact visits are discouraged during the COVID-19 pandemic. You should not visit a correctional or detention facility if you:\n\nHave had COVID-19 or COVID-19 symptoms\u00a0and have not yet met the criteria to discontinue home isolation\nHave been in contact with someone who has had COVID-19 in the last 14 days\nHave been in contact with someone who is suspected of having COVID-19 in the last 14 days\n\nPrior to a planned visit, you should make sure that visitation has not been suspended and review the facility\u2019s rules about visits. If there is someone in the facility who has COVID-19, visitors might not be allowed to enter the facility. Some facilities may arrange for non-contact visits when possible, and staff may screen and perform temperature checks on all visitors. You should also wear cloth face coverings. Wearing cloth face coverings may be difficult for people with sensory, cognitive, or behavioral issues and is not recommended for children under 2 years or anyone who has trouble breathing or is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the covering without assistance."}, {"question": "If a family member or friend is returning home soon (during the COVID-19 pandemic) from a correctional or detention facility, how should a household prepare to receive them and maintain everyone\u2019s safety?", "answer": "Depending on the steps facilities are taking and the length of stay, people released from a facility may have had screenings for COVID-19 symptoms, temperature checks, or even a test\u2014a pre-release planning process. The family member or friend may have also been offered information and resources on how to prevent COVID-19. If they were sick at the time of release, they may have been linked to community resources to make sure they follow proper medical isolation and have access to medical care.\nThere are things that family members and people who share housing can do to promote a healthy home and prevent getting sick. You\u2019re encouraged to find a room where the person can stay alone for at least 14 days and monitor their symptoms. During that time, they should limit contact with others within and outside the home, particularly people who are at higher risk\u00a0for severe illness from COVID-19 like older adults and those with underlying medical conditions. They should avoid providing care for children during this time, if possible. Friends and family should keep a distance of at least 6 feet, and everyone should consider wearing a cloth face covering, especially when going out in public. Finally, frequent handwashing, as well as cleaning and disinfecting\u00a0frequently touched surfaces, are also important.\nAdditional information is available regarding the prevention of COVID-19 for people who share a small apartment \u00a0or live in a household with large or extended families. If the person who was just released, or anyone in your household, develops symptoms or tests positive for COVID-19, please follow CDC recommendations for what to do if you become sick or have to care for someone who is sick."}]}, {"title": "Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What actions should I take to plan for an outbreak?", "answer": "Creating an emergency plan for mass gatherings and large community events, such as concerts and sporting events, can help protect the health of your staff, attendees, and the local community. This planning should include:\n\nEncouraging staff and attendees to stay home if sick.\nDeveloping flexible refund policies for attendees.\nProviding supplies for attendees and staff that can be used to help prevent the spread of germs.\nConsulting local public health officials about your event."}, {"question": "How many guests can safely attend a conference, sporting event, concert, or other community event?", "answer": "CDC does not have a limit or recommend a specific number of attendees for these types of events and instead encourages event organizers to focus on ways to limit people\u2019s contact with each other. Each event organizer will need to determine the appropriate number for their setting in collaboration with local health officials. They should also check state, county, and city rules regarding any current restrictions limiting the number of attendees at events.\nIn general, the number that is chosen should allow individuals to remain at least 6 feet apart from each other. Rather than focusing on an ideal number, event organizers and administrators should focus on the ability to reduce and limit contact between attendees, staff, and others. In general, the more people you interact with, the more closely you interact with them, and the longer that interaction, the higher your risk of getting and spreading COVID-19. Indoor spaces are more risky than outdoor spaces because indoors, it can be harder to keep people at least 6 feet apart and the ventilation is not as good as it is outdoors."}, {"question": "Does CDC have recommendations on how to maintain 6 feet between attendees during events?", "answer": "Yes. CDC recommends several strategies for this. For instance, organizers can:\n\nLimit attendance or seating capacity to allow for social distancing, or host smaller events in larger rooms.\nBlock off rows or sections of seating in order to space people at least 6 feet apart.\nUse multiple entrances and exits and discourage crowded waiting areas.\nEliminate lines or queues if possible or encourage people to stay at least 6 feet apart by providing signs or other visual cues such as tape or chalk marks.\nProvide physical guides, such as tape on floors or sidewalks and signs on walls, to ensure that individuals remain at least 6 feet apart in lines and at other times (such as guides for creating one-way routes).\nPrioritize outdoor activities where social distancing can be maintained as much as possible.\nOffer online attendance options in addition to in-person attendance to help reduce the number of attendees.\nConsider limiting the number of people who occupy the restroom at one time to allow for social distancing.\nDo not allow lines or crowds to form near the restroom. Take steps to ensure that individuals can stay at least 6 feet apart from each other."}, {"question": "Should organizers test all attendees and staff for COVID-19 before they can enter an event?", "answer": "CDC does not recommend testing all attendees and staff before allowing them to enter. Testing all event attendees and staff for COVID-19 before allowing them to enter the venue has not been systematically studied. It is unknown if entry testing at event venues provides any additional reduction in person-to-person transmission of the virus beyond what would be expected with other preventive measures (such as social distancing, wearing cloth face coverings, hand washing, enhanced cleaning and disinfection).\nCDC does recommend conducting health checks such as temperature screening and/or symptom checking of staff and attendees safely and respectfully, and in accordance with any applicable privacy laws and regulations."}, {"question": "Does CDC recommend all event attendees wear masks?", "answer": "Yes. CDC recommends that people wear masks in public settings and when around people who don\u2019t live in their household, especially when other social distancing measures are difficult to maintain. CDC recommends that organizers require staff to wear masks and encourage attendees ahead of events to bring and wear masks at the event. Masks are most essential when physical distancing is difficult (such as when moving within a crowd or audience). Masks offer some protection to the wearer and are also meant to protect those around the wearer, in case they are infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Masks are not surgical masks or respirators. They are not personal protective equipment.\nMasks are strongly encouraged in settings where individuals might raise their voices (such as shouting, chanting, singing). Provide all staff with information on proper use, removal, and washing of masks. Advise staff that masks should not be placed on:\n\nBabies or children younger than 2 years old\nAnyone who has trouble breathing\nAnyone who is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the mask without assistance"}, {"question": "What actions can staff and attendees take to prevent the spread of COVID-19?", "answer": "Encourage staff and attendees to take everyday preventive actions\u00a0to help prevent the spread of respiratory illnesses, such as COVID-19. This includes:\n\nCleaning your hands often.\nAvoiding close contact\u00a0with people who are sick.\nStaying home when you are sick.\nCovering coughs and sneezes with a tissue or the inside of your elbow.\nCleaning and disinfecting frequently touched surfaces.\nUsing a mask in public, especially when it may be difficult to maintain a distance of at least six feet from other people."}, {"question": "How should staff clean the facility before and during the event to limit spread of the virus?", "answer": "Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may also weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. Cleaning high touch surfaces and shared objects once a day is usually enough to sufficiently remove virus that may be on surfaces unless someone with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 has been in your facility. For more information on cleaning your facility regularly and cleaning your facility when someone is sick, see Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Facility"}, {"question": "What are things to consider when determining if an event needs to be postponed or canceled?", "answer": "Consult with local public health officials and continually assess, based on current conditions, whether to postpone, cancel, or significantly reduce the number of attendees (if possible) at an event or gathering. When determining if you should postpone or cancel a large gathering or event, consider the:\n\nOverall number of attendees or crowd size.\nNumber of attendees who are at higher risk of developing serious illness from COVID-19. This includes older adults and people with underlying health problems such as lung or heart disease and diabetes.\nHow close together attendees will be at the event.\nAmount of spread in local community and the communities from where your attendees are likely to travel.\nNeeds and capacity of the local community to host or participate in your event."}, {"question": "Is there information I can share with staff and attendees about COVID-19?", "answer": "Share these resources to help people understand COVID-19 and steps they can take to help protect themselves:\n\nPrevention and Treatment\nWhat to Do If You Are Sick\nGroups at Higher Risk\nFAQs: Pregnant People and COVID-19\nFAQs: Coronavirus Disease-2019 (COVID-19) and Children\nHandwashing: A Family Activity\nHandwashing: Clean Hands Save Lives\nConsiderations for Restaurants and Bars\nConsiderations for Animal Activities at Fairs, Shows, and Other Events"}]}, {"title": "Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness : Confirmed case of COVID-19 at an event", "url": "https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html", "data": [{"question": "What steps should I take if an attendee or staff person develops symptoms of COVID-19 while at the event?", "answer": "If a staff member or attendee becomes sick at your event, separate them from others as soon as possible and until they can go home. Provide them with clean, disposable facemaskspdf iconpdf icon\u00a0to wear, if available. If not available, provide them with a cloth face covering, which can be improvised if needed from a tee shirt, bandana or other clothing, as well as a tissue or some other way to cover their coughs and sneezes. If needed, contact emergency services for those who need emergency care. Public transportation, shared rides, and taxis should be avoided for sick persons. Be sure to contact local public health officials regarding the possible case of COVID-19 at your event and how to communicate with staff and attendees about possible exposure to the virus. Read more about preventing the spread of COVID-19 if someone is sick."}, {"question": "What is the best way to clean and disinfect the event space after a confirmed case of COVID-19 at my event?", "answer": "CDC has guidance for cleaning and disinfecting rooms and areas where a person with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 has visited. See Environmental Cleaning and Disinfection Recommendations."}]}]